<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ancient bounds, or Liberty of conscience tenderly stated, modestly asserted, and mildly vindicated.</title>
            <author>Rous, Francis, 1579-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E287_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860891</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860891</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158553</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92007)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158553)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E287[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ancient bounds, or Liberty of conscience tenderly stated, modestly asserted, and mildly vindicated.</title>
                  <author>Rous, Francis, 1579-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Henry Overton, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed and entred according to order."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Francis Rous the elder by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 10th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158553:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The ancient Bounds, <hi>OR</hi> Liberty of Conſcience, TENDERLY STATED, MODESTLY ASSERTED, AND MILDLY VINDICATED.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 10.15.</hi>
               </bibl> I ſpeake as to wiſe men, judge yee what I ſay.</q>
            <q>Quid jam nobis ulterius relinquitur, ſi etiam hoc quod voluntate fieri oportet libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do extorquet aliena? <bibl>Lactan. lib. 5. Inſtit. cap. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Etiamſi Magiſtratus Legum ſuarum Regulis ſubditos ſuos, Coercere debeat ne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioni quam approbat, apertè maledicant, Cogere eos tamen non poteſt ad fidem qua iſtam receptae Religionis formam approbent. Fides enim perſuaderi vult non Cogi, ae nihil tam voluntarium eſſe debet ac Religio, nihil à Magiſtratu Chriſtiano magis alienum, quàm praepoſtera ſeveritas quae homines hypocritas reddat, ecoſque ore Confiteri Cogat, quod corde non Credant.<bibl>Prof. Leid. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſ. pag. 767.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Popes-head Alley.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:158553:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:158553:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S is the fining pot to ſilver,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>ſo is a man to his praiſe;</hi> and (to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date onely the moralitie of this ſentence to my purpoſe) ſo is a Booke to its title. Wherefore leſt I be thought to praevaricate by prefixing either an improper or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or in ſignificant title to this Booke, not holding forth ſufficiently the nature of the Diſcourſe, which (as may be early deſcryed) is partly of the Magiſtrates duty as well as of Conſciences liberty: It appeares needfull to advertiſe the courteous Reader, that this Diſcourſe was intended primarily (as to its ultimate and adaequate ſcope) onely in the nature of a Plea for the <hi>Liberty of tender Conſciences;</hi> and meerly in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereto, (the condition of the Argument devolving it thither) it comes to have (what it hath) to doe with the Magiſtrate; otherwiſe power and intereſt (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when ſo eminently ſubjected) are render and delicate things; and our Saviours ſpeech of <hi>John</hi> may be applyed thereto, among all Arguments of this low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Region that are handled, there is not a greater then
<pb facs="tcp:158553:3"/>this; though the leaſt in that higher ſpheare of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall truthes (which God is not jealous of our prying into, and being familiar with in a holy way) is greater then it. But ſure it cannot be unacceptable either to the wiſe and <hi>judicious</hi> (Magiſtrates, or others) that count not <hi>names</hi> of honour a valuable conſideration, for <hi>loads</hi> of trouble, or to the <hi>Conſcientious,</hi> that looke to the <hi>work</hi> more then the <hi>title</hi> to apologize in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Magiſtrates behalfe, to exempt or excuſe him from the publique determining Cognizance of differences in Religion (though this by the way onely) and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion therof with the ſword, as whereby, if it prove not to be a meanes ſeparated and anointed by God to ſuch an end, he ſhall onely be ſure unneceſſarily to contract debt and ſin upon himſelf. Yet not that I would tempt the Magiſtrate to any thing, whereby he might incurre the ſcandall of Scepticknes and indifferency in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or limit him from lifting up the head of his owne avowed way (above others which he apprehends in ſome things alien from the truth) by a more eminent countenancing and ample endowment thereof with priviledges of maintenance, &amp;c. (for as He ſays; <hi>As is the man, ſo is his might;</hi> and ſo let his Religion be for outward accommodations;) or that I would indulge or comply with ſuch an unreaſonable expectation in any materially differing Party to ſtand upon equall termes of outward advantage, and to glory equally (with the moſt received way) in outward Priviledges of publiqueneſſe and publique maintenance (which are but Civill and ſecular things, and the Magiſtrates own that he may doe with what he will, and the truth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends not upon them:) for I waſh my hands of theſe in the ſixth particular of the ſecond Chapter; where as in other parts of the diſcourſe may be ſeene as well
<pb facs="tcp:158553:3"/>what I aske, as what I am far from asking. And this I deſire may be carried along and ſupplyed through the whole diſcourſe, and each particular therein; and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſſage or inſtance upon particular reaſon ſpeake higher, to bee reſtrained hereby and taken downe (which is no fault in an Inſtance to need it) to a <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſon</hi> with the poſtulation of this Diſcourſe, made upon grounds of Morall and Univerſall Reaſon and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>I have but a word more, and I have done; Let it not ſeeme an unreaſonable requeſt to be beleeved, that what I have here attempted, (as it is not carried with any ſuch reflexion, ſo it) was not bred with any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatory reſpect in my heart unto thoſe inventions which now like tares ſpring up with the wheat, and wherein many Saints are involved; but what is ſpoken is (1) in favour of the <hi>perſons</hi> that differ, not of their <hi>errours,</hi> for I would pleaſe my Brother, but to his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification;</hi> and while I carry his perſon before the Lord with love in my prayers, I deſire to carry his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours with complaints. (2) To take men off from the wrong way of oppoſing errours, which will be as fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as 'tis faithleſs, that they may apply themſelves to the uſe of the right meanes, as ſure as ſafe, the Word of God, which requires this Libertie (but accidentally onely ſerving to errours) for 'its better operation, as Phyſick doth require open weather, when the humors are ſtirring, not clung up nor reſtrained, for to purge them away. I ſhall not be offended nor count it ſtrange to heare of much weakneſſe and many failings in the handling of this Argument (which by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this proportion, being ſo early driven to my Apology, I may well expect to be multiplyed through the Diſcourſe) but I beg but that charitie to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb facs="tcp:158553:4"/>that could I foreſee them, I ſhould prevent them with an amendment, or Apologize for them particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly as for this: whereas now all I can doe is to crave a generall pardon. Many <hi>Ahimaazes,</hi> which I call not ſo for impertinentneſſe, for they are before me, but for latterneſſe of ſetting out, have over-run me, who was ready more then ſix moneths ſince: and what ſimilitude of Notions I have with others, is not (I may cleare my ſelfe and the matter herein) by any furtive extraction out of them; (though I am a debtor to them all, and the leaſt of them may adde to me who am leaſt of all) but through the onenes of Truth. And as I have been preſt in ſpirit, and ſerv'd with an opportunitie of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy from ſome other buſineſſe to the vindicating of this Truth; ſo in the bearing it forth, I have no leſſe ſtrangely to my ſelfe, (if ſo ſafely, and that it appeare ſo to others) obſerved a ſpeciall conduct leading me all along contrary to thoſe prae-engagements (ſuch as they were) upon my judgement, who had dipt my pen on the other ſide; I ſay, I have been no leſſe ſtrangely led, then the milch Kine that did beare the Arke out of the Land of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> taking the ſtraight way to <hi>Bethſhemeſh,</hi> the inſtinct of <hi>Providence</hi> ſuperſeding the inſtinct of <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:158553:4"/>
            <head>The Series, and Titles of the Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Sect. 1.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter 1.</hi> The State of the Queſtion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> An appendix to the State of the Queſtion, clearing the Principles of this Book from diſcharging or diſcouraging the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, to improve his authoritie for the Lord Jeſus, his truth, and people.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> Coercive power (as before ſtated) diſputed againſt by a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> taken from the Conſent of all Presbyterian Authors (though alſo the Medium be proved by the Authors <hi>own reaſons) viz.</hi> that the Magiſtrate hath not the Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of differences in matters of Religion, in the ſenſe that is expreſſed in the Chapter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Coercive power more directly impugned.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> The Cognizance aforeſaid, and Coercive power, both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppoſed: and theſe three Chapters bitherto are with ſpeciall Relation to the Magiſtrate, if he exerciſe it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Againſt all Coercive power, exerciſed by whomſoever for the forementioned matters in Chap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Sect. 2.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> The Argument Illuſtrated and Confirmed by Examples and Teſtimonies; and firſt out of the old Teſtament.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> By Examples and Teſtimonies out of the New.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> By ſome few fragments of Examples and Teſtimonies out of humane Story.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Sect. 3.</head>
               <item>Chap. 10. Objections againſt the premiſſes anſwered.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:158553:5"/>
            <head>A light to the Work.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two things contended for in this liberty of Conſcience; Firſt, to <hi>inſtate</hi> every Chriſtian in his <hi>right</hi> of <hi>free</hi> (yet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt) <hi>judging</hi> and accepting what he holds. Secondly, To <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate a neceſſary advantage</hi> to the truth; and this is the maine end and reſpect of this liberty. I contend not for variety of opinions, I know there is but one truth; But this truth cannot be ſo eaſily brought forth without this liberty; and a generall reſtraint, though intended but for errours, yet through the unskilfulneſſe of men, may fall upon the truth; and better many errours of ſome kinde ſuffered, then one uſefull truth be obſtructed or deſtroyed. Beſides, truth would not oftentimes be ſuffered in the world, if it went not diſguiſed, and if there were not other things like the truth, therefore this liberty is neceſſary alſo to its preſervation, (as well as production) as it is for a Prince or Generall when he fights to diſguiſe himſelfe, and habit himſelfe like one of his Souldiers, elſe all would lay at him, and <hi>fight with neither ſmall nor great</hi> but him. When Chriſt was to be borne, all the world was to be quiet, and it was ſo, though immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after there was a cruell ſlaughter; and then if other infants had not been like Chriſt, and Chriſt like other infants, he would have been ſingled out and ſlaine; So that as errours muſt be, that thoſe that are approved may be made manifeſt to God and ſpirituall men, ſo errours muſt be that the truth and the profeſſors of it may be tryed, and ſometimes alſo covered from the world, from their diſdaine which lights upon common and obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things; and from their Odium, that it may be divided and diſtracted, and may ſpend and wast it ſelfe againſt other things then the truth; and ſo <hi>the earth helpes the woman,</hi> and ſwallowes up the floud that is powred out againſt the truth. <hi>Moſes</hi> permitted divorce to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> notwithſtanding the hardneſſe of their hearts; ſo muſt this libertie be granted to men (within certain bounds) though it may be abuſed to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton opinions more then were to be wiſhed.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158553:5"/>
            <head>THE ANCIENT BOUNDS, <hi>OR</hi> LIBERTY OF CONSCIENCE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The State of the Queſtion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſt Jeſus, whoſe is the Kingdome, the power, and the glory, both in <hi>Nature</hi> and in <hi>grace,</hi> hath given ſeverall Maps and Scheames of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions gradually differing, ſome greater, ſome leſſer, of all ſorts and ſizes: Both of his <hi>great Kingdome</hi> the world, his Dominions at large, which he hath committed to men, to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in <hi>truth and righteouſneſſe,</hi> in a various forme as they pleaſe; each of which he cloaths himſelfe withall: And alſo of his <hi>ſpeciall</hi> and peculiar Kingdome the kingdome of Grace. Which kingdomes though they differ <hi>eſſentially,</hi> or formally, yet they agree in one common <hi>ſubject matter</hi> (man, and ſocieties of men) though under a <hi>diverſe</hi> conſideration: And not onely man in ſociety, but <hi>every</hi> man individually is an <hi>Epitome,</hi> either of one onely, or of both theſe Dominions. <hi>Of one onely,</hi> ſo every naturall man (who in a naturall conſideration is called <hi>Microcoſmus,</hi> an Epitome of the world) in whoſe <hi>Conſcience</hi> God hath his <hi>throne,</hi> ruling him by the light of <hi>nature</hi> to a Civill outward good and end.</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>both,</hi> ſo every beleever who beſides this naturall conſcience and rule, hath an <hi>inlightned</hi> conſcience, carrying a more bright and lively ſtampe of the Kingly place and power of the Lord Jeſus, ſwaying him by the light of <hi>faith</hi> or Scripture: and ſuch a man may be called <hi>Microchriſtus,</hi> the Epitome of Chriſt myſticall.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:158553:6"/>
                  <p>This is conſcience, and this its diviſion. And of this conſcience is the Queſtion, or rather of the <hi>perſon</hi> that hath this conſcience, and the <hi>things</hi> he holds or practiſes conſcientiouſly; For the <hi>power</hi> of conſcience it ſelfe, as it will not be beholden to any man for its liberty, ſo neither is it capable of outward reſtraint, they muſt be morall or ſpirituall inſtruments that can worke upon conſcience. But the exerciſe or practice of conſcience, or the perſon ſo exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, is properly the object of outward reſtraint in queſtion.</p>
                  <p>Now then if we keep but to this terme <hi>Conſcience;</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt all vitious &amp; ſcandalous practices, contrary to the light of nature, or manifeſt good of ſocieties, are cut off, not to trouble us in this matter, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving themſelves not from <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but a malignant <hi>will</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcienc't ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Nor yet may all principles that derive themſelves from <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> have the benefit of this plea of Liberty, ſo as to ſave their ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; as firſt, if they ſhall be found of a <hi>diſabling</hi> nature, or <hi>want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in their due proportion of benevolence to publique peace, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſocieties; as in ſome of thoſe caſes inſtanced by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Palmer;</hi> as for inſtance, Scruple of conſcience cannot exempt a man from any <hi>Civill</hi> duty he owes to the State, or the government thereof, but it may well beſeeme a State to force men to contribute to their own, and the publique good and ſafety: And though <hi>God</hi> can have no glory by a forced Religion, yet the State may have benefit by a forced ſervice. Again, the ſervice of the State is <hi>outward,</hi> civill, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and is perfect as to its end, <hi>without</hi> the will and conſcience of that perſon from whom it is extorted; ſo is not the ſervice of God, which is inward and ſpirituall, yea it muſt be <hi>in ſpirit and in truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Then much leſſe may any ſuch Principles find favour in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as beſides the former deficiency ſhall be found pregnant, with <hi>poſitive</hi> malignity (and that in a high nature and conſequence too perhaps) to ſocieties, as the doctrines of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not of theſe Principles that are either of the <hi>frigid</hi> Zone of deficiency, or the <hi>torrid</hi> Zone of malignancy, but of conſcientious Principles and practices, though perhaps erroneous, yet not inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to publique good either way.</p>
                  <p>And of Principles thus allayd and qualified,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the Queſtion is not whether there be not <hi>a</hi> power to deale with them, and <hi>a</hi> force to be applyed to them; yea to conſcience it ſelfe, the ſource of <hi>them;</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:158553:6"/>for wee all agree in this, that there is, viz. <hi>Chriſts</hi> power, and <hi>a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> force; but the Queſtion is, whether <hi>outward</hi> force be to be applyed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And in this the Queſtion is not inſtituted in grudge or envy of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> Whether it be lawfull for him <hi>ſpecially,</hi> much leſſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be <hi>leſſe</hi> lawfull for him then for <hi>ſome other</hi> men, or generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men, to force in theſe matters: but whether it be lawfull for <hi>any</hi> man, or kinde of men indifferently. And therefore though there be ſome arguments applyed <hi>particularly</hi> to the Magiſtrate, in the third, fourth, and fifth Chapters; yet there are far <hi>more</hi> againſt force in <hi>generall,</hi> Chap. 6. and from thence the greateſt part of the diſcourſe is carried generally and indefinitely.</p>
                  <p>Yet neither in theſe is the Queſtion,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Whether the Chriſtian Magiſtrates power doe or <hi>may</hi> beare <hi>any</hi> proportion of <hi>ſubſerviency</hi> to a worke of publique Reformation, and whether he cannot doe more then another man towards it. Wee freely grant he may doe much more, and therefore ought; as the next Chapter will ſhew, which is added as an Appendix unto this; but the Queſtion is, Whether to other meanes he may <hi>adde</hi> force.</p>
                  <p>Nor will it ſeeme unrighteous in our eyes,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> that a <hi>difference</hi> ſhould be made by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate (as by every man in his place) between <hi>men</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> according as they judge them to be in truth or error (eſpecially in <hi>equall</hi> and <hi>ſetled</hi> times, wherein <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>humanitie,</hi> in reſpect of their brethrens <hi>neceſſities</hi> and <hi>ſufferings,</hi> not onely <hi>with</hi> them, but <hi>for</hi> them, ſhall not otherwiſe require) as is more largely expreſſed before to the Reader. So that this difference be but by <hi>withholding</hi> their own <hi>favours,</hi> and not by taking <hi>away</hi> their Brethrens <hi>rights,</hi> and that it be alſo but in a <hi>due</hi> proportion, to the demerit of their difference, diſcerning between the <hi>greater</hi> and <hi>leſſer,</hi> between diſputable and manifeſt errours, I meane mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to the light of the godly and judicious generally. For certainly in thoſe things which are even by the principles of the <hi>powerfull</hi> ſide themſelves, remote from the <hi>vitalls</hi> and <hi>fundamentalls</hi> of Religion, and of a <hi>very controverſall</hi> nature: for theſe, I ſay, (reſerving the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall</hi> liberty of every mans judgement to judge thereof as he finds) there is none or very ſmall difference outward, juſtly to be made by the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> or power of a State; but if <hi>honour</hi> be to be given <hi>to whom honour is due,</hi> and they that <hi>doe well</hi> are by the Magiſtrate to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:158553:7"/>be
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.14.</note> 
                     <hi>praiſed, (i.)</hi> countenanced, authorized, and rewarded, then if any whit of a juſt proportion be obſerved, and no more praiſe and honour be detracted from ſuch brethren, then the demerit of their difference cals for, I hope they ſhall neither be put to <hi>fly</hi> for feare, or <hi>dye</hi> through want.</p>
                  <p>Nor doe we queſtion,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> whether the Magiſtrate may not to this <hi>negative</hi> diſcountenance, adde <hi>poſitive,</hi> viz. to declare againſt errors, as well as the Miniſters to convince and exhort againſt them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Nor whether (among us) errors of manifeſt ſcandall and danger to mens ſoules and conſciences, as <hi>Arrianiſme, Socinianiſme, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſme, &amp;c.</hi> ought not to be reſtrained by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, and the Aſſertors and maintainers of them, interdicted under pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, the divulging or ſpreading of them by publique preaching or printing. For though God alone can convince and reduce <hi>their</hi> conſciences; yet to preſerve the <hi>acknowledged</hi> truth from being <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed,</hi> and the conſciences of <hi>others</hi> yet free and disingaged from being <hi>ſcandalized</hi> and <hi>corrupted,</hi> is a work of <hi>love</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> which the Magiſtrates <hi>arme</hi> is requiſite, and muſt extend it ſelfe unto, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed alone bearing ſufficient proportion to ſuch a ſervice, as the preventing occaſions and removing ſtumbling-blocks of ſuch like temptations out of the way, which the ſecular power can doe, though the
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.27.</note> 
                     <hi>anoynting</hi> of the Spirit muſt preſerve their conſciences inwardly, and enable them upon all occaſions to <hi>diſcerne between things that differ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Laſtly (though we cannot likely be miſtaken) wee doe declare that ſuch liberty as we plead for in the caſes ſpecified, is not by us, nor ought to be by any reputed as a <hi>vindication,</hi> juſtification, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or eſtabliſhment of any opinion or way ſo tolerated, (as no fin nor error, as the truth and Orthodox) as ſome may poſſibly think; eſpecially, if they be uſed ſo lightly to diſcharge their <hi>owne</hi> reſpects and countenance to the truth they profeſſe and avow, as counting it almoſt enough <hi>to doe nothing againſt it:</hi> Whereas did they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their duty to the truth, and fulfill it, they would ſee a great doore of <hi>negative</hi> diſcountenance opened to them againſt errours, whereby they might put a <hi>broad</hi> difference between them and the truth they embrace, (even as if lively communion of Churches were known, non-communion would appeare a terrible thing) though a negative diſcountenance be not all that wee allow in ſome caſes:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158553:7"/>But by this liberty wee onely <hi>referre</hi> mens conſciences to God to be convinced in his time, not ceaſing to uſe all <hi>proper</hi> meanes in the meane time: And this onely in thoſe things that pertaine <hi>onely</hi> to conſcience, making onely the ſtate <hi>thereof</hi> good or bad towards <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II. Being an appendix to the ſtate of the Queſtion. <hi>Of the Relation that the Chriſtian Magiſtrates office beares to the Church, and matters of Religion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruth requires that we ſhew how far wee <hi>agree,</hi> as well as wherein we differ. Though it be eaſier to ſay what the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may <hi>not</hi> do, then what he may: We are never more out, then when we goe about to make <hi>formes</hi> and <hi>ſyſtemes,</hi> and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitive comprehenſive <hi>Doctors</hi> of that which we muſt be <hi>learners</hi> &amp; proficients in all our life time. Eſpecially in things of this nature, which may better be perceived &amp; diſcerned <hi>upon occaſion</hi> from time to time, by the humble and godly, then digeſted into a few Rules or <hi>Canons.</hi> This premiſed we acknowledge that the duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrate is ſomewhat more then of another Magiſtrate. <hi>Civill protection</hi> is that which all Magiſtrates owe, whether Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an or not Chriſtian, to all <hi>quiet livers</hi> within their Dominions, whether Chriſtian or not Chriſtian, as being founded upon ſuch <hi>politique</hi> conſiderations and conditions (ſetting aſide Religion) as being performed on the Subjects part, it cannot with juſtice be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied them. But a Chriſtian Magiſtrate owes ſomething more to the truth he profeſſes, and to thoſe that profeſſe the ſame with him; which duty of his differs onely in <hi>degree,</hi> not in <hi>kinde</hi> from the duty of another Chriſtian that is no Magiſtrate. For it is the duty of <hi>every Chriſtian,</hi> to improve every talent and advantage entruſted with him, for the honour of Chriſt, and good of the body to the utmoſt, in a lawfull way. So a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, if he have (as he hath) by vertue of his Magiſtracy a talent and advantage above other men, he is bound to improve it all lawfull wayes, to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid purpoſe. To which he is to direct even all the common acts and parts of his government; for though all doe equally ſhare in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158553:8"/>the outward benefits of Magiſtracy, <hi>viz.</hi> peace and plenty, &amp;c. yet ought Chriſtian Magiſtrates principally <hi>ex intentione</hi> to direct their whole government to the good of the <hi>Churches,</hi> and the glory of <hi>God</hi> therein; for as much as <hi>all things are the Churches,</hi> and for the <hi>Churches.</hi> And doubtleſſe, Magiſtracy, though an Ordinance of man, yet is a moſt glorious Ordinance, and of ſingular uſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, if rightly applyed to the Church; as I ſhall ſhew gradually in theſe ſteps.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,
<note n="1" place="margin">Morality is within his Cognizance.</note> Magiſtrates doe <hi>prepare</hi> by a good Government for the Goſpel; Civility not reſted in, nor miſtaken for godlineſſe, makes men in a more proximious outward capacity for, and diſpoſition towards Religion, in as much as they are thereby reſtrained from groſſe prophaneneſſe, and inſolent oppoſition of the truth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Word may come amongſt them with ſafety to the perſons of thoſe that bring it; according to which part, <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayes well; That the Magiſtrate helps the Miniſtry, <hi>viz.</hi> by taking cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of all morall vices, and it is their part not to commend one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but to <hi>command</hi> a good morall converſation of their Subjects, at leaſt <hi>negative:</hi> In which caſe again <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſays well; That good Princes make vertue eaſie, while they both urge it with their example, and drive men to it by feare and puniſhments.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>now</hi> for <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> gifts, as <hi>illumination,</hi> ſpeciall or common, to make a man of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> judgement or opinion; or <hi>faith,</hi> to make a man of this or that <hi>practiſe</hi> in Religion, may not be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Civill ſword; it may be perſwaded, induced by exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, example, or ſuch meanes, and that's all. And ſo <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in purſuance of his former ſentence, namely, the aſſiſtance that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy contributes to the Miniſtry, hath theſe words; <hi>For wee</hi> (ſays he) <hi>teach men loyalty, chaſtity, modeſty, and dehort them from murder, falſe-witneſſe-bearing, adultery, thefts, but the Magiſtrate takes cognizance of them at his tribunall.</hi> And <hi>Origen</hi> in like manner ſeemes to make this the adaequate object of the Magiſtrates compulſive power, upon that place, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and us, to lay no other burden upon you, &amp;c.</hi> But if they will not charge them with more precepts, doe they give them liberty to murders, thefts, perjuries, luſt, adultery? in no wiſe, but of theſe there was no need to ſay any thing; for they are within the Magiſtrates cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, and prohibited by the Civill Lawes. And by the way, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158553:8"/>hath it the denomination or diſtinction of <hi>Civill power,</hi> but that <hi>(ex vi vocis)</hi> Civility is the next, moſt proper, immediate, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt utmoſt care and extent of this power? For though the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrate well diſcharging his place, doth promote the <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> good and edification of the Churches, yet not <hi>immediately</hi> and directly, but by and through a <hi>politique</hi> good, as he procures reſt and ſafety to them, and ſo they are edified, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.31. Which is a very conſiderable and needfull ſervice, while the publique worſhip and the Churches in the exerciſe thereof (though according to their being and beauty in the Spirit, they tranſcend the underſtanding and principles of the world, yet) are circumſtanced &amp; <hi>habited</hi> with ſuch outward relations and conſiderations as need ſuch a <hi>worldly</hi> proviſion, which Magiſtracy applying it ſelfe unto God, hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (by the rule of proportion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.23. whereby the leſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable parts have more honour given them) provided a <hi>more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant</hi> worldly honour for the Magiſtrate (then for Eccleſiaſticall Officers) for their <hi>worke</hi> ſake. And is not here a great deale of work, and enough to take up a whole man, and may not very acceptable ſervice be done to God herein, and much good redound to the Church, while not onely the Church hath hereby fairer quarter in the world, but a rude preparation is made for the Goſpel?</p>
                  <p>Thus wee have committed to the Magiſtrate the charge of the <hi>ſecond Table; viz.</hi> Materially, that is,
<note n="2" place="margin">The firſt Table how farre.</note> he is not to ſee God diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by the manifeſt breach thereof, or any part thereof; But is that all? No ſurely; He may enter the vault even of thoſe abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>firſt Table,</hi> and ferret the <hi>Devils</hi> and Devil-worſhip out of their holes and dennes, ſo far as <hi>Nature</hi> carries the candle before him: Therefore it ſeemes to me that <hi>Polutheiſme</hi> and <hi>Atheiſticall doctrines,</hi> which are ſins againſt the <hi>firſt Table</hi> and Commandement; and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> (which is againſt the ſecond Commandement) ſuch as may be convinced by naturall light, (or the letter of the command where the Scriptures are received) as the worſhipping of <hi>Images,</hi> and the <hi>breaden-god,</hi> the groſſeſt Idolatry of all; theſe ſo far forth as they <hi>breake out</hi> and diſcover themſelves, ought to be reſtrained, exploded by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate; for 'tis that which a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> light ſhould not tolerate, nature carrying ſo far; <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. and alſo <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> which is againſt the third Commandement, and is a common nuſance to <hi>man-kind;</hi> and the inſolent prophanation of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158553:9"/>the Lords day (though the keeping of it be not obvious to Natures light) ought not to be ſuffered by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate; for herein (as in the former) no mans <hi>liberty</hi> is infringed, no mans <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> inthrall'd, <hi>truth</hi> not at all prejudiced or obſtructed, while onely <hi>manifeſt</hi> impiety and prophaneneſſe is excluded, and the <hi>peace</hi> of thoſe that are better diſpoſed procured, and <hi>ſcandall</hi> avoyded by theſe <hi>Negatives.</hi> And thus farre the Magiſtrate is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque tabulae,</hi> not to require the <hi>Poſitive</hi> ſo much, as to reſtraine the <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;</hi> and all this <hi>Nature</hi> teaches hitherto.</p>
                  <p>But thirdly,
<note n="3" place="margin">Generally received Principles.</note> as belonging to the <hi>third</hi> Commandement, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrate may, not onely require a converſation and practiſe moralized according to the Principles and light of Nature, where they run <hi>loweſt,</hi> as among the <hi>Heathen;</hi> but as they are <hi>improved</hi> and raiſed by the Goſpel, through the common irradiation thereof: For <hi>Conſuetudo eſt altera natura,</hi> Cuſtome or Education is another nature. And look what notions fall upon <hi>every</hi> underſtanding, that is <hi>ſo</hi> ſituated, or look what impreſſions are made upon <hi>every</hi> natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſcience by the Goſpel, which <hi>ripens</hi> and meliorates nature in ſome degree, and hath at leaſt <hi>ſome</hi> fruit and ſucceſſe where ever it comes, though it do not change and ſanctifie: I ſay theſe fruits, <hi>tales quales,</hi> the Magiſtrate is Gods Titheman or Officer to gather them in for him, and to require a demeanor ſuitable to ſuch an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged light, at leaſt <hi>negatively,</hi> that is, to reſtraine the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that ſo the <hi>name of God be not taken in vaine.</hi> As to inſtance, though it be not eruable by the light of Nature, the article of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> or the <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>Office</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, yet ſure to teach do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that denies either of theſe, where the Goſpel hath ſounded, is not tolerable; Or to deny the Reſurrection, or a Judgement day, &amp;c. I ſay, the Chriſtian Magiſtrate ought not to tolerate the teaching of ſuch Contradictions (in an inſtructed Common-wealth) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Principles and manifeſt impreſſions upon all hearts that have lived under the Goſpell within his Dominions. And the reaſon is, Becauſe theſe Principles fall into the <hi>ſame</hi> rank and order and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration with
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.14.</note> naturall Principles, in as much as they are not onely habituated unto men as naturall, but <hi>atteſted</hi> unto within by a <hi>divinely</hi>-impreſt Conſcience, though but naturall and in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way. And although in treating hereof, I have reflected much upon the <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>light of Nature,</hi> and the <hi>outward</hi> good and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158553:9"/>
                     <hi>conſiſting of ſocieties,</hi> yet I make not theſe the <hi>onely grounds,</hi> authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the Magiſtrate that is <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (of whom this Chapter ſpeaks) to the premiſes, nor the <hi>ultimate end</hi> &amp; ſcope he is to ayme at there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For though the light of Nature be <hi>Gods Law</hi> in the hearts of men, not to be <hi>violated,</hi> and the preſervation of ſocieties one end thereof, not to be <hi>deſpiſed;</hi> yet certainly the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrate, as he hath his authority from God, ſo he is to take the <hi>Riſe</hi> of exerciſing it from him <hi>who hath not committed to him the ſword in vaine;</hi> and he is to ayme at the <hi>glory of God</hi> (the preventing or redreſſing his diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) in every act thereof, and to puniſh evill out of that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that it is <hi>evill:</hi> though God hath given him that <hi>Rule</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by, and to <hi>make out</hi> the evill of evill to the world, even the <hi>contrariety</hi> thereof to the <hi>light of Nature, and the good of Societies.</hi> Wherein alſo God hath admirably ſhewed his wiſdome and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, both in twiſting and combining ſo the intereſts of <hi>his glory,</hi> (in this ſenſe we ſpeake which is <hi>negative</hi>) and the <hi>happineſſe of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties,</hi> that this <hi>latter</hi> cannot be without the <hi>former:</hi> and in laying no other burthen on the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrate for the <hi>Materiale,</hi> then what is within <hi>every</hi> mans Cognizance, and the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will lead him to. And though (as is ſaid in effect already) we make not the light of Nature, and the conſiſting of ſocieties, the <hi>onely,</hi> nor <hi>higheſt</hi> conſiderations, which the Magiſtrate as a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is to hold forth before God, and into which he is to reſolve his act, (I ſay as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> though as a Magiſtrate he ought to hold out theſe Principles to the world, and <hi>build</hi> upon them; but as a Chriſtian he is bound certainly (as every <hi>man</hi>) to make every ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice as <hi>ſavoury</hi> as may be, grafting them with the <hi>beſt</hi> Principles) yet certainly, they may very well be <hi>Harmonicall</hi> reaſons, and <hi>additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> inforcements, even to him that is a Chriſtian, when the <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riale</hi> of his duty is no other then what may be convinced and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the light and principles of Nature, either (<hi>Prima</hi> or <hi>à primis orta</hi>) and is but the <hi>old</hi> Commandement; though if he be a <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> it is a <hi>new</hi> Commandement to him, and according to the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male</hi> is diſtinguiſhed eſſentially from the act of a wiſe and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Heathen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly,
<note n="4" place="margin">The exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall peace and order of the Churches.</note> The Chriſtian Magiſtrate owes a duty about the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall peace and order</hi> of the Churches to look to that; For though the Magiſtrate take not Cognizance of ſeverall forms and opinions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158553:10"/>in Religion, yet of the outward manner and order he doth, and ought, and to bound and rectifie that is his place, and to puniſh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and all this (what ever noiſe it makes) is but a <hi>Civill</hi> thing. For there are theſe two things goe to Religion; The thing it ſelfe, and the <hi>managing</hi> of it; Though conſcience is not to be forced to or from the thing, yet the manner of the practiſe is to be regulated according to <hi>peace and comelineſſe</hi> by the Civill Magiſtrate.</p>
                  <p>But all this yet is but extrinſecall to Religion;
<note n="5" place="margin">All meanes and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for the promoting of the truth on this ſide of forcing.</note> may the Chriſtian Magiſtrate come no nearer? Yes doubtleſſe, he may and ought to doe all that he is <hi>able</hi> and hath opportunitie to do in the behalfe of the truth, ſo that he keep on this ſide of force; as for inſtance, He ought to be <hi>Exemplary</hi> in the profeſſion of the truth, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> was, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.15. <hi>As for me and my houſe, wee will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Wherein (as alſo in his Exhortation of the people) he is without all ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple imitable by all in eminent place or authority, though the faith of their Subjects or Tenants is not to be pind upon <hi>their</hi> ſleeve, yet if their example, countenance, intereſt, exhortations will gaine any credit to the truth, it is an honeſt way to make uſe thereof. Nay, if God hath given them <hi>parts</hi> to contend for the truth, and ſtop the mouthes of gain-ſayers, they ought to uſe them, by writing or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, as their Charge will give them leave. They may and ought to propoſe the truth to all, to apply meanes for the reclaiming of thoſe that erre, and to ſend forth Teachers into blind and ignorant places, where they are not capable of the care of their own ſoules: and to call Synods or Aſſemblies to conferre their light in relation to a work of Reformation, or to the ſolving of ſome particular dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties. In a word, he may doe any thing for the truth, ſo that when he have done, he leave men to their conſciences that are of a different minde from him, and manage that difference <hi>without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixtly and laſtly,
<note n="6" place="margin">A defenſive power in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the truth.</note> The Chriſtian Magiſtrate ought to be a <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Father</hi> to the Church, to nouriſh the truth and godlineſſe. The begetting Father he is not, that is Chriſt, <hi>the everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> by the ſeed of the Word. But the Magiſtrate is to conſerve and maintaine the Churches peace and liberty, in the exerciſe of their conſciences, and worſhipping of God in all his Ordinances according to their light; and ſo he is to exerciſe a <hi>defenſive</hi> power for Religion both at home and abroad.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:158553:10"/>
                  <p>And this reſpect he is to bear to <hi>all</hi> equally whom he judges to be the children of truth in the <hi>maine,</hi> though ſcabby or itchy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren through ſome odd differences, in which things though he be not to further them or edifie them (wherein he apprehends them alien from the truth) by any compliance, but to leave thoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to themſelves to ſtand or fall; yet (<hi>notwithſtanding</hi> them) he is to afford to them his <hi>Civill</hi> protection, they managing their differences in a lawfull peaceable manner (as hath been noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.) I ſay, this provided, Theſe differences ought not to impaire or prejudice them at all in the intereſt they have in common juſtice and protection; but if any aſſault them in an unquiet way, they are to be defended, the aſſaylants puniſhed. So that with this <hi>difference</hi> is the Magiſtrate to carry himſelf towards the acknowledged truth, and the reputed errours, (I meane ſo reputed by him) he may and ought to do all he can to promote and inlarge the truth he ownes. He is not to doe ought againſt the other in controverſie, nor ſuffer any to doe ought againſt them, ſave to apply ſpirituall meanes, to preach, write, diſcourſe, diſpute, exhort againſt them, which kind of fighting is allowable among Brethren, ſo it be with right ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
                  <p>I expect here to be demanded, What I thinke of this preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> and of their <hi>action</hi> in calling this Aſſembly, and what I thinke of this Aſſembly?</p>
                  <p>For the Parliament I looke upon them under the Notion deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and allowed in this Chapter, as (warrantably and lawfully) improving an opportunity, God hath put into their hands for the <hi>increaſing</hi> of light, and <hi>excuſſion</hi> of truth, for which minde of theirs the bleſſing of Chriſt and the Churches awaites them: and I hope they will not exceed their <hi>Bounds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the Aſſembly, I looke upon them, not as a Nationall Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery of the Churches in <hi>England,</hi> but as godly and learned men, congregated by the power of the State. And I and all the people of God may and ought to ſeeke a <hi>proofe of Chriſt</hi> ſpeaking in them, which he may doe, by vertue of <hi>generall</hi> promiſes to his people to be found of them ſeeking him and his will, in and by all lawfull wayes and meanes, and of the particular advantage of their abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: as in every faculty the <hi>profeſſors</hi> of it that are moſt exerciſed in it, are <hi>likelieſt</hi> to diſcover truth, though alwayes they doe <hi>not:</hi> but is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158553:11"/>not tyed by any <hi>ſpeciall</hi> or particular promiſe to be preſent with them, as he is to a <hi>Church,</hi> Mat. 18. therefore I ſtand ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace any light, that Chriſt ſhall pleaſe <hi>providentially</hi> to miniſter unto me by their hands; but tie my ſelfe by no meanes to their <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrament,</hi> further then I ſee it to be according to the Word; for Chriſt never made them the <hi>Lords</hi> of my faith; no not if they were the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have given my judgement (at length) in this matter, and I think I give not much leſſe power to the Magiſtrate in Religion, then hath been by our <hi>moderne,</hi> and more moderate Writers aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to them, who contend on their behalfe for no more, but <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Juriſdiction,</hi> and ſtate the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Primatus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius eſt quo princeps prae eſt Eccleſiae tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam caput externae poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae; ſeu quo Princeps eſt primas Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae quantùm ad externam Eccleſiae poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam.</hi> Alſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Primacy</hi> of the Magiſtrate onely in the <hi>externall</hi> policy of the Church, relating onely to ſuch acts as theſe, <hi>Synodum convocare authoritate publicâ, Conſtituere ſalaria Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris Eccleſiae,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Eccleſiae procurare &amp; conſervare per Miniſtros, Eccleſiarum jura conſtituere, &amp;c.</hi> But including no <hi>ſuch</hi> power, as hath been diſputed againſt, for that appertaines not to the <hi>outward</hi> poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church.</p>
                  <p>And my judgement herein, for the Magiſtrates intermedling thus farre, is founded upon <hi>this</hi> Reaſon or Principle; It is lawfull for every man, (and ſo for the Magiſtrate) nay, it is his duty to <hi>doe all he can</hi> for the truth; but it is unlawfull to do the leaſt thing <hi>againſt</hi> the truth. Now becauſe by earneſt <hi>invitations,</hi> hearty <hi>recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> exemplary <hi>profeſſion,</hi> generall <hi>tuition;</hi> in a word, by <hi>offering</hi> and <hi>propoſing,</hi> not magiſterially <hi>forcing,</hi> commanding, impoſing, much and great and <hi>certaine</hi> ſervice may be, will be done <hi>for</hi> the truth, and nothing <hi>againſt:</hi> And becauſe by the other way of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, prohibiting, cenſuring, puniſhing, (impeacht in this diſcourſe) though ſomething <hi>may light</hi> for the truth, and <hi>ſometimes</hi> (as in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins</hi> dayes is noted in the caſe of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi>) yet much <hi>more</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice is much more <hi>probably</hi> like to redound to the truth: Many a truth <hi>ſnibd,</hi> kept low, or quite kept out; Men confirm'd in <hi>obſtinacy,</hi> if in errors, and more prejudiced againſt the right wayes, through the force that hangs over them, therefore <hi>that</hi> is lawfull, and <hi>this</hi> is unlawfull.</p>
                  <p>And in relation to theſe benefits which the Church reapes, and may expect from Chriſtian Magiſtracy, the Churches are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded firſt of all when they come together by way of reſtipulation,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158553:11"/>and for the further continuance and increaſe of this ſhadow, under which they reſt, to pray <hi>for Kings and all in authority,</hi> becauſe they doe, and that ſtill they may, through the benefit of their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>lead quiet and peaceable lives in all godlineſſe and honeſty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Queſtion thus ſtated, we proceed to prove the Concluſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Magiſtrates <hi>Cognizance</hi> of Religion, and the differences therein, is not the <hi>Concluſion</hi> diſputed againſt in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. It is ſufficiently done already by many able men, and all the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Authors agree with us in it, allowing him onely that which is to be allowed every man, <hi>viz.</hi> to lead forth his act (what ever it ſhall be found to be) under the conduct of a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular</hi> or <hi>perſonall</hi> Cognizance, but a <hi>publique Magiſteriall binding</hi> Cognizance they deny; therefore to doe this were but <hi>actum agere.</hi> Nevertheleſſe, becauſe ſome few conſiderations have been miniſtred to me in my own thoughts concerning this, I thought good to offer them being not many; as alſo becauſe the Cognizance diſproved may ſerve as a <hi>Medium</hi> againſt the <hi>Coercive act.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That this <hi>publique determining binding Cognizance,</hi> belongs not to him, appeares. 1. Becauſe it belongs to <hi>another</hi> charge,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>1</label>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> properly and peculiarly to <hi>try the ſpirits,</hi> and judge of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, therefore it is <hi>uſurpation</hi> of the Churches power and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to take this out of her hands. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. The Church is there declared to be <hi>the Pillar and ground of the truth;</hi> Not a Pillar, one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others, but <hi>the</hi> Pillar and ſtay of the truth; in alluſion to the ſetting up of the Edicts and Proclamations of Kings upon Pillars, to the view and notice of all their Subjects: So is the Church the Pillar of the truth, exhibiting it to the view and notice of all men, diſclaiming and reproving the contrary errors by the Word of God. Thus the truth <hi>as a Rock,</hi> beares up the Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. and the Church (in lieu) <hi>is a Pillar</hi> beares up the truth: the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is not the Pillar, nor his Lawes and Proclamations. By the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum dico, non unum aut alterum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotem, aut Miniſtrum, ſed Legitimum ac Chriſtianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum nomino &amp; innuo.</hi> Humfred. de Relig. verâ Conſervanda. pag. 24.</note> Church here, I mean not <hi>Petrus in Cathedra,</hi> the Pope in his chaire, nor the Biſhops in their Conſiſtory, nor the Angels and Lights of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158553:12"/>the Churches onely, but the intire Church inſtituted <hi>[in the maine]</hi> according to the Goſpel. Further ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. where the Churches are reſembled by Chriſt to <hi>John</hi> in a viſion as golden Candleſticks; Now the Analogy is plaine (and not forged) in reſpect of holding forth the light unto the world. There be indeed braſſe and copper Candleſticks, that hold forth falſe lights, but the ſheep of Chriſt know the one from the other, that they turne not aſide to the flocks of Chriſts Companions, by <hi>a divine effectuall inſtinct,</hi> whereby Chriſts ſheep know Chriſts voice, and will not follow a ſtranger, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.5. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1.</p>
                  <p>Now mark here, the Church is the Pillar, the Church is the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick, particular Churches, as well as the Catholick; not the Magiſtrate, not the State; If ſo, the Holy Ghoſt would not have wronged them, and <hi>detracted</hi> from them, by <hi>contracting</hi> this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous power and intereſt to the Church. It is proper for Kings and Magiſtrates <hi>to aske,</hi> and to aske of Chriſt, as <hi>He,</hi> (but more ſincerely) in the Miniſtry of his Word, in his Church adminiſtration, <hi>What is truth?</hi> and to watch at his gates, and waite at the poſts of his doores, yea to ſit at the feet of Chriſt there; For therefore hath Chriſt given gifts to his Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. And what are thoſe? Why, <hi>he gave ſome Apoſtles; and ſome Prophets; and ſome Evangeliſts; and ſome Paſtors and Teachers;</hi> He gave none Magiſtrates; Sure if Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy had been one of thoſe gifts, now that the Apoſtle was rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, he would not have been ſo injurious and deficient, but to have put it in. And what are theſe gifts for? Why, <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints; for the worke of the Miniſtry; for the edifying of the body of Chriſt.</hi> If for theſe ends <hi>adaequately,</hi> then where ſhall the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate come in? or what work is left for the Magiſtrate? I meane in point of authoritative teaching, or determining the truth. But you may ſay, This was onely for that time while there were no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Magiſtrates. Nay, read on; <hi>Till wee all come into the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt:</hi> So that this proviſion was not temporary onely, but for perpetuity, therefore ſufficient.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt is the Judge of Controverſies,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>2</label> and the interpreter of holy Scripture: (this is a <hi>Characteriſticall Tenet,</hi> diſtinguiſhing us from the <hi>Papiſts:</hi>) that is, Chriſt by his Word and Spirit, in the true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Church, not in the Popes ſentence, nor in the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:158553:12"/>of the Fathers, or the Votes of Synods, or the Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Nationall Aſſemblyes, though much helpe may be had by them, (for what difference (then) were there between the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and us, but that wee make <hi>many men</hi> a Pope, and they <hi>one man?</hi>) Now to give the Magiſtrate this Cognizance of differences in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, were to ſet up him (after we have puld downe theſe) as Judge of Controverſies, and Interpreter of Scripture.</p>
                  <p>This were alſo to commit unto the Magiſtrate <hi>the better part</hi> of the Miniſtry, whoſe office it is, to declare the whole Counſel of God,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>3</label> and to be the Boundſmen between truth and errour; and therefore Chriſt writes unto the Angels of the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and by them communicates himſelfe to the Churches. Nay, it is to give them a greater power and office then the Miniſtry, who are onely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe doctrines, not to impoſe them, and to <hi>waite</hi> with patience, if they be oppoſed, trying if God will give repentance,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.4.2. 2 Cor. 1.24.</note> to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the truth. This I ſay, is their utmoſt Commiſſion, <hi>to exhort, inſtruct, rebuke, with all long-ſuffering and doctrine, not as Lords of mens faith, but helpers of their joy;</hi> and whenſoever they flaſh and lay about them, it is to be onely with the ſword of the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>If the determining of Religion, and differences therein,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>4</label> belong to the Magiſtrate, <hi>quatenus</hi> a Magiſtrate, then to all Magiſtrates, or to the Magiſtracy of every Countrey, then to the great Turke, and Pagan Kings and Governours: But how uncapable of ſuch an intereſt they are who are aliens from the true God, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I need not ſay. The conſequence is good, for <hi>Quatenus &amp; ad omne,</hi> are termes adaequate and convertible. That which belongs to a man as a man, belongs to every man.</p>
                  <p>If you ſay therefore that it belongs not to the Magiſtrate, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus</hi> a Magiſtrate, but <hi>quatenus</hi> a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, &amp; ſo make it a flower that Chriſtianity ſticks in his Crowne.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, that Chriſtianity being altogether accidentall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall to a Magiſtrate, adds nothing of <hi>power</hi> (over others in Religion) to him, more then to another man, but onely perſonall <hi>priviledge;</hi> For Chriſtianity is the ſame in all; and why ſhould <hi>one</hi> man by vertue of his Chriſtianity (for 'tis denyed to be by vertue of his Magiſtracy) have power over judgements, and conſciences in matters of Religion, more then <hi>another</hi> that hath <hi>equall</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps more Chriſtianity? But the Word of God adds nothing of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:158553:13"/>that nature to a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, and let that ſuffice; for it adds nothing in the <hi>ſame</hi> kinde, <hi>viz.</hi> of Civill power, therefore it much leſſe adds any thing of <hi>another</hi> kinde, as namely, Eccleſiaſticall power. For the <hi>ſame</hi> ſubjection, and degree of ſubjection, is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſervants, and ſubjects to Maſters and Governours, without diſtinction of good and bad, Chriſtian and Pagan, nay though they be cruell and froward, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. By Chriſtianity Chriſt hath ſetled no advantage of <hi>power</hi> on the head of the Magiſtrate, though thereby he commend the yoke to the ſubject with an advantage of <hi>ſweetnes.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. For the proportion is the ſame, and 'tis a found Argument, from a Maſter to a Magiſtrate; that if a beleeving <hi>Maſter</hi> have no inlargement of power over his ſervant by beleeving; then neither hath a beleeving <hi>Prince</hi> over his Subjects, (and if not in Civill things, then much leſſe in Religion.) But wee ſee plainly, the Apoſtle neither accumulates authority on a beleeving Maſter, nor duties on the ſervant of ſuch a Maſter, but makes it a greater motive to obey the authority they had before. Let them not deſpiſe them, becauſe they are Brethren, but obey them rather. Therefore to conclude this Reaſon; Chriſtianity makes Magiſtrates <hi>members</hi> of the Church, not <hi>Maſters</hi> of the Aſſemblies; It charges them to look to their <hi>own</hi> opinions, but not to determine and <hi>impoſe</hi> upon other men.</p>
                  <p>And this I ſhall demonſtrate in the fift place,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>5</label> from the maine ſcope of the Magiſtrates work, as 'tis laid downe in Scripture. The object or matter about which Magiſtracy is converſant, which they puniſh or reward, is not faith, but facts, not doctrines, but deeds; and thoſe not any deeds that differ, but evill deeds. Thus <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3. Where the Apoſtle handles this point; <hi>For Rulers are not a terror to good workes, but to the evill, &amp;c. — if thou doe that which is evill,</hi> (he doth not ſay, if thou be of an heterodox opinion) <hi>be afraid; for he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evill.</hi> Where <hi>doing evill,</hi> is thrice mentioned, and no other termes uſed, that ſhould bring a mans judgement or opinion in Religion under the verge of the Magiſtrate. And ſo 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Submit your ſelves unto every Ordinance of man, — Whether to the King, — or unto Governours, as ſent by him for the puniſhment of evill</hi> doers, <hi>and for the praiſe of them that</hi> doe <hi>well.</hi> His determination therefore is about theſe.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:158553:13"/>
                  <p>This practiſe of Magiſtracy, to be the <hi>Dictator of truth,</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>6</label> and to <hi>moderate</hi> with the <hi>ſword,</hi> lays an unhappy caution, &amp; too effectuall an obſtruction, in the way of truth, which comes not in alwayes at the ſame end of the Towne; not alwayes by the learned and eminent in parts or power
<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 7.48.</note>; <hi>(Have any of the Rulers or Phariſees beleeved on him?)</hi> but even by the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quid? unius laici ſententia quae cum Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturis conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, praeponenda eſt ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Concilii.</hi> Gerſon.</note> 
                     <hi>people</hi> oftentimes. Who imbraced Chriſt, but the <hi>poore,</hi> but the people that <hi>knew not the Law,</hi> in the eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Phariſees?</hi> Ought not this to be conſidered, that truth be not prevented, by ſhutting the doore ſhee often chooſes to come in at, and opening a ſtately doore which ſhee delights not alwayes in?</p>
                  <p>The juſt care that Chriſt ſhewed, to maintaine the due <hi>diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> between <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> the Office <hi>Politique</hi> and <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick,</hi> doth likewiſe impeach this Cognizance of the Magiſtrate.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>7</label> When the two Brethren came to him to <hi>divide</hi> the Inheritance <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially;</hi> Chriſt refuſes, ſaying, <hi>Who made me a Judge?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 12.13.</note> If <hi>Chriſt</hi> would not judge in <hi>Civill</hi> things; <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> as ſuch ought not to judge in the things of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Hence then we may argue thus; If the <hi>higheſt</hi> Cognizance of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in Religion be ſubjected in the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſo be onely <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall,</hi> and a <hi>publique determining binding</hi> Cognizance be not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the Magiſtrate, then there can be no <hi>Magiſteriall Coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive</hi> act lawfully put forth in ſuch differences; for
<note n="*" place="margin">That the Magiſtrate ſhould decree puniſhment, <hi>Magiſterially,</hi> &amp; yet decerne the <hi>cauſe</hi> but after a <hi>private</hi> manner, will exerciſe the fineſt wit to find a pretext for.</note> ſuch as the Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance is, ſuch of neceſſitie muſt the Coercive power be, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed it; therefore as there is onely a Miniſteriall judgement in the Church, ſo there is onely a Miniſteriall Coercive power to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the Church alſo; for the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the <hi>one</hi> is the ſubject of the <hi>other</hi> alſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Containing Arguments, directly concluding againſt the Magiſtrates Coercive act in Caſes of difference.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Order in which I draw forth my Reaſons, is under theſe foure Heads or Titles in diſtinct Chapters.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Againſt the Magiſtrates Cognizance.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Againſt his Compulſion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Againſt the whole Complexum, Cognizance and Compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on together.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:158553:14"/>4. Againſt all externall compulſion in Religion.</p>
                  <p>The firſt I have paſſed already. The ſecond followes.</p>
                  <p>The immunity and impunity of differing opinions in Religion,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>1</label> as in relation to the Civill Magiſtrate may ſeem to be a Principle in Nature, founded upon the light of reaſon, ſeeing many of the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Heathen practiſed it; as in that inſtance of <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe, who was impeached by the <hi>Jewes,</hi> of greater Hereſie, then any differing Brethren in theſe dayes can charge one another withall: for he puld downe the old Religion, eſtabliſhed by God himſelfe, and preacht a new doctrine: Yet ſee what <hi>Pleads</hi> for <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of his Judges, who had nothing in them but what they ſuckt in with their Mothers milke. You have the ſtory, <hi>Acts</hi> 23. where I ſhall not comment upon the <hi>deeds</hi> of <hi>Lyſias,</hi> (a <hi>ſtranger</hi> to Religion, who yet <hi>delivered Paul</hi> both from the <hi>fury, and the fraud</hi> ſeverally, of thoſe that <hi>pretended</hi> much to Religion, and would for Religion ſake have deſtroyed him in the former part of the Story) but onely give you the words of his Letter to <hi>Felix</hi> in behalfe of <hi>Paul,</hi> ver. 26. <hi>Claudius Lyſias, unto the moſt excellent Governour, Felix, &amp;c. — This man was taken of the Jewes, &amp;c. — Whom I perceived to be accuſed of Queſtions of their Law, but to have nothing layd to his charge worthy of death, or of Bonds, &amp;c.</hi> Yet theſe were <hi>ſtrange</hi> Queſtions at that time. And of the <hi>ſame</hi> minde, in the <hi>ſame</hi> caſe, is <hi>Feſtus,</hi> Chap. 25.18. where declaring <hi>Pauls</hi> cauſe to King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> he uſes theſe words; <hi>Againſt whom, when the accuſers ſtood up, they brought none accuſation of ſuch things as I ſuppoſed, but had certain Queſtions againſt him of their own ſuperſtition, and of one Jeſus which was dead, whom Paul affirmed to be alive. And becauſe I doubted of ſuch manner of Queſtions, &amp;c.</hi> (obſerve here the <hi>ingenuity</hi> of an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that will not by a <hi>ſecular</hi> ſword cut in ſunder thoſe knots in Religion which he cannot <hi>unty</hi> by a <hi>Theologicall</hi> reſolution.) Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, on the morrow when <hi>Paul</hi> was brought forth, <hi>Feſtus</hi> uſes theſe words, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. <hi>King Agrippa, and all men which are here preſent with us, yee ſee this man, about whom all the multitude of the Jewes have dealt with me, both at Jeruſalem, and alſo here, Crying that he ought not to live any longer: But when I found he had committed nothing worthy of death, &amp;c.</hi> See the <hi>moderation</hi> of a Heathen, and the <hi>ſtability</hi> of his reſolution againſt the importunity of multitudes. He is not ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of <hi>his Gods,</hi> but he will <hi>let</hi> a Chriſtian <hi>live;</hi> nay, he will <hi>ſave</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:158553:14"/>him from any that would hurt him; juſtice ſo <hi>conſtraines</hi> him, that he <hi>diſdaines</hi> the ſollicitations of the multitude. O what a check was this to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> from the mouth of an <hi>Heathen!</hi> And when <hi>Paul</hi> had declared his own cauſe, before King <hi>Agrippa, Feſtus,</hi> and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, and the whole Councell,</hi> they ſaw no reaſon to be of any other mind, <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.31. For 'tis there ſaid, <hi>That when they were gone aſide, they talked between themſelves, ſaying, This man doth nothing worthy of death, or of bonds:</hi> An inſtance which Chriſtians in theſe dayes may look upon and bluſh, who think an <hi>inconvenient expreſſion</hi> deſerves a <hi>priſon. Paul</hi> had made a <hi>free confeſſion</hi> of his converſation, and of his faith; yet, ſay they, <hi>This man doth nothing worthy of death, or of bonds.</hi> They look for <hi>deeds, evill deeds,</hi> and thought it unreaſonable to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him for his <hi>different opinions.</hi> Now to enervate the force of this Inſtance and Argument, ſome man perhaps will repreſent my infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thus: Theſe <hi>Heathens</hi> did <hi>de facto</hi> permit differences of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, &amp; remit thoſe that were accuſed of them, <hi>Ergo</hi> Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates muſt be as careleſs <hi>de jure.</hi> But I urge it not as a <hi>fact</hi> onely, but as flowing from a <hi>principle</hi> of reaſon and juſtice, that did <hi>glow</hi> in the hearts of theſe <hi>Heathen,</hi> and ſo argues ſtrongly from them to <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and let any prove it was from a <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>Heatheniſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To imploy the Magiſtrate in this kinde of compulſion,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>2</label> is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the Lord Jeſus, and the proviſion he hath made for the propagation of the Church and truth: Chriſt hath a ſword for the vindicating of Truth, for the propulſing of Errours, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering of Enemies: And what is that? Why, the ſword of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> the <hi>Word of God:</hi> it is deſcribed <hi>Emblematically,</hi> Rev. 19.21. by a <hi>ſword coming out of his mouth.</hi> If <hi>Antichriſt</hi> the great enemy ſhall be conſumed with this, ſure then it ſhall be effectuall againſt the <hi>leſſer.</hi> And the Apoſtle cryes up, not onely the ſufficiency, but the <hi>migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe</hi> of this meanes; <hi>The weapons of our warfare are not carnall,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4.</note> but ſpirituall, and mighty through God,</hi> ('tis through God indeed, and through him they are) ſo mighty, that Chriſt will not be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to King, or Magiſtrate, for their power to convert men by, though he may uſe them to coerce inſolent enemies, and ſhelter the profeſſion of the truth, as was noted before. <hi>Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit.</hi> The Spirit of Chriſt is the Churches <hi>neck,</hi> mentioned <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.4. that knits Chriſt and the Church together, as the neck doth the head and the body: and ſee how 'tis deſcribed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158553:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:158553:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:158553:16"/>there; <hi>Thy neck is like the Tower of David, builded for an Armoury, whereon there bang a thouſand Bucklers, all Shields of mightie men.</hi> Chriſt (you ſee) hath not left his Church without a Magazine, an Armoury, even his Word and Spirit, which is <hi>quick</hi> and <hi>powerfull,</hi> wherewithall Chriſt <hi>that mighty man,</hi> defended himſelfe againſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and overthrew him: like that ſling of <hi>David</hi> wherewith he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt the mighty <hi>Philiſtim;</hi> and what cannot this ſword doe, backt by the Spirit, in the hand of Chriſts Miniſters and Members?</p>
                  <p>For the Efficacy of all Chriſts Inſtitutions in his Church, lies in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and not in the <hi>fleſh;</hi> As in preaching, and Sacraments; ſo in <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> ſo in beating downe Errors; 'tis Chriſt doth all by his Spirit; not by <hi>ſuch</hi> inſtruments, nor in ſuch an order, as to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the wiſdome of man, ſpecious, likely, probable to a fleſhly eye, (ſuch as the Magiſtrates compulſion may ſeeme to be) but by <hi>poore deſpiſed</hi> things, that ſo he may bring downe the pride of man, and the glory of the fleſh, and may traine up his people in the noble ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>faith,</hi> and may feaſt himſelfe with the glorious <hi>aſcribings</hi> of might and power to him alone. But in the way that moſt men goe, in drawing men to Religion, they leave but little to God; which practiſe hath indeed a principle in our natures, that ſhews it ſelfe in other things as well as this. For how apt are we in the point of Juſtification, to confederate with the <hi>Babel</hi>-builders? and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate adventure doe we count it, to caſt our ſelves upon the free grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt; ſo likewiſe in this buſines, we count it preſumption in ſtead of faith, to relie upon God in the uſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall means, without carnall weapons, to bring men to the truth; and therefore we deviſe wayes, to keep men in, that they ſhall not ſtirre; But if this be not of God, it will have the ſame ſucceſſe that <hi>Babel</hi> had, <hi>God will come down and confound</hi> this pride;
<note place="margin">Jer. 17.5.</note> 
                     <hi>For curſed be man, that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arme, and withdraweth his confidence from the Lord:</hi> And this Arme ſtretched forth to an Heterogeneous act, will wither and be ſhrivelled up.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3.</note> It is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enim gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis, aut jacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, aut m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tari manu veritas praed catur: ſed ſuadedo, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do; Quae auteni ibi ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi libertas, aut conſulendi ratio, ubi qui co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradicit, pro mercede, aut exilium aut mortem repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat?</hi> Athanaſ. Epiſt. ad ſolit. vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agentes.</note> contrary to the nature of Chriſts kingdome, to have the miniſtery of theſe <hi>carnall</hi> meanes; For 'tis a <hi>ſperituall</hi> kingdome, 'tis an <hi>inviſible</hi> kingdome, and the Apoſtle diſclaimes (as before) all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall weapons. A mans inke may be tempered too thick with <hi>humane</hi> Elegancies, to write the myſteries of the Goſpel. Chriſts kingdome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:158553:16"/>is not of this world, nor ſerved by this world: And as the manner of this world is contrary to him; ſo he delights to walke contrary to the manner of this world, who make their party as ſtrong as they can, but Chriſt <hi>hath choſen</hi> (marke, 'tis upon choice, not of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) <hi>the weake things of the world,</hi> even babes, to ſhew forth his praiſe and ſtrength. His Spirit in the Miniſtry of his ſervants, is that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Arme, that he puts forth to conquer all the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>He
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50.2.</note> ſhines out of Sion, the perfection of beauty,</hi> (not out of the Thrones of Princes as ſuch) and with his
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 43.3.</note> 
                     <hi>light</hi> and his <hi>truth,</hi> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the enemies of his truth. Chriſts veine lyes in this, in cloathing weak things with incredible ſtrength, and acting them on to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous atchievements.
<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>By me Kings raigne;</hi> but ſhall it ever be ſaid, By Kings Chriſt raignes, otherwiſe then as being nurſing Fathers to his Church? No; but he <hi>rebukes Kings for his peoples ſake,</hi> and ſayes, <hi>Touch not mine anointed, and doe my Prophets no harme:</hi> He firſt anoints them, and thereby <hi>teaches them all things,</hi> and then ſayes, <hi>Touch not mine anointed.</hi> Chriſt doth not uſe <hi>all</hi> meanes that he could uſe, to eſtabliſh his Kingdome, and inlarge his Dominion. He <hi>could</hi> have called for more <hi>Legions</hi> of Angels, then he had <hi>units</hi> of Apoſtles, to have reſcued him. So Chriſt could uſe the Miniſtery of the Civill Magiſtrate, and make them his friends, his champions, but he hath not pleaſed ſo to doe. <hi>Not many wiſe, not many mighty are called,</hi> and thoſe that are, he doth not uſe their might nor authority for any ſuch purpoſe as to conquer, but nurſe for him, by countenancing, providing, defending, &amp;c. As the vine needs the pole to climb up by, but yet grows up of it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Wee may bring an Argument <hi>à Majori.</hi> If Paſtours and Teachers,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>4</label> nay the Apoſtles themſelves, be not Lords of the peoples faith, (in a way humanely-authoritative) to impoſe doctrine or practiſe upon them; then much leſſe Magiſtrates: But the Apoſtle himſelfe dares not aſſume that greatneſſe; <hi>Not that wee are Lords of your faith, but helpers of your joy.</hi> Miniſters may be too magiſteriall in their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and people may be too implicit in their faith, and in their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their doctrine: as on the contrary, the one may be too low, the other too cenſorious.</p>
                  <p>It will be granted on all hands, that if Religion be the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates charge, yet as it is not his onely, ſo neither his <hi>firſt</hi> charge;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>5</label> for though it be the higheſt charge, it follows not that it muſt be the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:158553:17"/>proper charge of Magiſtracy: But Magiſtracy <hi>immediately</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly reſpects the good of men, their <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>outward</hi> being, and <hi>Religion</hi> onely <hi>obliquely</hi> and <hi>Collaterally;</hi> for ſuch an end muſt be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to Magiſtracy, as doth <hi>competere omni,</hi> hold among all, and to levell Magiſtracy at an higher and further end, then God hath, or its own principle will carry, is vaine. Now this will preſſe after the other, to be admitted likewiſe, that the <hi>firſt</hi> charge muſt be <hi>firſt</hi> lookt to, and attended upon, and the latter doth not diſoblige from the former, much leſſe <hi>contra</hi>-oblige the former, that is, differing opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Religion being of a <hi>ſecondary and remote conſideration</hi> to the outward well-being of men, doth not oblige to deſtroy or to expoſe to deſtruction, by mulcts, bonds, or baniſhment, the <hi>perſons</hi> of men; for whom, and in relation to whoſe preſervation, Magiſtracy was erected. For this is a Rule, <hi>The Law of Nature ſuperſedes Inſtitutions.</hi> Men have a <hi>naturall</hi> being, before they come to have a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; they are <hi>men</hi> before they are <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> Now therefore for faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe in Chriſtianity, you muſt not deſtroy the <hi>man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis alſo certain,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>6</label> there ought to be a <hi>proportion</hi> between the fault and the puniſhment, as that wherein juſtice mainly conſiſts; Now this proportion is not, nor cannot be obſerved, when you goe out of <hi>that nature</hi> and capacity in which a man hath offended, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him in <hi>another,</hi> as the Magiſtrate doth when he puniſhes for ſuch opinions in Religion. As for inſtance; A man is capable of a three-fold notion, according to a three-fold capacity, <hi>viz. Naturall, Politick, Religious.</hi> He ſins or offends in his religious capacity, and hath ſome heterodox opinions; yet a good ſubject, and fellow-ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, a good Father to his Family, &amp;c. Why now ſuch may his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours be, that he may forfeit his <hi>religious</hi> notion, and ought to be <hi>rejected,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, after once or twice admoniſhed in vaine; but now to come upon his <hi>politick</hi> beeing or priviledges, is to puniſh him in that notion and capacity wherein he hath not at all offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (except he have diſturbed the publique peace by the turbulent managing of his opinion, and then no man may excuſe him, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) as he was a good ſubject before he drunk in this opinion, ſo he is never the worſe ſince; therefore to deny him roome in the kingdome, or to ſeiſe upon his perſon, or to come upon his eſtate, is as to puniſh <hi>one</hi> man for <hi>another</hi> mans fault. Therefore ſeeing the Magiſtrate cannot reach the <hi>mind,</hi> and judgement, and conſcience,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:158553:17"/>with his puniſhments, which is the offender, he ought not to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the <hi>outward</hi> man; Errours being properly <hi>ſinnes without the body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Containing Reaſons againſt the whole Complexum,</hi> viz. <hi>Cognizance and Compulſion together, in the ſenſe before mentioned.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſt never <hi>appointed</hi> nor <hi>anointed</hi> Magiſtracy to ſuch a worke, neither ever came it into his heart ſo to doe;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>1</label> therefore we muſt not <hi>adde</hi> them; (for that were to be more carefull then Chriſt, and <hi>wiſe above that which is written</hi>) and therefore Chriſt will not
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Illa vero quae à ſpirituals Chriſti Regno aliena ſunt, effect us qui ad hoc Coeleſte Chriſti Regnum pertincnt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducere neque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, proinde quod inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutione divind ad cos produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dos non ſunt ſanctificata.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>bleſſe</hi> them therein.</p>
                  <p>If this honourable burden of all the Churches belong to the Magiſtrate, it is either by the <hi>law of Nature,</hi> or by <hi>Inſtitution;</hi> Not by the law of Nature, for that is the ſame every where, and would ſtate it as well in a <hi>Heathen</hi> Conquerour, as a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King. Not by Inſtitution; for 'tis none of thoſe <hi>gifts</hi> mentioned, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. if any where els, let it be ſhewed; And if it can no where be ſhewed, then either it belongs not unto them, or one of theſe three worſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences will inevitably follow; <hi>viz.</hi> how doth Chriſt <hi>render unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> (who commands us ſo carefully that we ſhould) in concealing this their honourable intereſt? 2. <hi>How is he faithfull in all his houſe,</hi> if he have left but this one duty uncharg'd upon Magiſtrates? 3. How ſhall the <hi>Word of God</hi> be found <hi>perfect, and able to make the man of God perfect,</hi> throughly inſtructed to every part of his worke, if it inſtruct him not in this duty of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate?</p>
                  <p>Now then if this care doe not <hi>appertaine</hi> to Magiſtrates, we ſhall in vain <hi>caſt</hi> it upon them, or they aſſume it to themſelves; for Chriſt will bleſſe his own <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and concurre with them, but not mens <hi>inventions:</hi> he is ingaged to the one, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.11. but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines the other, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.6.</p>
                  <p>The intermedling of the Magiſtrate in this kinde,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>2</label> is the way but to confound policy and piety, and to make Religion a <hi>State-notion,</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:158553:18"/>which while it ſeems to ſtrengthen Religion, doth indeed
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſte null ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, vi &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetiâ omnes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, adeo ut ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim nulli non appareat, ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſententia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non ſecundum Deum, ſed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam eſſe.</hi> Athanaſ. Epiſt. referring to the Arrian Magiſtrate.</note> eate out the native authority and majeſty of it. It is the honour of the truth of Chriſt (that which was the honour of Chriſt the Truth,) <hi>not to receive honour from men,</hi> in this kinde; 'tis a prejudice which the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Parliament will not doe to an <hi>ancient</hi> law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to enact that for law which is a law long ſince. Religion and every particle of it, is enacted already by an higher authority, then any earthly King or Magiſtrate; and if that will not ſway the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to obey, what can the lawes of men doe? can theſe cobwebs catch thoſe that the nets of God cannot?</p>
                  <p>This courſe likewiſe would lay a ſtumbling-block in mens way, to <hi>prophane</hi> the things of <hi>God,</hi> by doing them out of obedience to <hi>men,</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>3</label> and to miſtake obedience to men, for obedience to God; And on the other hand, it may breed a Queſtion in tender hearts, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are over-ruled by the commands of God, and not ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by man, in doing what is good, and ſo they may loſe the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> through jealouſie of the <hi>Principle,</hi> occaſion'd by this ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of mans power therein.</p>
                  <p>From the <hi>fruſtraneouſneſſe</hi> of ſuch meanes,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>4</label> we may argue againſt it: How ſhort and improportionate is the interpoſing of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Cognizance and power, to ſuch an effect, as to convince the judgement, or to worke faith? it may indeed make hypocrites: <hi>Egregiam vero laudem, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>5</label> You aſcribe to the Magiſtrate the Cognizance of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and put a ſword into his hands to keepe downe errours; the <hi>preſent</hi> Magiſtracy is good and orthodox, but there ariſes a <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh that knows not Joſeph,</hi> a Magiſtracy that knows not the truth; now will errours <hi>walke on every ſide,</hi> (when heterodox Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are exalted) and that not by permiſſion, but by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and you ſhall be forced to them, and ſo whipt with your own Rod.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:158553:18"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Containing Arguments againſt all externall force in matters of Religion, or Compulſion in generall.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſts people are a <hi>willing</hi> people, therefore not forced,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>1</label>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. as may alſo be drawne from that Metaphor, applyed to Miniſters, who are called <hi>Fiſhers of men.</hi> Fiſhers <hi>allure</hi> by the baite, and doe not <hi>compell</hi> the fiſh with violence; there is an innocent guile, but compulſion cannot be innocent. It's an obvious principle, that Religion is to be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and not forced upon men: <hi>God perſwade Japhet</hi> (ſays the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch) <hi>to dwell in the tents of Sem;</hi> and <hi>David</hi> ſays to his people; <hi>If it ſeeme good unto you, let us fetch backe the Arke.</hi> That ſervice that is not
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sed nec Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis eſt cogere Religione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae ſponte ſuſcipi debeat, non vi. Cum &amp; hoſtiae ab animo libex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti expoſtulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: Ita etſi nos compuleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ad ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum, nihil praeſtabitis Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is veſtris, niſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentioſi ſint: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentioſus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Deus non eſt.</hi> Tertull. ad Scap. cap. 2.</note> free, is not acceptable to <hi>God,</hi> who loves a <hi>chearfull</hi> giver; and therefore the peoples conſent is alſo noted in that place, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.4. <hi>And all the Congregation ſaid, that they would doe ſo, for the thing was right in the eyes of all the people:</hi> and when the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle was to be built, how carefully is that Clauſe added, <hi>That every man bring what he brings willingly, and with his heart?</hi> Exod. 25.2. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 35.5. otherwiſe it was not to be received.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>2</label> Was not this doctrine held forth to us in a <hi>myſtery</hi> under the Law, when <hi>David</hi> was not permitted to build God a houſe, becauſe he had <hi>ſhed much bloud in warre?</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.8. But <hi>Solomon,</hi> a man of peace was deſign'd thereto. Was not this partly, (for I ſay not 'twas the adaequate reaſon) to warne us not to uſe violence, to make men Religious?</p>
                  <p>That zeale of the <hi>outwards</hi> of Religion that is hurtfull to mens perſons, is a breach of that <hi>exemplary</hi> Rule of Chriſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>3</label>
                     <hi>I will have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and not ſacrifice.</hi> Moreover, <hi>The Sabbath was made for man,</hi> (ſays Chriſt) <hi>not man for the Sabbath;</hi> and as much may be ſaid of <hi>all</hi> the outwards of Religion: then I muſt not for the Sabbaths ſake, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy man, for whom the Sabbath was made; for the Sabbath was made to advance mans happineſſe, not to take away his beeing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his opinion of the Sabbath differs from other men, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps from the truth alſo: the Sabbath is to help a man to what he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:158553:19"/>hath not, not to take away what he hath. Though we grant an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſtraint of all, for avoyding of ſcandall, as is aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>What ignorance and pride doth it ſavour of,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>4</label> for man to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to convince conſcience, and to work faith with his authority, who <hi>cannot make one haire white or black?</hi> And is it not <hi>God that muſt give repentance to the acknowledgement of the truth?</hi> 2 Tim. 2.25. What can man do but <hi>prove</hi> (whether God will) by the uſe of due meanes? and what's the meanes of faith? the <hi>ſword?</hi> Nay, but the <hi>Word: Faith comes by hearing.</hi> Beleevers are <hi>not
<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 1.13.</note> borne of fleſh, nor of bloud, nor of the will of man, but of God.</hi> A man cannot beleeve at his <hi>owne</hi> will, how much leſſe at <hi>anothers?</hi> Who can reveale and infuſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall notions and truths, but the <hi>Spirit?</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.) which the Spirit doth not by <hi>force,</hi> but by <hi>allurement</hi> rather or attraction.</p>
                  <p>And that is another Reaſon;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>5</label>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Piae religionis proprium eſt, non cogere, ſed ſuadere: ſiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Dominus, non cogens, ſed libertatem ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voluntati per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittens, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnibus, ſi quis vult veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repoſt me; Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis verò, num &amp; vos abire valtis? Quae autem ibiſuadend libertas aut conſulendi ratio, ubi qui contradic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t, pro mercede zut exilium, aut mortem reportat?</hi> Athanaſ. Epiſt. <hi>Deus coactam confitendiſe aſpernatus eſt voluntatem, ſiquidem Deus univerſitatis eſt, obſequi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> non eget neceſſario, non requirit coactam confeſsionem; ſimplicitate quaerendus eſt, confeſsione diſcendus eſt, charitate amandus eſt, timore vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus eſt, voluntatis prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e retinendus eſt; At vero quid iſtud, quod ſacerdotes timere Deum vinculis coguntur, poenis jubentur, ſacerdotes carceribus continentur, plebs in cuſtodia catenati or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis conſtricta diſponitur?</hi> Hilarius ad Conſtant. Auguſt.</note> The Spirit himſelfe waites, and violates not the liberty of the reaſonable ſoule, by ſuperſeding the faculties thereof, but <hi>approves</hi> every truth to the underſtanding, and moves the will without violence, with a <hi>rationall</hi> force. Shall man be more zealous for God, then God is for himſelfe. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe doth not force men, but <hi>call</hi> them to repentance, and to the knowledge, and acknowledgement of his Sonne. Let the extent of that word <hi>(Calling)</hi> be conſidered, whether it will warrant any further means then Arguments, perſwaſions, intreaties, (make them as forcible as you can) and if you hold the feare of puniſhment o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver men, it muſt be the feare of <hi>divine</hi> puniſhments: <hi>Wee knowing the terrours of the Lord perſwade men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Furthermore,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>6</label> as a reaſon againſt this compulſion, I will be bold to aske, Where is the man that needs not a graine of allowance in his opinions or practiſe? I will allude to the equity of that counſell, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Take not heed unto all words that are ſpoken, leſt thou heare thy ſervant curſe thee: For often-times alſo thine owne heart knoweth, that thou thy ſelfe likewiſe haſt curſed others.</hi> So I ſay, infiſt not upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:158553:19"/>every errour of thy brother, for thou thy ſelfe knoweſt, if thou knoweſt thy ſelfe, that thou haſt errours not a few, or at leaſt-wiſe, if thou wilt beleeve the Scripture, that ſaith, <hi>Wee know but in part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And how will you avoyd the <hi>devouring of one another,</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>7</label> and ſo the conſumption of your owne Kingdome, who differ among your ſelves, as well as from (thoſe whom you call) <hi>Independents?</hi> As when the Aſſembly were to carry up their Votes, and the Reſult of their debates concerning Church-government, I have heard, ſome contended for the Claſſicall Government that it <hi>muſt be,</hi> and that it is <hi>jure divino,</hi> and no other: Others, that it <hi>may be</hi> by the Word: a third ſort, that <hi>any Government</hi> was indifferent, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate was to determine; and therefore you were conſtrained to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate the termes of your Propoſition to the advantage of your cauſe, <hi>that a Presbytery may be by the Word of God,</hi> els you had loſt two parts of three, who would never have gone, that it <hi>alone muſt</hi> and might lawfully be. So here is <hi>Manaſſeh againſt Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Ephraim againſt Manaſſeh,</hi> as well as both againſt a third; and ſeeing <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> cannot conſiſt themſelves without an accommodation, why ſhould not a third come in, and be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated with them?</p>
                  <p>I aske not onely whether you may not erre,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>8</label> but whether you have not err'd; nor whether you may not have errours <hi>latent,</hi> but whether you will not acknowledge your ſelves to have been in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours <hi>patent?</hi> I know you will not deny it, though I wiſh and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly exhort; that it be more frequently, more publickly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by ſome, with more ſhame-taking to themſelves, that you have been thoſe Leaders that have cauſed the people to erre; you have preacht for <hi>Conformity,</hi> written for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> pleaded for the <hi>Common-Prayer-Booke,</hi> and <hi>walked willingly after</hi> almoſt every <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</hi> Now you have altered your minds and practiſes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted your opinions, deſtroyed what you built, condemned your ſelves in the things you allowed. Well then, have you taken your ſelves once in an errour? learne this wiſdome by it, to ſuſpect your ſelves, and be not too violent againſt others. Why may you not in a while ſee cauſe to exchange your preſent judgement for a better? Why may there not be more truth yet behind? Is that which is perfect come, or are we come yet to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt?</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:158553:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>9</label> And what have you to
<note n="*" place="margin">Of all things a man may diſpute alike. <hi>Charran.</hi>
                     </note> ſay for your judgement, that your dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Brethren have not to ſay for theirs? for the controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, is not in ſuch things as wherein one part muſt needs be convicted in his own conſcience, as ſinning againſt common prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in all men. You have grounds, ſo have they; you propoſe Objections, they anſwer them; you are perſwaded that you are in the right, and that this is the meaning, and right underſtanding of the Scriptures; they thinke no leſſe on their own ſide. Now who ſhall ſtate the difference, and be the <hi>dayes-man</hi> between you, but Chriſt in his owne time clearing the truth, and leaving naked the errours; except you can prove that the Word of God <hi>came out from
<note n="*" place="margin">Verity is not a thing of our own inventio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and purchaſe, and when it yeelds it ſelfe into our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, wee have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in our ſelves where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may challenge it, poſſeſſe it, or aſſure our ſelves of it. <hi>Charron of Wiſdom, p.</hi> 250.</note> you, or came to you onely?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, Is there not <hi>a time and a ſeaſon</hi> for every purpoſe under heaven? Hath not God his time of <hi>winking,</hi> and his time of <hi>warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> And ſo hath not man his time of <hi>ignorance,</hi> and his time of <hi>repentance?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>May not a Truth for a time, lie under the ſuſpition of an errour; was it not <hi>as</hi> ſtrange, and diſpleaſing to you not many yeares ſince, when ſome of your Brethren fell off from Common-prayer, and the Ceremonies, <hi>as</hi> thoſe wayes of difference, wherein they walke at preſent? And had you not exceedingly wronged them, ſinned againſt the truth,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>10</label> and your owne ſoules, if you had for theſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, wherein now you are come over to them, proſecuted them? though I ſay not ſome were altogether free from it.</p>
                  <p>And may not Errours for a time, have the credit of Truthes? as many Epiſcopall Doctrines, now rejected, might be inſtanced in; hath not every truth its ſet time, the <hi>fulneſſe of time</hi> to be borne into the world; as Chriſt Jeſus the perſonall truth had? Would you have thought it faire dealing, if your judgements and conſciences had been ſuperſeded by mans authority, and you had been forced to the renouncing of thoſe things, which you held in ſuch eſteeme, while you ſo held them, and to have embraced the contrary mind and practiſe of conſtraint, which now you doe voluntarily? Now walke but by the ſame Rule to others, and that is all that is deſired.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>11</label> And as there are ſome truthes proper and peculiar to ſome
<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 9.24. &amp; 12.4.</note> times, and not to every time, (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>preſent truths</hi>) ſo to ſome perſons and not to all perſons. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.16. <hi>Seale up the Law
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:158553:20"/>among the Diſciples.</hi> There are truthes then, proper to the Diſciples; Truth (indeed, all truth) in the ſpirituall underſtanding of it, is peculiarly vindicated to ſuch, it is the Churches joynter or dowry. <hi>The truth ſhall make you free.</hi> Is every man a free denizon of Heaven? I deny not but the common notion of many truthes, of any truth, may fall, beſide the Church, upon other men (though for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſake;) but what is a prerogative diſpenſation, muſt not be our ordinary expectation;
<note n="*" place="margin">So ſome truths are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſome of the Church, as the Spirit ſhall reveale, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. and without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the reſt; as when Chriſt tooke the three Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples into the Mount; ſo the doctrine of juſtification was ſpecially revealed to <hi>Paul;</hi> the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of grace to <hi>John;</hi> reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture things to <hi>John</hi> the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, &amp;c.</note> however, our expectation or compulſion cannot bring it, and then 'tis vaine; for <hi>the winde blowes where he liſts,</hi> as well in common as in ſpeciall graces.</p>
                  <p>Further,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 12.</note> It will afford no ſmall ſatisfaction, and have no leſſe then the force of an Argument with him that conſiders the riſe and root of this compulſive power (in the particulars we ſpeak of) as too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently deriving it ſelfe either from the <hi>ignorance</hi> of thoſe who think themſelves to be in the very right, and would have all men think ſo of them, that they had attain'd <hi>the reſurrection of the dead,</hi> the utmoſt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and period of all poſſible knowledge and underſtanding, at leaſt in the preſent age, or inſtant; either, I ſay, it comes from this, or els from an <hi>arrogating</hi> ſpirit in ſome, that would tie all men to their girdle, that cannot endure any ſhould differ from them, leſt they ſhould be preferr'd before them, that abhorre any change of their opinion, though it be for the better, becauſe that would ſpeake them imperfect; that cannot bring downe their ſtomacks to follow another, and receive light from their Brethren, affecting themſelves to be called <hi>Rabbi,</hi> the leading Men and Oracles of the age, (whereas God hath ſaid of no man, <hi>Heare him,</hi> but of his own Son;) Or els it comes in others from a <hi>covetous</hi> ſpirit, that would make a gaine of godlineſſe, a profit of the Miniſtry, and ſo would make all men religious, and conformable to them, that their <hi>Tithes</hi> and <hi>Eaſter-bookes</hi> may riſe the higher; Or laſtly, it comes in not a few from a ſpirit of <hi>rule</hi> and dominion, which how doth it make us a ſcorne and deriſion to the enemy, while they ſee even Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, yea, the Teachers of Chriſtians, to be like the <hi>Fiſhes in the Sea,</hi> whereof the greater devoure the leſſer?</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle foreſaw and ſuppoſed there would be diverſity of opinions in men, untill the terme appointed, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>13</label>
                     <hi>Till we all come into the unity of the faith.</hi> Now where Chriſt upon the place and caſe, applyes no remedy or meanes, but ſpirituall, ſuch as is there
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:158553:21"/>deſcribed, without any further proviſion upon the ſuppoſall of their inefficaciouſneſſe, but ſaw good rather to diſpenſe and tolerate; let us take heed of over-witting Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Nay,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>14</label> the Holy Ghoſt not onely foreſaw there would, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines <hi>there muſt be Hereſies;</hi> and 'tis expedient as well for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of love, as gifts, and for a foyle to and diſcovery of the truth, &amp; the profeſſors thereof. What ſingular thing were it in the ſheep of Chriſt, that they <hi>know his voice,</hi> if there were no ſtrange voices, or (which will come all to one) if the Magiſtrate did brand all others with mulcts and heavy puniſhments? and how ſhall the Apoſtles conſequence but be prevented, <hi>That by reaſon of errours
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.2.</note> the truth ſhould be evill ſpoken of,</hi> if every errour be ſnapt up preſently, which if it prevent not errours from ſtarting, yet will prevent the ſcandall of the truth by them? Are not errours as well as afflictions part of Chriſts diſcipline, whereby he nurtures his Church? then let this diſcipline <hi>have its perfect worke,</hi> till it may be cured by its proper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, the ſword of the Spirit. You may as well ſay, there ſhall be no ſins in the Church, as no errours.</p>
                  <p>Is not the practiſe of compulſion in the particular we ſpeake of,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>15</label> at once to fruſtrate all thoſe exhortations of the Apoſtles,
<note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 4.2. Phil. 3.16.</note> 
                     <hi>To forbear one another in love;</hi> to <hi>walke whereunto wee have attained by the ſame rule; quietly waiting till God reveale what is behind,</hi> and cleare what is in controverſie? Is it not to goe contrary <hi>ex diamentro,</hi> to thoſe arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traments of the Apoſtle;
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Not to judge one another</hi> (then ſure much leſſe to proſecute one another) <hi>in meats, and drinks, or concerning a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly day;</hi> as conſidering that
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> ver. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>he that eateth, eateth to the Lord, and giveth God thanks,</hi> and he that for beareth, goes according to his conſcience too, and if right in the maine, may be acceptable to God alſo?</p>
                  <p>In policy 'tis the worſt way in the world,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>16</label> and will prove the leaſt ſucceſsfull to extirpate errours by force: For this multiplies them rather; even as the Biſhops tyrannies did drive men to extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and we may thanke their ſtrict urging Conformity and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformity, as the inſtrumentall cauſe and meanes of thoſe extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of abſolute Separation and Anabaptiſme, which many honeſt and tender hearts (thinking they could never run far enough from the Biſhops) did run into: as the <hi>Antinomians</hi> likewiſe have ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at our churliſh exacting Preachers of the Law,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 32.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Who made emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the ſonle of the hungry, and cauſed the drinke of the thirſty to faile:</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:158553:21"/>And who knows but if force were removed, and a league made, and free trading of truth ſet on foot, and liberty given to <hi>try all things;</hi> ſtraying Brethren on the right hand might be reduced? for as much as we know, that <hi>as ſin takes occaſion by the Commandement,</hi> ſo do errours by proſcription, and to forbid them, is to ſowe them, and no readier way to make men fond of them, then to reſtraine them by force; for <hi>Nitimur in vetitum,</hi> we love to be prying into a <hi>cloſed</hi> Arke, and the price of any thing is inhaunced when 'tis made dainty of; and ſo <hi>ex contrariis contraria ſequuntur.</hi> Our firſt Parents were eaſily induced by the Devill, to beleeve there was more in that forbidden tree, then in all the trees of the Garden: and men are not ſo wiſe as not to deliver themſelves of ſuch a ſophiſtry unto this day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 17.</note> The Apoſtle requires us, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. <hi>To prove all things;</hi> that is, as I conceive, not to gather all things whatſoever before us (as all the creatures were gathered together before <hi>Adam</hi>) to forme and ſtate a judgement of them; for this were a worke worthy of <hi>Solomon;</hi> but the Apoſtle meanes, that before we take up any thing in our beliefe or practiſe, we firſt bring it to the barre and ballance, and put it into the ſcales of an impartiall dijudication; and this is the <hi>dignity</hi> as well as the <hi>duty</hi> of a ſpirituall man, that he <hi>judges all things,</hi> and is not concluded by the former judgement of any: and this liberty is as worthy the vindication as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>O homines ad ſervitute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nati!</hi> What mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is this, for a man to deſire to have all things free, his body, his members, his goods, and not his ſpirit, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> nevertheleſſe is onely borne unto liberty? A man wil wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly make benefit of what ſoever is in the world, that comes from the Eaſt or the Weſt, for the good and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, nonriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, health, ornament of his body, and accommodate it all unto his uſe, but not for the culture, benefit, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching of his ſpirit, giving his body the liberty of the fields, &amp; hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſpirit in cloſe priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Charron of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. p.</hi> 261.</note> any, in theſe <hi>exonera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> times, this liberty of judging. And 'tis eſtabliſhed upon very good reaſon; for it makes much to the advantage of truth, both to the <hi>getting,</hi> and <hi>holding</hi> of it; for, <hi>What lightly comes, lightly goes,</hi> (as we ſay.) The <hi>Bereans</hi> for ſearching into <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining it by the Word, are recorded by an Epithet unuſuall for the Holy Ghoſt to give to men, <hi>They were more noble</hi> its ſaid.</p>
                  <p>Now this liberty of trying and judging is in vaine, if there be not a liberty of profeſſion; and to hinder this, were a moſt tyrannicall uſurpation, over that connection, which God hath made between the act of the underſtanding, and the will, (whereby <hi>Voluntas ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur dictamen intellectus</hi>) and to put aſunder what God hath joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, and indeed to violate the Law of God and Nature.</p>
                  <p>A man cannot will contrary to the precedent act of judgement, he wills weakly without an act of judgement preceding; To force a man to a profeſſion or practiſe which he wills not, nay, which he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:158553:22"/>nills, is to offer unto God a ſacrifice of <hi>violence</hi> on the part of the compulſor, and an <hi>unreaſonable</hi> ſervice on the part of the compelled; and therefore neceſſarily unacceptable.</p>
                  <p>God would have every man fully <hi>perſwaded in his owne minde,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>18</label> Rom.</hi> 14.15. even about dayes and meates, and nothing impoſed upon a doubting conſcience, becauſe it is great; nor nothing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with a ſleight credulity, becauſe it is ſmall; but would have us
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14.18.</note> 
                     <hi>ſerve him</hi> in every thing we take up to beleeve or practiſe, and not to be <hi>the ſervants of men,</hi> in any thing that hath relation to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
                  <p>And this brings in another Argument;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>19</label>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Who art thou,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, that <hi>judgeſt another mans ſervant?</hi> Man in a naturall or <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> conſideration, is the ſervant of <hi>men,</hi> of his Prince, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique: But man in a <hi>religious</hi> conſideration, is onely the ſervant of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>he ſtands or falls to his owne Maſter.</hi> He is the ſervant of men to their <hi>edification,</hi> by holding forth his light and conſcience before them; but he receives neither his <hi>law</hi> nor his <hi>judgement</hi> from man: God accepts perhaps whom man rejects. <hi>The day ſhall declare it, becauſe it ſhall be revealed by fire,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.13. A place worthy moſt ſerious conſideration, in relation to the preſent Queſtion; for there the Apoſtle ſpeaks in a caſe very fit &amp; parallell to what may be exiſtent among us; There may be among us building hay and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon the true and precious foundation Chriſt Jeſus; Well, what muſt man pull it downe by force? No; that were to take it out of Gods hand, who will do it better then we can, <hi>Who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a day to make manifeſt every mans worke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conſider likewiſe,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>20</label> what a miſrepreſenting of Chriſt the King of the Church this compulſion is, and what a prejudice againſt the meekneſſe of his government; and in what a diſtance and diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion it runs from thoſe ſweet and ſoft Prophecies of him;
<note n="*" place="margin">Zech. 9.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thy King coming, meek and lowly, riding upon an Aſſe,</hi> the moſt bearing and forbearing creature. And elſewhere;
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 42.2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>He ſhall not cry, nor lift up his voice, nor make his voice to be heard in the ſtreets; A brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed reed ſhall he not breake; Butter and honey ſhall he eat.</hi> Conſider how harſhly this ſounds, how inharmoniouſly to other of Chriſts admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations. When he had to deale with <hi>Jezabel,</hi> an harlot, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced his people to commit fornication, (a worſe body there could not be) yet ſays Chriſt, <hi>I gave her ſpace to repent,</hi> before ever I would
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:158553:22"/>threaten her; and notwithſtanding this threat is gone out, it ſhall not bring forth, if ſhe repent; for ſo 'tis carried, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.22. Shall Chriſt waite, and muſt not men waite? Will Chriſt waite on a <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel,</hi> a wanton <hi>Strumpet,</hi> and ſhall we thinke much to waite upon a wanton <hi>opinion?</hi> Muſt the <hi>ſervant</hi> be above his <hi>Maſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And may I not ſay to theſe forward forcing men;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>21</label>
                     <hi>You know not what ſpirit you are of?</hi> you forget that you are of that ſpirit that wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the old world an hundred and twenty yeares in <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching; and many other parallell inſtances might be given of the Lords patience: and when his date of patience hath been out, and he hath drawn up his accuſation againſt a Nation, what hath been the tenour of it but this,
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 23.37.</note> 
                     <hi>I would have gathered you, but yee would not: I ſent my Prophets, riſing early, and ſending them, yee killed and ſtoned them?</hi> but where doth the Lord lay it to the charge of Prophet or Magiſtrate, that they did not force and compell the people? Indeed when they have neglected their duty of teaching and giving good example; or when
<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 23.15.</note> 
                     <hi>pollution hath gone out from them into all the land,</hi> the Lord hath reckoned up that, as good cauſe why, but no where their not forcing them to an outward forme of amendment, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would or no.</p>
                  <p>How contrary is the preſent voice, <hi>Ad caſtra, ad inſulas,</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>22</label> to the patterne of your fore-fathers, who maintain'd their cauſe againſt unjuſt Tyrants, <hi>Precibus &amp; lachrymis?</hi> but now that you have to deale with <hi>differing Brethren,</hi> you diſmiſſe your good old principle, and commend it to us, to receive your hard uſage <hi>with prayers and teares:</hi> and you are not contented, with the King of the Church, that hath all power in his hands, to <hi>behold Jeraſalem, and weep over it,</hi> even over your differing Brethren, whom you count to be in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, (if they are ſo.) How doe you forget that you are <hi>in the body,</hi> and may be tempted, and erre your ſelves? Doe you mete the ſame meaſure, you would have meted to you again? Is the Church in her <hi>naturall</hi> guiſe (that uſes to run before the dog and the wolſe) when ſhee follows her own kind with a ſword in her hand? Is not this <hi>maſculine</hi> property more harmonious, and agreeing to the man of ſin, that exalts himſelfe againſt Chriſt Jeſus? Pardon us then if ſuch a temptation at leaſt ariſe in our hearts to thinke the ſcene is quite changed, and you are (as to this) no longer the <hi>perſecuted</hi> Saints, but the <hi>perſecuting</hi> world.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:158553:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Many ſhall run to and fro,
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>23</label> and knowledge ſhall be increaſed,</hi> Dan. 12.4. As a dog doth in following the ſent, ſo doe men in following the truth, and they that will not give this liberty, muſt not expect they ſhould <hi>diſereetly</hi> follow the track: Wee have a Proverb, that <hi>they that will find, muſt as well ſeek where a thing is not, as where it is.</hi> Let us look upon the truth as <hi>Gods,</hi> and not <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s;</hi> and let us look upon our ſelves in all our diſcourſes, as <hi>hunting</hi> after it; every one acting and ſeeking for himſelfe, and for his part onely, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that God muſt lead every man by a <hi>ſenſe</hi> and inſtinct, ſo ſhall we give God his due glory, and ſave our ſelves much unprofitable vexation. And this liberty of free diſquiſition is as great a meanes to <hi>keep</hi> the truth as to find it. The running water keeps pure and cleare, when the ſtanding poole corrupts; that's the ſenſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbiall ſpeech, <hi>An Academick, or Pyrrhonian was never heretick.</hi> While men <hi>ſleep</hi> in a carnall recumbency upon their Doctors and Teachers, the Devill <hi>ſowes tares;</hi> the true temper and proper imployment of a Chriſtian, is alwayes to be working like the Sea, and purging ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance out of his underſtanding, and exchanging notions and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions imperfect for more perfect, and forgetting things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde to preſſe forward.</p>
                  <p>Why ſhould not men put on the ſame kindneſſe,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>24</label> and meekneſſe, and good manners, in debates of ſuch truths, as we now ſpeake of, as in Civill and ſecular matters, where every one <hi>ſuſpects himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>preferres others</hi> before himſelfe, not <hi>impoſing</hi> his <hi>ſenſe</hi> nor <hi>will</hi> upon any? Wherein ſhould there be free and ingenuous dealing, if not about the <hi>truth,</hi> which <hi>makes</hi> men <hi>free?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle ſays in a ſpeciall manner of Chriſtians,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>25</label>
                     <hi>that wee are called unto peace;</hi> and,
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 12.18.</note> 
                     <hi>For as much as in us is, we are to live peaceably with all men.</hi> Marke <hi>[with all men]</hi> ſure then with Brethren. Let them fall out with us, but let not us fall out with them, but onely as the Apoſtle did, by ſpirituall weapons contend for the truth. God is the <hi>God of peace:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 20.10.</note> and he commanded his people when they went out to Battell in a juſt war, they ſhould firſt offer peace, for ſo long. Nay, in that place, before referr'd unto, 1 <hi>Gor.</hi> 7. God would have his people ſuffer unbeleevers Infidels, not onely in the ſame king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with them, but to live in the ſame houſe, lie in the ſame bed together, that is, that the breach and deſertion ſhould not be on the Beleevers part (if there be no other cauſe, that may require it, but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:158553:23"/>the unbeliefe of the other;) and the reaſon is, <hi>God hath called us to peace.</hi> And peace is a Character of truth; <hi>The wiſdome that is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, it is firſt pure, then peaceable,</hi> Jam. 1.17. and therefore thoſe metaphoricall deſcriptions of converſion, by the changing of fierce natures into gentle diſpoſitions, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 11. <hi>The wolfe ſhall dwell with the lambe, and the Leopard ſhall lie downe with the kid, &amp;c.</hi> As a notable inſtance hereof may be given in <hi>Paul;</hi> While he was in a falſe way, he drives furiouſly (<hi>Jehu</hi>-like) he rides to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> fetches letters of authority thence, and is poſting to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to ſilence, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon all that preach Jeſus: But when he hath the truth on his ſide, we finde no ſuch carriage in him, but beſeeches the Brethren by his gray haires, &amp;c. indeed againſt obſtinate ſeducers, he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth much zeale, but that's a ſpirituall force, not corporall; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the truth needs no ſuch violence to promote it.</p>
                  <p>That doctrine or way that is urged with violence,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>26</label> is rather pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced then promoted thereby; for it ſavours, as if man were more intereſted, and concerned in the cauſe then God; for otherwiſe why is man ſo haſty, where God is ſo patient? It is a figne of men that
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Invitos ad mutatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae coegeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Ariani, quod hominium eſt, minimè ſuae cauſae conſidentium,</hi> Athanaſ. Epiſt. <hi>Nova autem iſta &amp; ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>r abilis haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, cum rationibus ſubruitur, cum ipſaver itate pudefacta concidit; quos non potuit verbis inducere, eos vi plagis carceribuſa; ad ſe pertrahere annititur; at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> vel ita ſeipſam quam non fit pia &amp; Dei cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix maniſeſtat.</hi> This prejudice and ſuſpition will any way incurre that is urged with violence on men.</note> 
                     <hi>diffide</hi> their cauſe, to be violent, and that the way is rather of man then of God; for if it be of God, it ſhall prevaile: What needs this force?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Haſt thou faith.</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>have it to thy ſelfe.</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>27</label> My faith muſt not be the rule of anothers practiſe, though voluntarily taken up, much leſſe will it warrant me to impoſe upon another, (that's the meaning.) For indeed practiſe comes not naturally, but from ones own principles, and a low practiſe that yet grows upon a <hi>true</hi> principle, <hi>well-beaten</hi> and underſtood, is better then the higheſt <hi>top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> practiſe, without a principle; as <hi>a living dog is better then a dead Lyon.</hi> Faith without workes are dead, ſo are works without faith; for faith is the forme and life of the worke. Therefore what a poore thing doe they contend for, that would bow the practiſe, and what <hi>arrow-ſpirited</hi> men are they, that are content with a <hi>conformed</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, though there be a <hi>contradicting</hi> principle, whereby a man <hi>jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:158553:24"/>himſelfe and his impoſer of weakneſſe and of ſin?
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.11.</note> 
                     <hi>Wee are made manifeſt to God</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle, and 'twas a great matter that he could undertake ſo farre) but doth that ſatisfie him? No, but <hi>wee truſt alſo</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that we are made manifeſt in your conſciences,</hi> els the Apoſtle would have had little joy in them, or boldneſſe towards them, notwithſtanding all their outward conformity.</p>
                  <p>The practiſe of forcing ſtraitens men in their liberty they have as they are <hi>men</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quid jam nobis ulterius relinquetur, ſi etiam hoc quod voluntate fieri oportet, libido extorquet alic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na?</hi> Lactant. lib. 5. Inſtit. cap. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>reaſonable</hi> creatures, who are borne with this priviledge and prerogative, to be led forth alwayes under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their <hi>own</hi> reaſon. Which liberty is much <hi>inlarged</hi> by being Chriſtians: Therefore the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>The ſpirituall man judgeth all things;</hi> which is not onely the <hi>Clergy man,</hi> but as <hi>Alſted</hi> gloſſes well, <hi>Spiritualis homo,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>verè Chriſtianus.</hi> And to the teſt and tryall of ſuch doth <hi>Paul</hi> ſubmit his doctrine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>I ſpeake as unto wiſe men, judge yee what I ſay.</hi> And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29. <hi>Let the Prophets ſpeake two or three, and let the reſt judge:</hi> Upon which <hi>Alſted,</hi> in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to another Argument, thus; <hi>Quò etiam pertinet locus ille celebris, ubi omnibus in Eccleſia Chriſti congregatis, qui viz. munere ac dono prophetandi,</hi> (i.) <hi>docendi, praediti ſunt, poteſtas loquendi; reliquis autem omnibus poteſtas judicandi conceditur;</hi> that is, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto all in the Church, to whom is given the gift of prophecying, that is, of Teaching, is granted the liberty of ſpeaking; to all the reſt, the liberty of judging.</hi> To this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument I will adde the words of a late, and (for ought I know) yet living Author.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The true office of a man, his moſt proper and naturall exerciſe, his worthieſt profeſſion is to <hi>judge;</hi> Why is he a man diſcourſing, reaſoning, underſtanding? Why hath he a Spirit? to build (as they ſay) Caſtles in the aire, and to feed himſelfe with fooleries and vanities, as the greateſt part of the world doth? <hi>Quis unquam oculos tenebrarum cauſa habuit,</hi> Whoever had eyes given him to keep them ſhut? No doubtles, but to underſtand, to judge of all things, and therefore he is called the <hi>Governour,</hi> the Superintendent, the keeper of Nature of the world, of the workes of God. To goe about to deprive him of this right, is to make him no more a man, but a <hi>Beaſt.</hi> If not to judge, hurts the <hi>ſimple</hi> and proper nature of man, what ſhall it doe to a <hi>wiſe</hi> man, who is farre above the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of man? To judge ſingularly and excellently is indeed the peculiar part of a wiſe man, not of everyman. It is ſtrange
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:158553:24"/>that ſo many men (I ſpeake not of Idiots, and the weaker ſort, who have not the faculty &amp; the meane to exerciſe it, but of thoſe) who either are, or make ſhew to be underſtanding and ſufficient, deprive themſelves willingly of this right and authority, ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſo juſt, and excellent, who without the examining or judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any thing, receive and approve whatſoever is preſented, either becauſe it hath a faire ſemblance and appearance, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is in <hi>authority,</hi> credit, and practiſe: yea they think it is not lawfull to examine or doubt of any thing; in ſuch ſort doe they debaſe and degrade themſelves; they are forward and glorious in other things, but in this they are fearfull and <hi>ſubmiſſe,</hi> though it doe juſtly appertaine unto them, and with ſo much reaſon, ſince there are a <hi>thouſand</hi> lyes for <hi>one</hi> truth, a thouſand opinions of one and the ſame thing, and but one that is true, why ſhould not I examine with the inſtrument of reaſon, which is the better, the truer, the more reaſonable, honeſt, and profitable? — It is to play the part of <hi>prophane</hi> men and beaſts, to ſuffer our ſelves to be led like Oxen—What can a wiſe or holy man have above a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, if he muſt have his ſpirit, his mind, his principall and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall part a <hi>ſlave</hi> to the vulgar ſort?—Why ſhould it not be as lawfull for one to <hi>doubt</hi> &amp; conſider of things as doubtfull, as 'tis for others to <hi>affirme</hi> them?—How ſhould we be capable to know more, if we grow <hi>reſolute</hi> in our opinions, ſettle and repoſe our ſelves in certain things, and in ſuch manner, that we ſeeke no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor examine any more, that which we thinke we <hi>hold.</hi>— They know not that there is a kind of ignorance and <hi>doubt,</hi> more learned and certain, more noble and generous then all their <hi>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and certainty. — There is a <hi>generation of men,</hi> that if they be conſtrained to change their opinions, being altered, they are <hi>as reſolute</hi> and obſtinate in their <hi>new,</hi> as they were before in their <hi>firſt</hi> opinion, not knowing how to hold any thing without <hi>paſſion,</hi> and never diſputing to <hi>learne</hi> and find the truth, but to <hi>maintaine</hi> that which they have ſworne and bound themſelves unto. Theſe kinde of people know nothing, neither know they what it is to know, becauſe they think to know, and to hold the truth in their ſleeve, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. — It is fit that weake men, that have not ſtrength to keep themſelves upright upon their feet, be kept up with <hi>props;</hi> they cannot live but in bonds, nor maintaine themſelves free, a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:158553:25"/>people borne to ſervitude, they feare Bug-beares, or that the wolfe will eat them, if they be alone. But in wiſe, modeſt, and ſtayed men, it is quite contrary. — <hi>hoc liberiores &amp; ſulutiores ſumus, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> integra nobis judicandi poteſtas manet.</hi> It is a very ſweet, peaceable, and pleaſant ſojourne or delay, where a man feareth not to faile or <hi>miſcount</hi> himſelfe, where a man is in the calme under covert, and out of danger of <hi>participating</hi> ſo many errours (produced by the fantaſie of man, and whereof the world is full,) of intangling himſelfe, in complaints, diviſions, diſputes, of offending divers parts, of belying and gain-ſaying his own beliefe, of changing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, and readviſing himſelfe: For how often hath time made us ſee, that we have been deceived in our thoughts, and hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced us to change our opinions? To be briefe, it is to keepe the mind in peace &amp; tranquillity, far from agitations, and vices, which proceed from that <hi>opinion of ſcience,</hi> which we thinke to have in things; for from thence do ſpring, pride, ambition, immoderate deſires, obſtinacy in opinion, preſumption, love of novelties, &amp;c. There is an <hi>univerſality</hi> of ſpirit in a wiſe man, whereby he takes a view, and enters into the conſideration of the whole univerſe; like <hi>Socrates,</hi> who contained in his affection all humane <hi>kinde,</hi> he walketh through all, as if they were <hi>neare</hi> unto him; he ſeeth like the Sun, with an <hi>equall</hi> and <hi>ſetled</hi> regard, as from an high watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tower, all the changes and interchangeable courſes of things. — Which is a <hi>livery</hi> of the <hi>Divinity,</hi> and a high priviledge of a wiſe man, who is the <hi>image of God</hi> upon earth. <hi>Magna &amp; generoſa res animus humanus, nullos ſibi poni niſi communes, &amp; cum Deo terminos patitur.</hi> The moſt beautifull and greateſt ſpirits, are the more <hi>univerſall,</hi> as the more baſe and blunt are the more <hi>particular.</hi>— Every man calleth that <hi>barbarous,</hi> that agreeth not with <hi>his</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and cuſtome; and it ſeemeth that we have no other touch of truth and reaſon, then the example and the <hi>Idea</hi> of the opinions and cuſtomes of <hi>that place</hi> or Countrey where we live. Theſe kind of people <hi>judge</hi> of nothing, neither can they, they are ſlaves to that they hold, a ſtrong <hi>prevention</hi> and anticipation of opinions doth wholly poſſeſſe them, &amp;c.</q> Thus <hi>Charron of Wiſdome,</hi> 2 <hi>booke Chap.</hi> 2. which he ſpeaks of in generall as a diſpoſition to wiſdome, but who knows but he might intend it in the nature of the woman of <hi>Tekoa's</hi> parable, as an advantage to divine truth; however, I bring it not as an authority, but as reaſon.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:158553:25"/>
                  <p>Furthermore, are there not <hi>ſeverall ſtatures</hi> in Chriſt,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſ. </seg>29</label> and that in knowledge as well as in other graces; as there are ſeverall kinds of metalls in the earth, ſome more precious and <hi>better concocted</hi> then other; and doth not <hi>one ſtarre differ from another ſtarre in glory?</hi> Even ſo doe men, and ſo will they, (do we what we can,) in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curateneſſe of their knowledge, and in the clearneſſe of their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions. Some can onely ſee a rule of Diſcipline in the Scripture confuſedly and <hi>indiſtinctly;</hi> like the purblind man, that <hi>ſaw men like trees walking:</hi> (and in truth 'tis moſt proper for them to cry for a toleration, and he had a hard heart that would deny it them) Others ſee more <hi>clearly</hi> the perfect draught, and all the lineaments thereof, not through the <hi>excelling</hi> of their own wit, but the <hi>teaching</hi> of Chriſts Spirit, yet not aſſuming to themſelves a greater meaſure of it then the other, who perhaps in <hi>other</hi> things may ſee more then they by the ſame Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, I ſhall conclude the <hi>poſitive</hi> part of this Diſcourſe, with opening (in ſome meaſure) the <hi>deſigne</hi> of Chriſt, in eſtabliſhing no other, <hi>more ſpecious,</hi> better ſatisfying order and meanes, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the truth, and in excluding force and power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <hi>humane,</hi> from miniſtring in his kingdome in this particular, leaving this and all that hath been ſaid, to ſpirituall men to judge, who can <hi>compare ſpirituall things with ſpirituall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is in <hi>this</hi> matter as 'tis in the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>particular</hi> Churches, the adverſary carries it the ſame way, and turns upon the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon hinge of <hi>humane reaſon,</hi> and muſt be anſwered the ſame way in both. They diffide the ſufficiency of a particular Church to manage its own affaires, and why? becauſe they have ſo <hi>few</hi> Officers, and in ſome Churches perhaps but <hi>one,</hi> and he none of the greateſt Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and the Brethren a company of <hi>illiterate</hi> men, &amp; a good meſſe of government theſe are like to make. This errour proceeds now, from not conſidering, <hi>where</hi> the ſtrength &amp; ſufficiency of this poore flock doth lie, which is, not in themſelves, were they as eloquent as <hi>Apollo,</hi> as logicall as <hi>Paul,</hi> but in <hi>Chriſt their head,</hi> who is by his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall promiſe preſent with them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>Where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in his Name. The Lord is in the midſt of her, therefore ſhee cannot be moved,</hi> Pſal. 46. <hi>And the government is upon his ſhoulder.</hi> Now hence (I ſay) is the miſtake, through not conſidering, that the Government of the Church by Officers, is but <hi>miniſieriall,</hi> and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:158553:26"/>that they are guided and acted by Chriſt, and he puts wiſdome into their hearts, and right words into their mouthes; as once he fitted <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab</hi> for the worke of the Tabernacle. The ſame doth Chriſt now; for <hi>he is aſcended upon high, that he might fill all things,</hi> and he doth fill carefully all his own Inſtitutions with force and efficacy; and they doe not wiſely that judge of them according to their <hi>appearance,</hi> for ſo, they are the moſt contemptible unlikely things in the world, but could you ſee the vertue and power that Chriſt conveyes ſecretly under them, you would fall downe before them. So I ſay now in this matter of ſuppreſſing errours, (as before qualified) which we ſay, muſt be onely by the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> by the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which in the hand of the Spirit is <hi>quick and powerfull,</hi> by brotherly <hi>admonitions</hi> and earneſt <hi>exhortations,</hi> and holding forth the contrary light, <hi>doctrinally</hi> and <hi>practically,</hi> &amp;c. Now alas, ſay our carnall hearts, what are theſe like to doe? 'Tis true; look upon them in the outward appearance onely, and they promiſe little, but men do not conſider, that theſe are but the <hi>vaile</hi> and <hi>covering</hi> of that arme and power which muſt doe the deed. For <hi>God himſelfe is Judge,</hi> Pſal. 50.6. Chriſt Jeſus is the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>light</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> the decider of Controverſies, <hi>Dictator</hi> to his Church, and in the obſervation of Goſpel Rules, he diſcovers himſelfe unto his people, and by and through his people to thoſe that erre. The O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle in the Temple ſpake not, 'twas but a forme or image, but God ſpake in the Oracle. The Scriptures themſelves are but a ſealed Booke, except Chriſt by his Spirit ſpeake in them, and by them, to our underſtandings and hearts. What matter is it what the forme be, if God fill it? What of ſtrength or force doth the ſleeve or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring contribute to the arme? There is no means of any efficacy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, and the ſmalleſt means is of abſolute ſufficiency through Chriſt; and what means ſhould be bleſt by him but his <hi>own</hi> means? We forget that Chriſt will have his Church in all their ordinances, affaires, and adminiſtrations, to ſhew forth his <hi>death;</hi> that all things and perſons in the Church muſt beare a ſuitablenes and correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to <hi>Chriſt crucified,</hi> the head of the Church. It is ſpoken par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of that <hi>one</hi> Ordinance, and chiefe one the Lords Supper, that 'tis <hi>to ſhew forth the Lords death;</hi> 'tis true of <hi>all</hi> Ordinances; Chriſt will have his people in the carriage and managing of all his and their affaires, performe his funerall rites, and obſequies, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:158553:26"/>hold forth an Embleme of his death to the world; and therefore 'tis ſaid, <hi>The waters of Shiloah,</hi> that is, the Ordinances of the Church, <hi>run ſoftly,</hi> Iſa. 8.6. a pace for a funerall, and they are not cloathed in the light and gawdy colours of this worlds excellency and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but in the moſt poſſible ſimplicity and lowlineſſe; <hi>And I Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, came not</hi> (ſays <hi>Paul,</hi> who could have afforded it as ſoone as any man) <hi>with excellency of ſpeech, or of wiſdome, &amp;c. For I, determined not to know any thing among you, ſave Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. Marke here the ground and roote of the whole matter, (I meane of the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> of Chriſts wayes and Ordinances,) 'tis <hi>Chriſt crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Chriſts death is thus <hi>avenged</hi> upon the glory of the world, whileſt the power and greatneſſe of this world is <hi>reprobated</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected from the moſt <hi>noble</hi> uſes and honourable ſervices, namely, from miniſtring <hi>in</hi> his kingdome: Goe, ſays Chriſt to <hi>mans wiſdome</hi> and humane Eloquence, I will have none of thee in preaching my Goſpel; and returne into the ſcabbard, ſays he to the <hi>Magiſtrates ſword,</hi> I will have none of thee to cut the way for my truth, through <hi>woods,</hi> and <hi>rocks,</hi> and <hi>mountaines,</hi> through ſtony hearts and impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated reaſonings. <hi>Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Thus Chriſt reprobates parts and learning, and the moſt ſpecious and likely meanes, (ſhall he be <hi>crucified,</hi> and ſhall theſe be in their <hi>flower</hi> &amp; bloſſome?) and he brings down the mighty things of the world, by the
<note n="*" place="margin">Here may be pertinently &amp; commodioſly inſerted a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry out of <hi>Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finus,</hi> of a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher that evaded all the learned Arguments of the Divines, and was converted by a plain illiterate man; which I ſhall doe in his own words. <hi>Cum pro ſtudio Religioſi Imperatoris, ex omniterra ſacer dotes Dei coiſſent, opinione commoti, Philoſophi quoq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> &amp; Dialectici valde nobiles &amp; opinatiſsimi convene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. In quibus quidam inſignis in arte Dialecticâ per dies ſinguloe, confl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ctatus ſummi certaminis cum Epiſcopis noſtris, viris adae<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> in Dialectica, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> improbabilitèr eruditis, movcbat, &amp; ficbat ingens ſpecbaculum convenientibus ad audiendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doctis &amp; literatis viris. Nectamen ullo genere Philoſophus concludi à quoquam poterat aut conftring. Tanta etenim dicendiarte, objectis quaeſtionibus occurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, ut ubi maximè putaretur aſtrictus velut anguis lubricus labcretur. Sed ut oftenderet Deus, quod non in ſermone regnum Dei ſed in virtute conſiſtit, quidam ex confeſſoribus, ſimpliciſsimae na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae vir &amp; nihil aliud ſciens niſi Jeſum Chriſtum, &amp; hunc crucifixum, inter caeteros auditores E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopos adorat, quiciam vidiſſet Philoſophum inſultantem noſtris &amp; callidâ ſe diſputationis arte jactantem, poſcit ab omnibus locum, velle ſe paucis cum Philoſopho ſer mocmari. Tum verò noſtri qui ſimplicitatem viri, &amp; imperitiam de ſermone duntax at noſſent, pavere, &amp; velut pudorem quendam pati, ne fortè apud callidos homines riſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> officeretur ſancti ſimplicitas. Perſtitit tamen ſenior, &amp; hinc movet ſermonis exordium. In nomine, inquit, Jeſu Chriſti Philoſophe aud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>quae vera ſunt; Deus unus eſt qui ficit Coelum &amp; terram, qui<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> homini quem de terrae lime formaverat, ſpir it um dedit: univerſa quae videntur, &amp; quae non videntur, virtute verbi ſui creavit, &amp; ſpiritus ſui ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione firmavit. Hoc Verbum ae Sapientia quem nos Filium dicimus, humanos miſcratus errores, ex virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e naſcicur, &amp; per poſsionem mortis, à perpetua nos morte liberavit, ac reſurrectione ſua aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam nobis contul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>am: quem &amp; expectamus Jud cem omnium quae gerimus eſſe venturum. Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis hoc na eſſe Philoſophe? At ille velut ſi nunquam ullum ſermonem contradicends dideciſſet, itaob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtupoſactus vtrtute dictorum, mutus adomn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a hoc ſolum potu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t reſpondere, it a ſibi videri, nec aliud verum eſſe quam quod dixerat. Tumſenior, ſi haec (inquit) ita eſſecred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s, ſurge &amp; ſequere me ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicum, &amp; hujus fide ſignaculum ſuſcipe. Et Philoſophus cenverſus ad diſcrpulos ſuos, vel ad eos qui audiendi grat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> convener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>: Andite (inquit) ô Eruditi viri: Donec verbis mecum geſt a res eſt, verba verbis oppoſui, &amp; quae dicebantur dicendiarte ſubverti. ubi vero pro verbis virtus proceſſit ex are di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>entes, non potuerunt reſiſtere verbavirtuti, nec komo adver ſari potuit Deo. Et ideo ſi quis veſtrum potuit in his quae dicta ſunt ſentire quae ſenſi credat Chriſto, &amp; ſequatur hunc ſenem, in qyo locutus eſt Deus. It a Philoſophus Chriſtianus effectus tandem ſe gratulatus eſt victum.</hi> Kuffi. l. 3. c. 3. And there is this good note adjected in the Margent; <hi>Ubi ſunt nunc qui ſophiſticis argutus opus eſſe putant ad convincendos Philoſophos?</hi>
                     </note> weake; and things that <hi>are,</hi> by things that <hi>are not, that no fleſh may glory in his preſence, but he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord,</hi> that neither our <hi>faith,</hi> nor the Ordinances <hi>ſucceſſe, ſhould ſtand in the wiſdome of men,</hi> nor in the likelineſſe of the meanes, approving themſelves ſo to mans underſtanding, <hi>but in the power of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:158553:27"/>God.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like are the Reaſons rendred in the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond Chapters of the firſt Epiſtle to the Corinths;</hi> and theſe are enough (I conceive) to ſatisfie a moderate underſtanding. For my owne part, I muſt profeſſe it is the <hi>Clue</hi> of threed that carries me through this <hi>Labyrinth,</hi> 'tis the <hi>Pole ſtarre,</hi> by which I <hi>ſteere</hi> my judgement, and by which my doubts are reſolved ſatisfactorily. I ſee reaſon enough for that ſlender and <hi>abject</hi> proviſion, which Chriſt hath made (in the worlds account) for the propulſing of errours, and for that meane forme and guiſe, wherein all Chriſts Ordinances appeare unto us, when I look upon the death of Chriſt, or upon <hi>Chriſt crucified.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:158553:27"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Illuſtrating the Argument, with Examples and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies out of divine and humane Writ.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſtated the Queſtion, both on the <hi>poſitive</hi> and <hi>negative</hi> part of the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> duty, and proved it with Reaſons; I proceed further to confirme and illuſtrate this Argument with Examples and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. Beginning with the <hi>old Teſtament,</hi> and therein with Inſtances of <hi>Heathen</hi> Kings, (whoſe Religion, and the <hi>Jewes</hi> were diametrally oppoſite) whereby it may ſeeme this to have been a principle in Nature,) that yet upon grounds of <hi>ingenuous reaſon,</hi> as well as <hi>policy,</hi> (though we deny not a providence in it) not onely permitted the publick exerciſe of a contrary Religion, (which is more then we plead for) but alſo gave <hi>faire quarter</hi> to the Church, and <hi>all liberty,</hi> yea <hi>authority</hi> and <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations</hi> for their religious ingagements; yea, endowed them and their worſhip with <hi>great priviledges, immunities,</hi> and <hi>advantages;</hi> then which Inſtances, nothing could poſſibly be alledged by us, more pregnant, preſſing, provoking, upbraiding, conſtraining, to thoſe, between whom and us there is the <hi>ſame</hi> Religion, truth, and worſhip ſubſtantially, though ſome lighter <hi>circumſtantiall</hi> differences.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are eſpecially <hi>Cyrus, Darius,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes;</hi> I might adde to them <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> who though a ſtranger to the Church,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ahaſuerus.</hi>
                     </note> and to the true God, yet not onely <hi>protected</hi> the Church, deſtined to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction for their Religion ſake; but gave them a <hi>free avengement</hi> of themſelves, of his owne <hi>profitable</hi> ſubjects their enemies, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 9. to the ſlaying of ſeventy ſix thouſand men. And the book of <hi>Daniel</hi> is not without ſome paſſages, which might be referred hither, and good uſe made of them; as namely,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Nebuchadnezzars exalting</hi> men of a Religion <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> in the Provinces, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:158553:28"/>all the great Affaires of the Provinces to run through their hands, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.48, 49. And a ſecond time if not to a further degree of honour, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.30. And theſe things done by <hi>Politick</hi> Princes, that wanted not ſerious regards to their own ſafety, ſtability, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhing; and were <hi>Conquerours</hi> over theſe <hi>captives,</hi> (whoſe <hi>terrour could not make theſe Princes afraid,</hi> as <hi>Elibu</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Job</hi> 33.7.) nor had they any politick ingagements to their Religion, further then the ſatisfaction of theſe their Subjects in this particular, and their more willing ſubjection, and the union and peace of their kingdomes thereby; and they went on in their owne Heatheniſme themſelves, though they indulged thus to the Church.</p>
                  <p>But I ſhall content my ſelfe to ſet before you thoſe three before mentioned,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
                     </note> beginning with <hi>Cyrus,</hi> whoſe Story, ſo far as concernes our purpoſe, you ſhall find, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. to this effect; <hi>That he made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation throughout all his Kingdome, and put it in Writing, wherein be gave free liberly to all the people of the Jewes his Captives, to goe up to Jeruſalem, and build the houſe of God there. And whoſoever remaineth</hi> (he addes) <hi>in any place, where he ſojourneth, let the men of his place help him with ſilver and with gold, and with goods, and with beaſts, beſides the free will-offering for the houſe of God, which is in Jeruſalem.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he made reſtitution of all the veſſels of the Temple, plundred by his predeceſſour <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One would have thought a Proclamation of liberty, &amp; no more, had been enough, and doubtles that alone would have been moſt thankfully accepted by the godly <hi>Jewes,</hi> and they would have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that this Prince had indulged a great and ſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>your to them; but theſe further acts of grace might well make them ſay; as, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126. <hi>When the Lord turned againe our captivitie, we were like them that dreame. Then was our mouth fill'd with laughter, and our tongue with ſinging.</hi> Nay <hi>the Heathen</hi> could not chooſe but ſay, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for them:</hi> and truly ſay they, <hi>The Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>th done great things for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, whereof wee are glad.</hi> And who could blame them for being glad?</p>
                  <p>But I look it ſhould be objected;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">object. </seg>
                     </label> That <hi>Cyrus</hi> did not this of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but was <hi>extravrdinarily</hi> ſtirr'd up hereunto by God, (his owne words importing ſo much) and that he was acted in this thing <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove</hi> the conſideration of all politique reaſons, and the regard of his owne Religion: Therefore what <hi>Cyrus</hi> did upon ſuch an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:158553:28"/>motion, cannot be reaſonably expected from Princes now, that are not ſo ſtirr'd up and acted extraordinarily by the divine hand, but they muſt be faithfull to their Principles <hi>received,</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>eſtabliſhed,</hi> and muſt indulge no other liberties or favours, then may conſiſt therewith in a <hi>rationall</hi> and <hi>prudentiall</hi> way.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer. <hi>Cyrus</hi> was ſtirr'd up by God;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     </note> but firſt God would not ſtirre him up to an <hi>unlawfull</hi> or an <hi>uncomely</hi> thing, if that act of him being of <hi>one</hi> Religion himſelfe to accommodate <hi>another</hi> had been ſuch, God was not ſo put to it, he had <hi>other</hi> meanes to have brought this to paſſe, then by the <hi>ſin</hi> of any man, eſpecially then by becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>tempter</hi> thereto himſelfe. <hi>Let not any man ſay when he is tempted, that he is tempted of God, for God cannot be tempted, neither tempteth he any man:</hi> therefore if this was a temptation, 'twas not of God, if it was of God, 'twas no temptation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Gyrus</hi> was ſtirred up, but 'twas not by a Prophet that we read of, nor by a viſion, nor any extraordinary way. The Holy Ghoſt <hi>tels</hi> us he was ſtirred up, but perhaps none of his Court, nor his Princes could tell he was ſtirred up by the <hi>Lord,</hi> nor he himſelfe, the Lord might carry this force ſo ſecretly under rationall and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent conſiderations: And no queſtion he did, and ſhewed <hi>Cyrus reaſon</hi> for what he put him upon. And doe you thinke there were not politique Objections made againſt this act of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> by his Stateſinen and Counſellors (as there were to <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> with whom they prevailed for the ſuſpending of the worke that the <hi>Jewes</hi> had begun,) and was it likely <hi>Cyrus</hi> anſwered all theſe Objections to his carefull Counſellors, with the meere <hi>inſtigation</hi> he had to it <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> reaſon?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We need not feare to affirme, that <hi>Cyrus</hi> had reaſon for what he did, and did move upon <hi>reaſon</hi> in this act, (though reaſon <hi>alone</hi> would not have done it with him, there was the <hi>ſpeciall</hi> bleſſing of God upon that reaſon, and his effectuall inſtigation of <hi>Cyrus</hi> heart, making it facile and yeelding unto that reaſon) and we may <hi>aſſigne</hi> the reaſon partly what it was, at leaſt probably: 'tis couch'd in the act, which was an act of <hi>Juſtice</hi> as well as of grace: For theſe poore <hi>Jewes</hi> had in <hi>Cyrus</hi> his predeceſſors time, been <hi>wrongfully</hi> carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way captive from their own land, and the worſhip of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ever ſince in a ſtrange land, and <hi>diſabled</hi> to ſet it up againe of themſelves, and therefore <hi>Cyrus</hi> might well through the workings
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:158553:29"/>of a <hi>naturall</hi> conſcience, hold himſelfe bound to reſtore both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and utenſills, and to ſupply what ever inability or inſufficiency that accrew'd to them through their captivity: and no doubt alſo but this Principle, which it ſeemes by the ſtories in the Bible was a <hi>received</hi> one in thoſe ancient times, did glow in <hi>Cyrus</hi> his heart, that <hi>every Nation would willingly walke in the Name of their God;</hi> even as himſelfe would; and it ſeemed to him hard meaſure to reſtraine them, and therefore though as a Heathen, and ſo one that had <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> and pitcht his Religion already, he had <hi>no</hi> obligation to any <hi>other</hi> Religion but his owne, yet out of a principle of <hi>common</hi> juſtice, <hi>to doe as he would be done by,</hi> he might hold himſelfe bound to do what he did.</p>
                  <p>But it may be further objected,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">object. </seg>
                     </label> that <hi>Cyrus</hi> was in a <hi>falſe</hi> way him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and all that he did in this way of diſpenſation, he did it for the <hi>truth,</hi> and if he had done more, and left his <hi>own</hi> way, and joyn'd with the <hi>Jewes,</hi> it had been but his <hi>duty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>
                     </label> and grant, he did no more then was his duty, but yet by the Principles of <hi>ſome</hi> men in our dayes, he did <hi>over-doc</hi> his duty, nay he did <hi>contrary</hi> to his duty; if the duty of every Magiſtrate be, to be ſo zealous of his own <hi>conſcience</hi> and way, as to tolerate <hi>no</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as they affirme.</p>
                  <p>But it will be ſaid further,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">object. </seg>
                     </label> that <hi>Cyrus</hi> was <hi>convinced</hi> of the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be the true God.</p>
                  <p>Grant that,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>
                     </label> yet what was that to the <hi>inſtituted</hi> worſhip of the God of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> was he convinced of <hi>that</hi> too? Why did he not then <hi>goe up</hi> himſelfe with them to <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> No, but <hi>Cyrus</hi> was a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in <hi>worſhip</hi> ſtill: Or, Why might not <hi>Cyrus</hi> have ſaid, I know and acknowledge the true God as well as you, and do worſhip him, therefore you ſhall worſhip him after the <hi>ſame</hi> manner as I do? No, but he leaves them to their <hi>conſciences;</hi> els, if he had tyed them to his heatheniſh rites in worſhipping the true God, they had been but ſorry gainers by his converſion. Laſtly, <hi>Cyrus</hi> was convinced that the God whom <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſerved was the true God; and is that thought by you as a ſufficient reaſon for all the favour he indulged them? Why then I appeale to you, whether you have not the <hi>ſame</hi> &amp; much <hi>more</hi> reaſon to indulge as large priviledges to your differing Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, of whom you never had ſuch a ſinfull ſcruple, (I in charity thinke) <hi>whether they worſhipped the true God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:158553:29"/>
                  <p>Therefore to conclude this Inſtance; It ſeemed reaſonable to <hi>Cyrus</hi> to doe what he did in way of favour to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> though he himſelfe was of <hi>different</hi> principles from them in worſhip. For God ſcarce acts his <hi>owne</hi> people to any thing without reaſon, (much leſſe againſt reaſon) how much leſſe <hi>other</hi> men, who are not prepared with ſuch a principle of reſignation, and ſubmiſſion of will and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and all to him, as his owne are or ought to be?</p>
                  <p>The next Inſtance is of <hi>Darius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Darius.</hi>
                     </note> who (upon the occaſion of the <hi>Jewes</hi> adventuring upon the worke againe, after the proſcription of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> and a long ceſſation thereof, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.) is conſulted with by Letters from <hi>Tatnai,</hi> and <hi>Shetherboznai,</hi> Governours on the other ſide the River, what to doe, whether to ſuffer them, or to hinder them; and you have <hi>Darius</hi> his anſwer, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. which is to this purpoſe; <hi>That as upon ſearch, he found a decree of Cyrus, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them to build;</hi> ſo he charges <hi>Tatnai</hi> the Governour, &amp;c. <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therboznai,</hi> and their companions, <hi>to be far from hindring them, but to let the worke of this houſe alone, and let the Governour and Elders of the Jewes build it, in its owne place:</hi> Marke, how all is left to their conſciences: Yea moreover beſides the former indulgence and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of <hi>Cyrus, he decrees that of the Kings goods, even of the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute beyond the River, forthwith expences ſhould be miniſtred to them,</hi> (that they be not ſo much as hindred or retarded) <hi>yea and ſacrifices day by day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſerve here, 'tis not permitted, but <hi>commanded,</hi> not to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, but <hi>forthwith</hi> executed and obeyed by the Kings Officers, not to be lent, but to be <hi>given,</hi> not to be rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed of the people by tax, but to be <hi>taken</hi> out of the <hi>Kings</hi> revenue. O unparallell <hi>Darius!</hi> againſt many a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince and Magiſtrate ſhall he riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that <hi>ſnib</hi> and keep downe their own <hi>free-borne</hi> ſubjects, in the exerciſe of the <hi>ſame</hi> Religion that themſelves profeſſe, for differing in a <hi>Circumſtance</hi> comparatively. Well, the depth of <hi>Darius</hi> policy is this? that <hi>they may offer ſacrifice, and pray for the life of the King and of his children. Darius</hi> thought it but reaſonable, that if they did accommodate him and his children in their prayers, he ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate them in offering ſacrifice. <hi>Beneficium poſtulat Officium,</hi> and <hi>Officiwn</hi> relates to <hi>Beneficium.</hi> Doe yee expect our prayers, and will not let us offer ſacrifice? <hi>How can wee ſing the Lords ſong in a ſtrange land?</hi> How can wee pray for you, but as wee are bound to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:158553:30"/>pray for enemies, that God would turne their hearts, and breake the rod of their oppreſſion? But ſhall not our hearts indeed be lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up in the day of your ſhewing kindneſs and ſpeaking friendly to us, to pray for you? Wee promiſe not that we will doe it. Or doe you thinke we <hi>cannot</hi> pray, or that our prayers are nothing worth, will not <hi>ſtead</hi> you at all? or doe you not <hi>need</hi> our prayers? Wee goe on. <hi>This Decree he ratifies</hi> (doth <hi>not onely</hi> recommend an Order for their accommodation) but <hi>under the paine of a moſt exemplary death, to him that ſhould diſobey this Word, even the Timber ſhould be puld down from his houſe, to make a Gibbet to hang him on, and his houſe to be made a Dunghill,</hi> Ezr. 6.11. <hi>Concluding with a generall curſe, pronounced up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that ſhould put to their hand to alter or deſtroy that houſe,</hi> ver. 12. <hi>be they Kings or people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Will you ſee now O Magiſtrates, what you are to doe, and where to uſe your ſword and authority, even againſt thoſe that <hi>hinder</hi> the building of the houſe, that will not ſuffer the poore Saints that are inſtructed, to build the houſe according to the patterne, that they have taken out of the Word, but worke them diſturbance and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. Such you ought to puniſh; why? not becauſe they are of a <hi>differing mind</hi> and <hi>way</hi> from us, no more then you ought to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us for being of a differing mind and way from them, but if they hinder us in this worke of building the houſe of God, which <hi>they know not but</hi> we are <hi>ſtirred</hi> up of God unto (we ſay we are) and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected</hi> by him therein, (we truſt we are and ſhall be.) Therefore let them take heed in the feare of God what they doe againſt us: and thinke not you may <hi>alter</hi> the houſe, no more then <hi>deſtroy</hi> it, or that you may hinder <hi>us</hi> any more then we may hinder <hi>you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third and laſt Inſtance,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Artaxerxes.</hi>
                     </note> is of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> (not that <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> by whom the building was proſcribed, but another after him) who ſends <hi>Ezra</hi> with a large Commiſſion and authority to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> to this effect, <hi>Ezra</hi> 7.11. <hi>To take with him the reſidue of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Prieſts and Levites, that would freely goe,</hi> (he thought it not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to force them to goe, though they were of the Church by birth and Nation.) Obſerve that by the way [<hi>all that are minded of their owne free will to goe up,</hi> ver. 13.] <hi>and to carry with him the free will offering of the King and his Counſellors, in gold and ſilver, and all the ſilver and gold he could find in the Province of Babylon, with the free will offering of the Prieſts and people, to furniſh himſelfe for ſacrifice, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:158553:30"/>to doe with the overplus what ſeemed good unto him; He had alſo veſſels given him for the ſeruice of the houſe, and a liberty to take out of the Kings Treaſure-houſe, whatſoever more was needfull, (and charges his Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers accordingly to furniſh him) if it were to an hundred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>dents of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, &amp;c. And whatſoever is commanded</hi> (ſays he) <hi>by the God of Heaven, let it be diligently done.</hi> I beſeech you, what were <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to God and his worſhip, who was a ſtranger thereto, that he ſhould be more bound to take care of his houſe, and that every command of God concerning it and his worſhip there, ſhould be diligently obſerved; then Chriſtian Magiſtrates and people are now adayes? Obſerve how punctuall his naturall conſcience tells him the ſervants of God muſt be; and what proviſion he makes that they might be punctuall; and will you now on the contrary, blame, fine, impriſon them, for obſerving punctually what their confciences ſay is commanded by the God of Heaven? <hi>Furthermore, he exempts all the Miniſters of the Houſe of God from all Taxes, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizes Ezra to place and diſplace Magiſtrates, for the advantage of the true Religion, which he commends to him to promote and ſpread, as far as ever he can, ratifying this Commiſſion under the paine of heavy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to all that ſhould oppoſe, according to the degree and quality of their oppoſition:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Cyrus</hi> did this <hi>ſlaviſhly;</hi> for he addes,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">object. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <hi>Why ſhould there be wrath againſt the Realme of the King and his ſonnes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cyrus</hi> did this for feare of wrath,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="anſw."/> what then will not you doe it at all? Nay doe it <hi>for conſcience ſake,</hi> and not for wrath onely; as the Apoſtle ſays in another caſe, or God is able to bring you under the ſenſe and feare of wrath as well as <hi>Artaxerxes.</hi> Did God ſubject him to this feare (who was a Heathen, and was therefore more remote from ſuch a duty) for <hi>not furthering,</hi> and will he not judge Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Chriſtian Magiſtrates (as they will be acknowledged) for <hi>hindering</hi> the worke of his houſe? Nay, if they doe not further and incourage all they can, that all things may be done accurately and preciſely, that the God of Heaven hath commanded, leaving it to ſpirituall men to judge, who alone are able.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt Jeſus is the <hi>Prince of Peace;</hi> where he is kept out, there's trouble, and wrath. Therefore imitate at leaſt, and goe <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> farre</hi> as theſe Heathens herein; ſo ſhall <hi>wee pray for the King and his ſonnes,</hi> for our Rulers and Governours, <hi>under whom wee live peaceable lives,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:158553:31"/>in all godlineſſe and honeſty:</hi> and ſhall bleſſe God, as <hi>Ezra</hi> doth, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.27. <hi>Who hath put ſuch a thing into our Governours hearts, as to beautifie the Houſe of God, which is at Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is much the truly conſcientious expect from our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, in the name of the Lord, after the preſident of theſe Kings; Not a toleration onely, but an <hi>accommodation, incouragement,</hi> and ſufficient <hi>Protection</hi> from all moleſtation and damage. The Lord inlarge your hearts in proportion to this great duty and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Containing Examples out of the New Teſtament.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE come to the times of the New Teſtament,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sub Principib. Maccabaeis &amp; corum ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae Judaeorum ſectae, Phariſae, Sadducaei, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaei, &amp; ſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>les liberè vigueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſatis amicè inter ſe vixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> Alſt. de Eccl. l. 4. c. 14.</note> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, when there were I know not how many ſects, <hi>Caſſideans, Phariſees, Sadduces, Eſſenes, Gaulonites</hi> and <hi>Herodians:</hi> Theſe all differing from one another, as materially as Chriſtians doe now adayes. Some holding no reſurrection, no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or Spirits; others, holding all theſe, &amp;c. yet they lived by one another; yea, and our Saviour Chriſt, who lived among them three and thirty yeares, and upwards, whereof three yeares and more he ſpent in the Miniſtry, never (that we read of) ſtirr'd up the Magiſtrate to reduce them to an unity, never inſtigates thoſe that were in the right, or neareſt the truth, to proſecute the other: Our Saviour did neither feare them, nor ſpare them, but among all his woes that he pronounces, there's none againſt Magiſtrates for not forcing.</p>
                  <p>Further,
<note place="margin">Joh. Baptiſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciples were in a great error, had an envious eye upon Chriſt, and would have had their Maſter to have been the Meſſias. What doth <hi>John</hi> doe to convince them, and to right our Saviour? Doth he cudgell them into the true faith, or ſway their aſſent by his place and authority? No: but he
<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 7.19.</note> ſends them to Jeſus, to be convinced by his word and workes; and obſervable is our Saviours carriage: When theſe Meſſengers came to him, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:158553:31"/>made their errand known, he doth not require (as at other times) their Faith to bear upon his naked teſtimony of himſelfe, but he demonſtrates what he was, both by effectuall words and workes, and ſo is made manifeſt in their conſciences, as the Apoſtle ſayes elſewhere of himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Here was toleration, and giving time in Fundamentals, how much more may there, ought there to be the like in more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall differences?</p>
                  <p>And our Saviour foretels that there ſhould <hi>ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, that ſhould worke ſignes,</hi> and counterfeit the true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and <hi>deceive many.</hi> But what word ever dropt from Chriſts mouth, of violence to be uſed againſt them, as to drag them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magiſtrate, or the like? No, but he bids us beware of them, and tels us, <hi>By their fruits we ſhall know them,</hi> Mat. 7.16. And ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>By their fruits yee ſhall know them.</hi> It was our Saviours pleaſure, that there ſhould be a Chriſt and a Chriſt, Prophets and falſe Prophets, Apoſtles and falſe Apoſtles in the world; and that the one ſhould be <hi>diſtinguiſht</hi> from the other, not by any brands or eare-markes, but by their fruits, and that the one ſhould at length be overcome and <hi>extinguiſht</hi> by the other, not by might, nor by power, but by the Spirit. Even <hi>Michael contending with the Devill, brings no railing accuſation, but the Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo what differences were there after our Saviours depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in the Apoſtles dayes, about <hi>obſerving dayes, eating meat ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to Idols, Circumciſion, covering the head or face in worſhip,</hi> and the like; ſome of which were Church-differences; and how doth the Apoſtle endeavour to compoſe them, but by argument and reaſon, by reproving, exhorting, convincing? and where he meets with contentious ſpirits, what ſays he? <hi>We have no ſuch cuſtome, nor any of the Churches of God.</hi> Others were differences that diffuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves further, then in one particular Church, taking unſtable minds up and downe (perhaps) every where; as the <hi>oppoſition of the Law to the Goſpel and Circumciſion, &amp;c.</hi> Now how did the Apoſtles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves here, who were armed and inſtructed with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power and authority for the vindicating of the truth, then ever any ſince, either Civill or Eccleſiaſticall perſons; and when occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, ſhewed it, ſtriking <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> dead in the place, for lying in the face of the Holy Ghoſt, and their own conſciences?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:158553:32"/>I ſay,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Paul</hi> in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry caſes.</note> how did theſe men behave themſelves? Why, <hi>Paul</hi> is very hot (as one could wiſh) in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> he workes his head, and writes, and chides, and inſinuates, and exhorts, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces; <hi>If an Angel from Heaven, &amp;c.</hi> He was as warme as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were, when they called for <hi>fire from Heaven;</hi> as warme as any are now in the caſe of Church-government; but his zeale expreſſes it ſelfe the right way. Indeed, he hath one ſmart paſſage, <hi>I would they were even cut off that trouble you,</hi> but he cals not upon man to cut them off. Again, <hi>Paul</hi> knew in what cauſe he ſaid it, not in a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cauſe, wherein he might have been wrong, and they right, but he ſpeakes this in a full aſſurance and demonſtration of the truth by the Spirit; and 'tis but a committing the judgement to God. In other Epiſtles we finde errours and hereſies lay in <hi>Pauls</hi> way, and in the way of the truth: and thereupon he cals upon the Miniſters to quit themſelves, and ſhews how they had need to be furniſhed and accompliſht, that they may exhort and convince gain-ſayers; and they muſt doe it with patience and meekneſſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. Some indeed muſt be <hi>rebuked ſharply, that they may be ſound in the faith.</hi> But here's no calling to, nor authorizing any to exerciſe any forcible coaction.</p>
                  <p>And (yet not to have done with <hi>Paul</hi>) who had ſpirit enough for the truth, yet where he might, how did he <hi>become all things to all men? to the Jewes he was as a Jew, &amp;c.</hi> Not by an unworthy diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, putting on any forme, to the humours of the preſent company, but by a friendly accord, and walking with them, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thoſe differences; that his preſence was no more dreadfull, nor his company any more unpleaſant to them, then if he were one of their own, a Jew, or of the Circumciſion. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Apoſtle held forth an eminent practiſe of his owne Rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. who after he had arbitrated in many Controverſies, in the foregoing part of the Epiſtle, and laboured to compound their differences, and to bring them to an uniformity in the right order, (which if it may be had, I grant is not indifferently deſireable) <hi>yet</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſhew I unto you a more excellent way:</hi> and that is the way of <hi>charity</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> as it follows: which is better then to have a mans mind poliſhed with the pureſt notions and livelieſt apprehenſions. Its better for Chriſtians to be able to exerciſe abundance of love in differences, then to jump all juſt in a judgement. For Muſick is not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:158553:32"/>made with one ſtring, nor with many ſtrings ſet to the ſame note, but of various notes and ſtrings, rightly ſet and ſubdued to a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, is the ſweeteſt muſick, and of differing Inſtruments. Indeed, if they be not ſo ſet and ſubdued, the variety makes but a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant craſhing confuſion: ſo it is in this caſe of different judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with or without love. As order is ſaid to be the forme of the univerſe, ſo love may be ſaid to be the forme of the Church, which makes us all one, and uſefull to one another in what we have, pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and pardoning one another in what we have not.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, <hi>Paul</hi> foreſaw that as there were great, ſo there would be greater errors, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.29. <hi>For I know this</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, ſhall grievous wolves enter in, &amp;c. Alſo of your owne ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, drawing Diſciples after them.</hi> But what courſe doth <hi>Paul</hi> adviſe them to? but bids them therefore <hi>watch, and remember how by the ſpace of three yeares, he had warned eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryone of them night and day with teares,</hi> ver. 31. Yet are wee to have (after <hi>Pauls</hi> example) a ſerious zeale againſt pernicious doctrines, and the obſtinate diſſeminators of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Examples and Teſtimonies recorded and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us by humane Writings.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hall we fall downe from theſe times (the ſacred Stories going no further) to the ſucceeding times continued by other Hiſtories, <hi>Euſebius, Theodoret,</hi> and others, out of whom (and eſpecially out of an unparalleld golden Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript I have ſeene, which I wholly leave to tell his owne Tale) many Inſtances, very pregnant and commendable, might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, principally in the times of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and his ſonnes, and both the <hi>Theodoſius<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es,</hi> and ſome other Emperours, who tolerated divers wayes, and preſerved the peace between the ſeverall profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of them; but that it would increaſe the bulke of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, far beyond what was intended, therefore I ſhall content my ſelfe with one onely, that indeed an eminent one.</p>
                  <p>And before I bring forth that, I muſt vindicate the truth from
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:158553:33"/>needing that one, or any humane teſtimonies; and though it be lawfull to bring them, yet I would not <hi>be brought under the power</hi> of ſuch an obligation. But they may ſtand us in good ſtead, thus far, to induce an eare that is inclined to Antiquity and Authority. And what wee ſee of this kinde in darke times, in men voyd of Religion, and ſufficiently zealous of their own ſuperſtition, is like to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to reaſon, and the principles of naturall light; and ſo this Inſtance or Inſtances will have much authority with them, and a vertue not onely <hi>illuſtrative,</hi> but <hi>argumentative.</hi> The Inſtance is this;</p>
                  <p>Many complaints were brought by them of <hi>Aſia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Marcus Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Antonius. Euſeb. Eccl. Hiſt.</note> the Elders and Judges thereof, to the Emperour <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antonius,</hi> (as to his Father before him) upon occaſion of an Earth-quake which did them great damage,) againſt the Chriſtians, who by reaſon of their different Religion were <hi>their</hi> envy, &amp; a great eye-ſore to them, charging theſe Chriſtians to be the cauſe of that Earth-quake, (as was their manner upon every miſ-fortune that befell them, and to cry out againſt them, <hi>Ad Leones</hi>) even as now all the faction and tumult is laid upon tender Conſciences; to whom the Emperour anſwers thus, — <hi>De motibus autem terrae, &amp;c. Comperi quod in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſcemodi rebus, ad illorum invidiam, communes caſus transfertis, &amp;c. — Super quibus plurimis ex Provinciis Judices etiam venerabili Patri noſtro ſcripſerunt. Quibus reſcriptum eſt ab eo, ut nihil omnino moleſtiae, hujuſcemodi hominibus generarent, niſi fortè arguerentur, aliquid adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Romani Regni ſtatum moliri. Sed &amp; mihi ipſi, de his quam plurimi retulerunt, quibus ego paternam ſecutus ſententiam, pari moderatione re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripſi. Quod ſi quis perſiſtit hujuſcemodi hominibus abſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ullo crimine movere negotia, ille quidem qui delatus pro hoc nomine fuerit, abſolvatur, etiamſi probetur id eſſe quod ei objicitur, Chriſtianus; is autem qui cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men obtendit, reus poenae ipſius quam objecit, exiſtat.</hi> The ſumme of it in Engliſh is this; <hi>That as for the Earth-quake, he hath found by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that they doe put common accidents upon their</hi> (i. <hi>the Chriſtians</hi>) <hi>account out of envy, and commands them as his Father had done before, not to worke theſe men any trouble, except they ſhould be found to attempt any thing againſt the Roman Empire. If any did cauſeleſly moleſt them, the Chriſtian ſhould goe free, and his accuſer ſhould ſuffer the puniſhment he would bring upon him.</hi> Here's now a Heathen, not onely tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a contrary Religion to his own (for he remained a very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:158553:33"/>ſtill, as the firſt paſſage of his Epiſtle ſhews; <hi>Ego quidem non ambigo Diis ipſis cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ae eſſe ne quis noxius lateat; Multo enim magis illis convenit punire eos qui ipſis immo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>are nolunt, quam vobis</hi>) but counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing and pleading for it, not onely not impeaching it of facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but implicitly clearing of it, not onely providing for their eſcape of unjuſt puniſhment, but making an Ordinance to doe them juſtice upon their cauſleſſe accuſers. How ſhall this Emperour riſe up in judgement at the laſt day, againſt many in theſe dayes?</p>
                  <p>How many of the Ancients have father'd this opinion of mine,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auſtin</hi> how he came to be againſt us.</note> I take not upon me to tell. But <hi>Auſtin</hi> once for us, afterwards got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from us, by what means, I ſhall give you account out of <hi>Peter Martyr: At<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> haec ratio fuit cur Auguſtinus cum anteà judicaſſet, non oportere Magiſtratum anim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dvertere in Haereticos, poſteà mutavit ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam: Alii enim Epiſcopi proferebant multas Eccleſias, quae met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorum &amp; Legum, à Donatiſtarum factione deſciviſſent, &amp; jam aſſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine cognoviſſent Catholicam veritatem, ut nullo pacto vellent ab eâ diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere; The Biſhops of ſeverall places told him what great ſucceſſe the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours force had to reclaime men from Donatiſme.</hi> But ſucceſſe alone is not a rule for wiſe men to goe by, in as much as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays; <hi>That there be juſt men</hi> (and ſo juſt wayes) <hi>to whom it happeneth according to the worke of the wicked, and there be wicked men,</hi> (and ſo wicked wayes) <hi>unto whom it happeneth according to the worke of the righteous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zanchy</hi> puts the <hi>Criſis</hi> of the utmoſt extent of the Magiſtrates au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, not upon all evill manners, domeſticall or publique,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zanchy.</hi>
                     </note> except they diſturbe the publique peace, or hinder the publique good; though yet they may fall under the Churches Cognizance, yea cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. His words are theſe; <hi>There are many wickedneſſes, againſt which the Magiſtrate truly Chriſtian, doth not uſe to proceed, neither is bound by his lawes; is alſo many evill manners, both domeſticall and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, which doe not diſturbe the publique peace, on the publique good: But the Church ought not to beare theſe, but to correct them according to Chriſts inſtitution.</hi> Now then if by <hi>Zanchies</hi> rule, <hi>diſturbing the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique peace and good,</hi> is that which brings in the Magiſtrate, and gives him Cognizance of miſdemeanours and wickedneſſes, then by his judgement, errours in faith, or practiſe of Religion, are not within the Magiſtrates Cognizance, except they be ſuch in their nature or managing, as diſturb the publique peace. Which is all that wee aske.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:158553:34"/>
                  <p>And how far the ſpirits of many now are from the moderation of later Authors and Writers,
<note place="margin">Alſted.</note> I might ſhew. <hi>Alſted</hi> delivers his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition thus upon the Queſtion; <hi>De pace Religionis, (ut vocant) ſeu de libertate Religionis, ſive de bono autonomie: An &amp; quatenus concedi poſſit à pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Magiſtratu? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi licet nos concedamus unam duntax it Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem, quam videlicet ipſe Magiſtratus veram agnoſcit ex verbo Dei, ab eodem Magiſtratu, pro virili conſervandam eſſe, neminem tamen ad ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem externâ aliqua vi cogendum eſſe docemus: quin potius ſuam Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiis libertatem relinquendam: Et non nunquam etiam diverſarum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionum exercitium, ſi non publicum, ſaltem privatum, aut clandeſtinum ex ſingularibus cauſis permittendum eſſe ſtatuimus. At<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> hoc demum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu pacem &amp; concordiam externam ſeu politiam inter Orthodoxos &amp; non orthodoxos, ſaepe etiam haereticos ſimul colendam, ab ipſo pio Magiſtratu procurari, &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe &amp; debere exiſtimamus.</hi> I could not wiſh my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more happily expreſt, nor words more accommodate to my ſenſe, <hi>viz. That though the Magiſtrate be with might and maine to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend but one Religion, even that which he judges to be the truth by the Word of God; yet none ought to be compeld to that by outward force, but every mans Conſcience to be left at liberty, &amp;c.</hi> (I ſhall not Engliſh it all;) <hi>and that a Civill externall peace ſhould be maintain'd by the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Magiſtrate, even between Orthodox and Heterodox.</hi> And he gives three
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <p>Prima niti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus illis ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae dictis, quę juſtitiam &amp; charitatem ſtudium<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> pacis &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cordiae ſeriò nobis omnibus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendant: &amp; ne quid alitèr adverſus proximum ſtatuamus, quàm qualitèr nobiſcum agi velle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus diſertè praecipiunt. Deni<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ut conſcientiis ſuam libertatem concedamus &amp; diſſentientes in negotio Religionis amicè toleremus, omnino mandant, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.14. &amp; alibi.</p>
                        <p>Secunda petitur ab exemplis ſapientium &amp; piorum Principu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tum in veteri tum in N. Teſt. &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>Tertia ab ipſa naturali equitate item<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> adjuncta utilitate, quàm etiam experientia quotidiana fere comprobat. Nam praeterquam quod aequiſſimum eſt, in cauſa Religionis ab omni vi &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actione externa abſtinere, ipſis etiam rebus publicis ut ita fiat, omnino expedit, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> conducit; quippe quae alioqui facillimè turbarentur, &amp; inteſtinis bellis, ac mutuis lanienis tandem conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derent: prout hactenus in multis Europae provinciis, Gallia praeſertim &amp; B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>gio, accidiſſe novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Cum contrà in Germania, Helvetia, Polonia, &amp; alibi locorum, in quibus Religionum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> hactenus indulta fuit, iſtis diſcordiis &amp; lanienis, non fuerit locus. Ergo res ipſa perſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita, &amp; bona eſt, etiamſi per accidens abuſus aliquis accedere poſſit. <hi>Alſt. de Eccl. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</p>
                     </note> Reaſons for his judgement, which I ſhall transject into the Margent.</p>
                  <p>And what Reformation this Kingdome had in the late dayes, it did conſiſt in the incoaction or ſpontaneouſneſs of it in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">Humſred. de verâ Relig. &amp;c.</note> whatſoever it did in the people; as one reports of it; <hi>Nam in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:158553:34"/>ſenatu, ut fertur, patuit omnibus ad dicendum locus, nec ulli hominum generi poteſtas contradicendi, ſuam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fidem profitendi intercluſa eſt; imò integrum fuit cui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> liberis velitari ac pugnare ſententiis, in quo ſumma elucet aequitas &amp; moderatio Principum, qui allicere, ducere, perſuadere; non cogere, trahere, jubere voluerunt; ut impudens mendacium ſit, ſi quis jam dixerit, authoritatem viciſſe, non vecitatem. Illud etiam conſtat, liberum fuiſſe adverſariae parti in publica diſputatione ſuas partes tueri, arbitris adhibitis incorruptioribus, ſive voce ſive calamo certare, ſive oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, ſive reſpondere maluiſſent.</hi> Humfr. de vera Relig. conſerv. p. 31, 32.</p>
                  <p>I quote the words, becauſe if they had never been realized, yet the <hi>Idea</hi> of ſuch a carriage when men are ſeeking out the truth is lovely, as being very equall and rationall.</p>
                  <p>And if I were in <hi>Davids</hi> caſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. without my ſword and weapons, I might tranſlate two or three pages out of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Edwards Antapology.</hi> I ſhall produce but a paſſage or two, <hi>p.</hi> 168. he hath theſe <q>words; Now the remedies appointed for theſe (<hi>viz.</hi> Church-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; matters of Conſcience, and the inward man) are ſpirituall and Eccleſiaſticall, namely, ſpirituall puniſhments. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>My kingdome is not of this world:</hi> and the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3, 4, 5. <hi>The weapons of our warfare are not carnall, but mighty through God, to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds,</hi> by which the ſpirit, and the inward man, even every thought is ſubjected to the obedience of Chriſt. Spirituall remedies and meanes muſt be uſed in the kingdome of Chriſt, and by them Chriſt doth his worke; and hence in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Diſcipline, and thoſe ſcandals in the Church, all the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments in the body, and in the purſe, which can be by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, have no place, neither can ſuch means which are of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent kinde from the ſpirituall kingdome of Chriſt, produce thoſe effects which belong to that heavenly kingdome. 'Tis out of the ſpheare of the activity of the Politicall Magiſtrate to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the inward man, or to inflict ſpirituall puniſhment upon the Conſcience, &amp;c.</q> Thus M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Edwards,</hi> and far more, which I muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit for brevity ſake. Therefore I hope he will not thinke it meet to preſſe the Magiſtrates power in the <hi>Presbyteries</hi> quarrell, relating to <hi>Church-matters,</hi> &amp;c. which here he ſo expreſly declines.</p>
                  <p>To tell what <hi>Triglandius,</hi> and the <hi>Walacbrian</hi> and <hi>Leyden</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors ſay in this point, were to tranſlate Volumes worthy of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct labour by it ſelfe. For theſe that are produced, I have not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:158553:35"/>puld them from the ſhockes of any Diſcourſes of this Argument, already prepared and digeſted, which were a labour thankleſſe and needleſſe, but have gleaned and gathered theſe fragments here and there from places alien enough from this ſubject (at leaſt deſigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,) that there might be no loſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Wherein Objections are anſwered.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Shall begin with the great and maine Objection of all,
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">object. </seg>1</label>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> the Example of the Kings of <hi>Juda, Aſa, Jehoſaphat, Hezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> who reduced the people to the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, by compulſory meanes; For 'tis ſaid of <hi>Aſa's</hi> refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. <hi>That they entred into a Covenant, to ſeeke the Lord God of their Fathers; and that whoſoever would not, ſhould be put to death:</hi> And of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 Chron. 34.32. that renuing the Covenant firſt himſelfe, he <hi>cauſed alſo all that were preſent in Jeruſalem and Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin to ſtand to it.</hi> He [cauſed] them.</p>
                  <p>To this I might give a manifold anſwer;
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>1</label> as firſt I might wiſh you to look into the particulars of their Reformation, whereabout they exerciſed a compulſive power; and it will be found to be about maine ſubſtantiall fundamentall things; not ſuch as the preſent dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences among Chriſtians; ſo that the Argument comes not home to the Caſe and Queſtion. There might be different opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Reformiſts of <hi>Judah,</hi> notwithſtanding that they did all ſeeke the Lord God of their Fathers; and it might be indulged to them in thoſe opinions, though they were compelled to this.</p>
                  <p>Againe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the compulſion they exerciſed in the matter of ſeeking the Lord God of their Fathers, was by expreſſe poſitive law, warranted, yea and inſtituted, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.9. For 'twas no other then that law that this practiſe refer'd unto; which is the law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt inticing to Idolatry; to which law they had given their formall and expreſſe conſent, to the very letter of it; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as a reward the land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> which alſo they injoyed on that condition. Which law, if the equity of it hold ſtill, (and it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:158553:35"/>were not a temporary judiciall law peculiar to that Nation that was Church and Nation interchangeably) yet will it not impeach or prejudice the liberty and forbearance here ſued for; we plead not for manifeſt Idolatry, nor any ſuch practiſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is againſt the light of Nature.</p>
                  <p>But thirdly, Whatſoever they did rightly, (and what ever they might have done more, in this kind, perhaps,) yet cannot be drawn into preſident by us, and that becauſe there is not <hi>par
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Vid. Trigland.</hi> 1 <hi>De poteſtate Civili &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticâ. c.</hi> 12.</note> ratio</hi> for it now. As I ſhall ſhew in a foure-fold difference of thoſe times, and theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, thoſe were the times of the old Teſtament, theſe of the New, therefore 'tis not a ſound way of arguing from them to us in every thing; If they were under Tutors and Governours, it doth not follow that we muſt be ſo, nay the Apoſtle ſayes the contrary; if the Church in her nonage was uſed more like a ſervant then a ſon, muſt they therefore when they are growne up? How ever it was that their ſervice was compulſorily required from them, wee have a word that ours ſhould be free, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. <hi>Thy people ſhall be
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaria.</hi> The word comes from the ſame root that is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.2 &amp; Chap. 35.5. Where cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is put in, that all their offerings to the rearing of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle ſhould be moſt free: and the thing ſprings from the ſame e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and the example of Goſpel-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts confirms it, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41. yea, and the rule of ſuch converſſon, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 25, 26.</note> willing in the day of thy power,</hi> which day of Chriſts power, is the times of the Goſpel adaequately, though ſome more ſpeciall time may (I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not) be refer'd unto, and ſome more eminent accompliſhment of this promiſe, by a ſubdiviſion of the times of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Their worſhip was carnall, bodily, outward, conſiſting much in the conformity of the outward man and practiſe to certain worldly Ordinances, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. to the production and preſervation of which the inſtanced meanes of the Magiſtrates compulſion might beare a great proportion of ſufficiency and efficacy. But the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the New Teſtament is chiefly in the heart, and hidden man, in ſpirit and in truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. Which is at the back of no humane force or power: therefore it is no good argument from that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to this.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> (as it is generally received) had a peculiar Notion from Kings now; therefore 'tis no good argument from them to theſe; For they had not onely a Civill notion, but an Eccleſiaſticall alſo, which ours have not; They were types of Chriſt the King of the Church, and did bear viſibly and execute typically his Kingly office, (even as Prieſts and Prophets did his other two offices,) as is manifeſt by thoſe glorious promiſes of dominion and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:158553:36"/>ſtability, that are made to Chriſt in the perſons of the Kings of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah;</hi> and to bring home this exception, what is alledg'd to be done by them in the foregoing inſtances of compelling the people, was done by vertue of their Eccleſiaſticall Notion. But now the caſe is otherwiſe. Our Kings are onely the Miniſters of God in the world, (ruling indeed <hi>for</hi> the Church, not <hi>in</hi> the Church, and <hi>over</hi> it as then,) neither are they anointed in any ſuch Notion as <hi>They</hi> were, that is, to execute the Kingly office of Chriſt in his Church.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, The people of the <hi>Jewes</hi> were interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably a Church &amp; a Nation, (ſo that he who was head of the State, was ſo alſo of the Church in a typicall way; as he that was a member of the Common-wealth, was by that a member of the Church, and <hi>vice verſa</hi>) which no people ever ſince were, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Argument will not hold from <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation: and this compulſive power that was exerciſed by the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> among them, did relate to this Notion. Now then to any other Nation, that neither is nor can be lookt upon under ſuch a Notion, ſuch a diſcipline is not applicable: For a ſpirituall body as the Church, and a ſpirituall power or juriſdiction, (as if it be Chriſts it is,) are relatives, and as <hi>poſito relato ponitur &amp; correla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum: ſo ſublato uno relatorum tollitur &amp; alterum.</hi> Now though I know a Nationall Church in one ſenſe is the apple of ſome mens eye, (and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Prin</hi> of late hath endeavoured to make a lid for it with a numerous quotation out of the old and new Teſtament, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.7. &amp;c. But thoſe places doe no more hold forth <hi>Nationall</hi> Converſions and Churches, then the 12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 47. <hi>&amp; Eph.</hi> 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2. which ſpeak of Chriſts dying for the ſins of the <hi>world,</hi> yea the <hi>whole</hi> world, doe hold forth <hi>univerſall</hi> redemption.) Yet in this ſenſe they will none of them hold it; That as in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo in <hi>England,</hi> ſo in <hi>Scotland</hi> the Nation is holy, and all that are borne in it are of the Church <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> or <hi>ipſo natu;</hi> and if not ſo, then may not Chriſts Kingly Scepter, which relates onely to his Church, be ſwayed over them all generally. Therefore Kings or Magiſtrates may not now as then compell men to Religion: But that which thoſe Kings did in a typicall way, Chriſt the King of his Church doth in a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all antitypical way of accompliſhment; that is, as <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> the type diſtributed the knowledge and feare of the Lord by his Princes, (or
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> The chiefe ones.</note> chiefe Prieſts, for ſo the word may be rendred indifferently) with
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:158553:36"/>the aſſiſtance of Levites through his Dominions (which was Chriſts dominion and the Church adaequately then;) ſo Chriſt Jeſus the true King, it is his part, (and he did it when he aſcended, giving gifts to men,) efficaciouſly to apply and bring home to his Church the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of his Prieſtly and Propheticall office; and ſo might their other acts be paralleld by the Antitype.</p>
                  <p>Another Objection like unto the former, is Uniformity.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Object.</hi> 2.</note> How ſhall there be uniformity, if there be this liberty?</p>
                  <p>Unity there is and ought to be,
<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and uniformity alſo is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured after, becauſe the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Whereto we have attained, let us walke by the ſame rule,</hi> Phil. 3.16. But this cannot be in all things attained, more then to thinke the ſame thing, to which yet wee are alſo exhorted. <hi>There is one body,</hi> the Apoſtle ſays,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>and one ſpirit, even as we are called in one hope of our calling; One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God, and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in us all.</hi> Here's unity over and over, but this doth not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily draw uniformity after it in all things. Nay the Apoſtle ſays the quite contrary. <hi>But to every one of us is given grace, according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt;</hi> Not to every one the ſame gift, nor the ſame meaſure. As not to every Officer, ſo not to every Church, nor to every Chriſtian; much leſſe to every man. The rule holds proportionably throughout, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4. And wherefore doth the Apoſtle ſo urge and inſiſt upon unity, but partly, if not chiefly to ſalve up the want of uniformity? as <hi>ver.</hi> 3. doth ſhew. For <hi>ver.</hi> 2. he exhorts them to the duty (contended for through this diſcourſe,) of forbearing one another in love, (that is, in caſe of differences it muſt be ſuppoſed) not ſo much as to cenſure one another; (much leſſe to proſecute one another) and as an Argument to this forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, he minds them of their unity, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. Now what need were there of preſſing to unity where there is uniformity, <hi>(Saevis inter ſe convenit urſis,)</hi> where all are of a ſtraine? What needs a bond of peace, where there are no crackes nor flawes of diviſion? Neither were the preſervation of peace upon ſuch termes thank-worthy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Again, to require uniformity in a compulſory way, is to bind heavier burdens on the Churches, then Chriſt hath laid upon them: Doth not the Apoſtle ſay mercifully,
<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Nevertheleſs</hi> (that is, notwithſtanding all our particular &amp; ſeverall apprehenſions) <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto we have attained, let us walke together by the ſame Rule, and if any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:158553:37"/>man be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveale even this unto him.</hi> To vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late unity in the zeale of uniformity, is a bargain as will never make us rich.
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Wilt thou for meat,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>deſtroy him for whom Chriſt dyed?</hi> Gold may be bought too deare, ſo may uniformity. And is it not as vaine an expectation to have all men of one appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion in all things, as to have all men of the ſame ſtature or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, or their faces to be all alike? Is it not the glory of heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly myſteries, that <hi>as the Heavens for height, and the earth for depth,</hi> ſo they ſhould be of an infinite inſcrutability, and exerciſe the parts and acuteneſſe of men in an endleſſe variety? But laſtly, Uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was the Biſhops Argument (and let it dye with them) having in it more of name then of realty. As the Apoſtle ſays in the caſe of ſinging, be ſure it be done with a gracefull heart, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Making melody in our ſpirits,</hi> els a gracefull and melodious voice is a bawble, for God is a Spirit: So we may ſay in the matter in hand; There is indeed an outward uniformity, but this is nothing in compariſon of the inward uniformity which conſiſts in the having the ſame Chriſt in all our hearts, working the ſame workes of mortification and vivification in us: and this is not called indeed by ſo ſleight a name as Uniformity; 'tis Unity as before: Without which, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity is an abomination; but where unity is, uniformity may be, nay, muſt be diſpens'd withall, except it may be had upon eaſier termers then compulſion.</p>
                  <p>And let me adviſe thoſe that are thus bent for uniformity, and would purchaſe it at any rate, in <hi>Solomons</hi> words; <hi>Be not righteous over much, neither make thy ſelfe over-wiſe, why ſhouldst thou deſtroy thy ſelfe?</hi> as by ſuch burning and conſuming zeale and ſollicitude, which will never ſee anſwerable fruit; for God hath ſaid, <hi>there muſt be hereſies,</hi> and there ſhall be ſo, &amp; all this over-care will <hi>not adde one cubit</hi> to the Churches <hi>ſtature:</hi> And it is againſt your own happineſs to have a will thus ingaged to impoſſibilities: You cannot poſſeſſe your ſelves in peace. God ſings a <hi>requiom</hi> to himſelfe in all theſe, for all things ſucceed according to his purpoſe, and when we have ſhewed due care, and uſed all due meanes for preventing, for reclar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming errours, we ſhould be quiet too. For that which is crooked, can no man make ſtraight, and that which is wanting, cannot be numbred. Take heed of an evill eye;
<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 28.22.</note> 
                     <hi>He that haſteth to be rich,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon, hath an evill eye;</hi> So likewiſe hath he whoſe eye will be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:158553:37"/>with nothing but uniformity; 'tis an eye that covets an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attaineable happines, though I know not whether I may terme it happines, and whether it be not a greater happines, that Saints dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in the judgement and practiſe of ſome things, can yet love one another, and keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace notwithſtanding.
<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 2.24.</note> 
                     <hi>There is nothing better</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays in another caſe) <hi>then that a man eat and drinke, and make his ſoule injoy good in his labour;</hi> ſo ſay I, nothing better then to rejoyce in that proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and degree of truth and peace which God gives one to ſee: and know this, that as he ſays of proſperity and adverſity, ſo the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion holds of truths and errours: <hi>God hath ſet the one over againſt the other, to the intent that man ſhould find nothing after him,</hi> (i.) that we might reſolve our full contentment and joyfull reſt into Jeſus Chriſt alone.</p>
                  <p>Further, that place is objected againſt the deſired liberty,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11. <hi>For there are many unruly and vaine talkers, eſpecially they of the Circumciſion, whoſe mouthes muſt be ſtopped.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I am almoſt in an agony between compaſſion and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     </note> that godly men ſhould make Scripture lackey ſo to their owne conceits againſt the lawes of all genuine interpretation. I am for <hi>ſtopping of monthes</hi> too. But there are more wayes of <hi>ſtopping</hi> mens mouthes then one; as if you ſtop not your eyes and eares I ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you. Mens mouthes may be ſtopt, not onely by force, but with arguments. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>That every mouth may be ſtopped, and all the world may become guilty before God.</hi> What ſtopping is that there? Doe we not ſay, then a mans mouth is ſtopt when he hath nothing to ſay, when he is convinced or confounded with a power of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon brought againſt him? Looke but a little higher then the text, and ſee whether this be not the ſtopping there meant; For from <hi>ver.</hi> 7. the Apoſtle is ſhewing how a Biſhop muſt be qualified, not onely outwardly, <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8. but inwardly, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Holding faſt the faithfull Word, as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, both to exhort and convince the gain-ſayers.</hi> And it follows im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, <hi>for there are many unruly, and vaine talkers, and deceivers, &amp;c. whoſe mouthes muſt be ſtopped.</hi> Need I now ſhew you, how their mouthes muſt be ſtopped? Is it not plaine, 'tis the Biſhops Office, not the Magiſtrates: Not Lord Biſhops, but labouring Biſhops; not by his <hi>fift,</hi> bin by <hi>ſound doctrine;</hi> not by <hi>conventing</hi> them before the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:158553:38"/>Magiſtrate, but by <hi>convincing</hi> them in their conſciences. Now deare Brethren, if any of you have oppreſſed this Scripture with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull load of a Magiſteriall reſtraint of conſcience bearing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and if your mouths be now ſtopped, open them againe, and free the truth that hath made you free.</p>
                  <p>But how ſhall errours be reſtrained,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> if yee allow not Coercive power?</p>
                  <p>To reſtraine errours is a good worke,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     </note> but it muſt not be done by <hi>unrighteous</hi> meanes. If Gods glory may abound through my lye, it doth not make it lawfull for me to lye: But how ſhall errours be cut off? How? by the Word, which is the ſword of the Spirit, and it is for want of faith applyed to this meanes, that wee ſee ſo little fruit of it; and it is the policy of Satan to hide the efficacy of this meanes from us, and by making us zealous of a falſe, to divert us from the uſe of the true and proper meanes. Looke upon the Word as an <hi>inſtitution,</hi> and what can it not doe? <hi>The Word of God is quicks and powerfull;</hi> and you will never ſubdue errors, till you take to this courſe. The Devill joyes to ſee us upon courſes of violence againſt the perſons, even of erroneous men; what, is it becauſe he <hi>hates</hi> er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and hereſies? No, by them he alſo <hi>raignes,</hi> as well as by viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions; But he had <hi>rather</hi> yee ſhould fight againſt them with the <hi>ſword,</hi> then with the <hi>Word;</hi> and the reaſon is, becauſe the Word is Gods meanes, the ſword is mans; the Word is an Inſtitution, the ſword is our invention: the Word is a ſpirituall meanes, (and thoſe are mighty, as the Angels are above men) the ſword is a carnall meanes; God ſtands ingaged to make good his Word, and then 'tis no matter how weake and unlikely the meanes be, if God be bound for it; 'Tis the Inſtitution beſtowes that force and efficacy upon it; If God inſtitute a bit of bread, and a ſip of wine, in ſuch a uſe of it, to ſtrengthen my faith, it ſhall doe it. Thoſe brave men, Souldiers and Armies, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. had not obtained thoſe great victories and atchievements, but through faith; and had they been far weaker then they were, yet with faith they had done never the leſſe. The moſt ſpecious probable meanes without an Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is nothing; the pooreſt with an Inſtitution is almighty.</p>
                  <p>Aske not then, How ſhall men be preſerved from errours? for if they be intereſted in Church-fellowſhip fixedly, they have the proviſion of many Inſtitutions, and Ordinances, to be imployed for
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:158553:38"/>them, and applyed to them: the doctrine, practiſe, prayers, parts, and utmoſt help of Elders and Brethren, with the ſpeciall bleſſing of the relation, in and upon all and each of theſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. <hi>For there the Lord commanded the bleſſing, &amp;c.</hi> But if not ſo intereſted, or not ſo diſtinctly, or not in ſo pure a Church, that conſcientiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſes that mutuall inſpection, and care of one another: yet God hath not left himſelfe to any of his ſervants without witneſſe of a due care of their ſoules, in this concernment, nor left any of his people without ſufficient meanes.
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.20.</note> 
                     <hi>Yee have an unction which teacheth you all things,</hi> is not ſpoken peculiarly to Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, though in a larger proportion perhaps to them but God takes care of all his elect: if it had not been ſo, Chriſt would have told us; If it were not ſo, Chriſt would not make a <hi>ſi poſſibile</hi> of their being ſeduced,
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 24.24.</note> 
                     <hi>They ſhall deceive, if it be poſſible, the very elect.</hi> Let's not diſtruſt our cauſe, nor the truth in conflicting with errours, <hi>Tandem vincet veritas,</hi> Truth ſhall overcome: and let's not diſtruſt Chriſt, but that as he kept his owne while he was with them on earth, and recommended them to his Father at his departure: ſo he will not faile to keepe them now, that <hi>all power is given into his hands, the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt them.</hi> Let's commit this truſt to Chriſt, ſo ſhall we ingage him: a man will looke to be truſted, or he will not count himſelfe ingaged.</p>
                  <p>But we ſee many of the Elect (for ought that we can judge,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> woe dare not thinke otherwiſe of them) are carried away with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent errours.</p>
                  <p>No better a ground or conſideration would I deſire to mollifie any reaſonable man towards men in Errours:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     </note> The Elect are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to them, therefore exact not too ſtrict an account of all men. If there are many that ſhall live in heaven notwithſtanding their errours, it is no ſin to let them live on earth.</p>
                  <p>But we ſhall have no peace in the earth.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whoſe fault is that? Why,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     </note> cannot yee live peaceably by differing Brethren? The fault of variance, ſtrife, and envyings, lyes not in the <hi>judgement,</hi> but in the <hi>will,</hi> not in the <hi>head,</hi> but in the <hi>heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But differing opinions will be contending for victory.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>If there be pride, not els:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 14.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Onely through pride comes contention.</hi> Opinions may ſtrive, yet men may agree. There may be <hi>pugna logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calis,</hi> and yet <hi>pax moralis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:158553:39"/>
                  <p>But civill warres and ſeditions have ſprung from different o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>I grant opinions may be managed and actuated by turbulent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     </note> in a ſeditious, factious, tumultuous way: and in ſuch caſe the Magiſtrate muſt come in indeed: and none ſhould run faſter to call him then I would: if any party or kinde of men, doe either trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly undermine, or violently aſſault their Brethren, that live ſecurely by them, inoffenſively exerciſing their conſciences, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it is <hi>a matter to be puniſhed by the Judges;</hi> be the aſſaylants ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much in the right, and the ſufferers in ſome errours, yet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly and harmleſly managed.</p>
                  <p>There is another Objection,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Object.</hi>
                     </note> and no meane one, though of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular nature and force, relating not to all perſons concerned in the common cauſe of the argument of this diſcourſe, but peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us in theſe three united Kingdomes, and that is the <hi>Nationall Covenant,</hi> which is charg'd home in the <hi>Antapology,</hi> and made to ſpeake (for there are that can make any thing ſpeake what they liſt) againſt the deſired liberty.</p>
                  <p>But firſt, if this Covenant be applyed no otherwiſe then was at firſt intended, (which without greateſt ingratitude and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe I cannot admit,) in being thus made a barre and prejudice againſt the free diſquiſition of truth, (as in effect it is) I know not how the Authors of ſuch a project could be innocent. But to wave the <hi>intention,</hi> there is nothing more obvious then the <hi>practiſe</hi> to inſnare and illaqueate tender Conſciences by this Covenant; firſt, compelling them to take it; afterwards, conjuring them by it to a falſe <hi>Obſequium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who knows not that an unlawfull oath or Covenant, is better broken then kept: Therefore juſtifie the <hi>matter</hi> of the Oath and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, or the <hi>Bond</hi> will diſſolve it ſelfe. If the Parliament (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is charg'd very boldly, I ſay not preſumptuouſly upon them) have taken an oath to doe an unlawfull act, they muſt not be ſtirred up to that act in purſuance of that oath and Covenant. Therefore firſt make good this, that 'tis their <hi>duty</hi> to proſecute all different Brethren, elſe in charging a Covenant (ſo to doe) upon them, you lay a ſnare which the foote of ſo judicious a Parliament will not be held by.</p>
                  <p>But not to compound the matter thus: We cannot yeeld you that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:158553:39"/>ſenſe you put upon the Covenant: Nor will any expreſſion or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions therein, conſidered in their ſeverall <hi>place</hi> and <hi>relation,</hi> amount to ſuch a verdict as you give in moſt confidently: If they ſhould, as I muſt confeſſe then, that I was deceived, and ſo ſhall hold my ſelfe obliged in no other ſenſe, then I underſtood it when I took it; So I ſhall profeſſe my deſire to repent of my raſhneſſe in taking it, though I did it without the leaſt appearance to my beſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of any contradiction to my principles.</p>
                  <p>To come to the Teſt therefore, there are foure clauſes in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant urged againſt this liberty; (for a toleration wee owne not, <hi>permiſſio non eſt niſi peccati,</hi> and 'tis in ſuch matters wherein the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is authorized, nay is bound to reſtraine, which here I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive he is not, without prejudice to his juſt greatneſſe.)</p>
                  <p>The firſt clauſe is of <hi>Endeavouring the reformation of Religion, in the Kingdomes of England and Ireland, in Doctrine, Worſhip, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Diſcipline, according to the example of the beſt reformed Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond Clauſe is of <hi>Endeavouring to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes to the neareſt conjunction and uniformity in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Confeſſion of Faith, Forme of Church-Government, Directory for Worſhip, and Catechizing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third; <hi>That wee ſhall in like manner, without reſpect of perſons, endeavour the extirpation of Schiſme, and what ever ſhall be found con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to ſound doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe, leſt we partake of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſinnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fourth and laſt, is the <hi>Endeavouring of the diſcovery of ſuch as have been evill Inſtruments, by hindring reformation of Religion, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any faction, or parties among the people, contrary to this league and Covenant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall firſt take ſome Exceptions to the manner,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     </note> and then anſwer to the matter of this Objection: and becauſe there is more <hi>ill man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> in it then <hi>ſtrong matter,</hi> therefore the firſt part of my Anſwer will be longeſt.</p>
                  <p>The manner is full of exception, as rendring the Author and ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thus, guilty of <hi>Partiality, Tautology, ſubornation of ſenſe, diſ-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the State, and want of love to the Brethren.</hi> This charge I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lay nor proſecute againſt him in <hi>Foro externo,</hi> in the Magiſtrates Court, but in <hi>Foro Conſcientiae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:158553:40"/>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Partiality,</hi> clipping and partially repreſenting not onely the Parliaments ſenſe, but even the words of the Covenant, (as it he had got up againe the <hi>Index Expurgatorius</hi>) quoting onely the words that make for his own turne, and leaving out what doth and ought to goe along with them. This in two particulars. 1. Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out thoſe words belonging to the firſt Clauſe, <hi>viz. [according to the Word of God,]</hi> which is ſet before the example of the beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, as being the onely patterne and regulation for us and them: and we doe not <hi>jurare in exemplar,</hi> ſweare to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of the beſt reformed Church in the world, further then it ſhall approve it ſelfe by the Scriptures. <hi>Follow me, as I follow Chriſt.</hi> So that ſo far are other Churches from being the onely Rule, that they are not ſo much as a <hi>ſocious</hi> Rule: that is, they goe not in an <hi>aequipage</hi> with, but are <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to the Word, and of a ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary conſideration and imitation after the Word of God: and the leaving out of theſe words, I might well call the <hi>clipping</hi> of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, for it takes away the <hi>Ring</hi> of the Coine (as it were) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the letters of Inſcription (that ſhew whoſe this Covenant is, and who and whoſe we are that make it, and give the ſpecificall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, or characteriſticall diſtinction between it, and a Popiſh im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit faith) are contained. The other particular left out is in the latter end of the Covenant, which yet referres to the whole obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of each perſon reſpectively, <hi>viz.</hi> that he ſhall <hi>by all lawfull wayes and meanes,</hi> and according to his <hi>place and calling,</hi> endeavour to obſerve and performe the tenour of the Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> to bring the Churches to uniformity, and to extirpate ſchiſme: As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, 'tis the godly Magiſtrates duty, their <hi>place and calling,</hi> to ſend forth Miniſters into the darke places of the Land, and to ſet up lights to guide mens feet into the wayes of truth and peace, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them from errours: and he cannot be urged upon his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to puniſh or compell gain-ſayers. And the Miniſters place and calling is to improve his parts and opportunities, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, by exhorting, rebuking, inſtructing, with all long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and doctrine, and he is to goe no further, not to deliver up to the Judge and Executioner. So that here is nothing but fallacy in urging the Covenant thus, in putting men upon that <hi>abſolutely,</hi> which is deſireable and to be proſecuted onely <hi>conditionally,</hi> viz. Conformity to and uniformity with other Churches, if they be in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:158553:40"/>the truth, and it may be done with the Word of God; and fallacy likewiſe in prompting men to doe that <hi>omnibus viis &amp; modis,</hi> as they ſay, which is to be done onely <hi>regularly and orderly,</hi> as every mans calling leads him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Tautology,</hi> which is a conſequent of the former errour; for by leaving out theſe words <hi>[according to the Word of God]</hi> in the firſt Clauſe, he hath deſtroyed its particular nature and diſtinct kinde, and hath made it run into the ſecond Clauſe: that whereas the firſt Clauſe in the Covenant ſounds <hi>reformation,</hi> now as he has maimed it, it ſounds no more then <hi>uniformity,</hi> which makes it the ſame with the ſecond Clauſe, as by comparing the two Clauſes above may be ſeene.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Subornation of ſenſe,</hi> and that in theſe particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the <hi>neareſt</hi> conjunction in his ſecond Clauſe, to be an <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute</hi> conjunction and <hi>identity.</hi> If we be agreed of the ſame Church-Officers with the reformed Churches, and have caſt out the old u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers as they have done, if we have caſhier'd the common-Prayer-Booke as they, and all the fooliſh Ceremonies, and Organ-pipes, and Copes, and Veſtments, and diſtinction of places, diſplaced our Altars, broken our painted glaſſe and Crucifixes (all which have been done but ſince this Parliament, and upon this Covenant many of them.) Now I ſay, if this be the <hi>neareſt</hi> conjunction, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, which the Word of God in the Interpretation of our Conſciences, will allow; doe wee not ſave our Covenant, though we caſt not our Churches into ſuch Claſſicall, Provinciall and Nationall formes of adminiſtration as they? 2. In applying thoſe termes and Clauſes of <hi>[Schiſme and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe, and evill inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, hindering Reformation, making factions, and parties among the people]</hi> unto the Congregationall men: Againſt whom if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament did indeed levell theſe battering Clauſes, I am much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, onely I muſt crave leave to ſay then, 'twas not faire to draw theſe men into a Covenant to deſtroy themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Diſ-ſervice to the State,</hi> in weakning the hands, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the hearts, of ſuch a conſiderable number in the Citie and Kingdome, (who under God and the Parliament, have been the life of this cauſe ſo many wayes) by turning the whole traine of the Covenant againſt them, as if there were no Papiſts nor Malignants
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:158553:41"/>to diſcharge it againſt. And it ſeemes this is but the <hi>birth</hi> of that challenge againſt theſe men (to be the <hi>Sanballat's</hi> and <hi>Tobia's</hi> in this preſent worke and ingagement) which was the <hi>prodromus</hi> ſome moneths agoe. And is it not a great diſ-ſervice to the State, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave or goe about to bereave the Kingdome of the ſtrength of ſo many cordiall perſons, ſervent prayers, willing purſes, brave Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, and valiant Souldiers, which are of this way and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and to doe it at this time when we have need of no ſubdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fions, a common enemy waiting for us both? Could more pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous advice be given with more probable ſucceſſe for ruine then this, to divide the ſound party among themſelves? I call not this <hi>diſ-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> to the State, (for truly I judge not ſo of the man, but that he ſpake &amp; wrote herein he knew not what, nor of what conſequence) but certainly the greateſt <hi>diſ-ſervice</hi> to the State it is, that a man of no greater intereſt and influence could doe. I call not for Juſtice, but for Repentance.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the higheſt breach of love and charity is this that could be, to apply the fore-mentioned termes and things to this ſort of men: as let all the world, or any indifferent man that is not baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame ſpirit of gall and wormewood, conſider and judge.</p>
                  <p>Now to the matter of the Objection (avoyding what might be returned) that the Covenant may with as faire a conſtruction, &amp; as genuine and unforc't an interpretation, be urged againſt the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> and for the Congregationall way as otherwiſe.) I anſwer briefly thus; That the Covenant binds no man, nor number of men, no State or Church, for their parts reſpectively, to any patterne or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Reformation, Conformity, or Uniformity with other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: but what ſhall <hi>ſatisfactorily</hi> to them and each of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, <hi>appeare to be according to the Word of God:</hi> And ſuch a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation do the Congregationall men deſire, pray, preach, endeavour for and after, (therefore are no <hi>enemies to Reformation,</hi> as is alledged by the Objecter) in purſuance of their Covenant, as they ſhould and would have done, if there had been no ſuch outward Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant obliging them. I will not feare to appeale to you: would we have men driven in droves to the Sacrament ſtill, and the precious and the vile commixed together? Would we have idle drones and Idoll Shepheards ſuffered in Congregations, and the darke places of the Land remaine ſtill <hi>full of cruelty?</hi> Would we have the Biſhops
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:158553:41"/>Courts and Conſiſtories continue? Nay, had theſe ever been downe, if we had not under God, as a forlorne hope, firſt given them bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell? How then have you the face to ſay, wee <hi>hinder Reformation,</hi> when wee are for a further and purer Reformation (your ſelves being Judges?) You would ſit downe on this ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> we would advance, not onely ſo far with you, but paſſe over <hi>Jordan:</hi> how then doe we hinder you? Sit you quiet if you will not helpe us as we have helped you; and doe not ſay (to help your ſelves and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe your owne ingratitude) that we are <hi>enemies to Reformation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe are the moſt materiall and obvious Objections that I have met withall, and could gather in with either ſenſe, my eye or eare: Onely there is a paſſage in the <hi>Antapology,</hi> that I muſt give an Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſion upon, <hi>viz. That by vertue of many Scriptures both in the Old and New Teſtament, the example of the Kings of Judah, &amp;c. The Parliament is bound to eſtabliſh, and to command obedience to that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation which is judged</hi> (to wit, by the preſent Synod) <hi>moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Word, and to ſuppreſſe and hinder all other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now theſe places <hi>in the New Teſtament</hi> (I confeſſe) made me li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten: (for of the old Teſtament and Now, there is not <hi>eadem ratio,</hi> nor of the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> and of <hi>England,</hi> as hath been ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) but if the New Teſtament conclude us under ſuch an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we are gone. I turned to the places quoted, and ſhall deſire no more of any man, but to turne to them, and ſatisfie himſelfe. The Scriptures are, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22 2 <hi>Epiſt. Joh.</hi> 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt of them, I have already prevented it, and ſhewed that it aſſignes deeds and workes to the Magiſtrates Cognizance, not opinions in Religion.</p>
                  <p>For the next, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11. <hi>And have no fellowſhip with the unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full works of darkneſſe, but rather reprove them.</hi> It is nothing more then an admonition to all Chriſtians, in as much as they are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light, to have no fellowſhip with the ſinnes before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that Chapter, fornication, uncleanneſſe, covetouſneſſe, &amp;c. But what is this to different opinions, or to the Magiſtrates act of ſuppreſſing ſuch.</p>
                  <p>For the third place, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no man, neither be partaker of other mens ſinnes; keepe thy ſelfe pure:</hi> It is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and all ſuch whom it may concerne, that are
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:158553:42"/>called to lay hands and ordaine Officers, that they ordaine onely worthy men. This reaches not yet the Magiſtrate, nor within a mile of him.</p>
                  <p>For the fourth place; 2 <hi>Epiſt. Joh.</hi> 10.11. (for I will give him a verſe more then he quotes, and yet not feare the cauſe) <hi>If there come any unto you, and bring not this doctrine, receive him not into your houſe, nor bid him God-ſpeed. For he that biddeth him God-ſpeed, is partaker of his evill deeds.</hi> Firſt, this is written to a <hi>Lody,</hi> not to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; then he requires onely a <hi>Negative</hi> of her, <hi>viz.</hi> not to be a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker by any countenance, but he requires not to proſecute ſuch a one. We muſt not <hi>receive</hi> ſuch <hi>into our houſes,</hi> but muſt we therefore <hi>caſt them out of their owne houſes,</hi> or native Countrey, or put than into the priſon-houſe? And who are thus to be ſhook off and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced? Why, <hi>whoſoever brings not this doctrine,</hi> that is, if he bring <hi>another</hi> doctrine, as it is <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.5. <hi>another Goſpel</hi> that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes this; Not if he differ in the underſtanding of ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trovertible place. Now doe not thoſe men againſt whom this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is urged, bring this doctrine with them in as pure and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a diſcovery of it as others? Becauſe they differ in point of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, doe they ſet up another Goſpel? If you judge ſo: then bid them not God-ſpeed: but yet God doth not bid you ſpeed them out of the Land.</p>
                  <p>For the fifth and laſt place, 2 <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Notwithſtanding I have a few things againſt thee, becauſe thou ſuffereſt that woman Jezabel, who calleth her ſelfe a Propheteſſe, to teach and to ſeduce my ſervants to commit fornication, &amp;c.</hi> Now will you ſee who and what ſhee was that was ſuffered, both a ſtrumpet, and a diabolicall inſtrument of ſeduction, and that to fornication; (here was <hi>fact,</hi> as well as <hi>faith,</hi>) and to eat things ſacrificed to Idols: and will you conſider likewiſe by whom ſhee was ſuffered, by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> 'tis ſhee is blamed or her <hi>Angel,</hi> and ſure what ever Church ſhould retaine or ſuffer ſuch a Member without the application of the <hi>cenſures</hi> to her, deſerve an Epiſtle from Heaven, to be written unto them in <hi>bloud:</hi> and ſuch a Member may be no wayes ſheltred under any Church relation, from the <hi>ſword</hi> of the Magiſtrate.</p>
                  <p>Thus you have heard theſe Witneſſes ſpeake, what thinke yee? doe they ſpeake to the purpoſe for which they are brought? Doth it appeare by theſe places in the New Teſtament, that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:158553:42"/>is bound to ratifie the Decrees of the preſent Synod, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt all that vary from them with ſevere puniſhment? Or is it not rather as the old Proverb; <hi>Parturiunt, Montes naſcetur ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous mus: Mountaines in expectation, bring forth mice in the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?</hi> The neareſt-ſounding Scripture, and but in ſound, is that to <hi>Timothy, Lay hands ſuddenly on no man;</hi> But if he might eaſily mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake a <hi>Biſhop</hi> for a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> yet ſure there's a great deale of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>laying hands,</hi> and <hi>laying no hands;</hi> and 'tis a <hi>Non-ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur</hi> that would be hiſt at in the Schooles; <hi>The Biſhop muſt not ordaine every one that is offer'd: Ergo, the Magiſtrate muſt order every one that differs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I know upon the laſt Scripture, <hi>viz. Rev.</hi> 2.20. he will thinke he has a good ground to ſtate his <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Coercive</hi> power at leaſt; For that Chriſt deales with the <hi>Angel,</hi> and charges him with ſuffering <hi>Jezabel,</hi> therefore if there be not a Civill power, yet there is at leaſt an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall power</hi> to deale with ſeducers. Now for ſuch as ſhee, 1. We have before granted that an Eccleſiaſt call power is <hi>not ſufficient</hi> to deale withall, but the Civill Magiſtrate is alſo to intereſt himſelſe. 2. That there is a <hi>Church-power</hi> to deale with men in point of faith as well as fact, I deny not, though I ſtate it not where the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> doe, that is, not in a <hi>Combination of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> but in a <hi>particular Church:</hi> (for Chriſt doth not threaten the Angels of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Smyrna</hi> for <hi>Thyatira's</hi> fault, who yet all did belong to one <hi>Regionall,</hi> though not to one <hi>Claſſicall Presbytery:</hi> Nor doe I ſtate it in the <hi>Elderſhip</hi> alone, but within the whole body. For though the Epiſtle be directed to the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> yet 'tis intended (as all the others are) to the <hi>whole body;</hi> which appeares clearly out of the Epiſtles themſelves: Not onely that what is written to the <hi>Angel,</hi> is of concernment to the Church, but is <hi>written to the Church.</hi> For is it written to the Officer onely, <hi>I know thy workes, and charity, and ſervice, and faith, and thy patience, and thy workes, and the laſt to be more then the firſt,</hi> or is it ſaid to the body of the Church? To whom (be it one or more) this is ſaid, to him or them is it ſaid in the next verſe, <hi>Notwithſtanding I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what againſt thee, &amp;c.</hi> If it be the Church that is commended for her workes, and charity, &amp;c. then it is the <hi>Church</hi> alſo, that is here bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for not exerciſing the power committed to her againſt <hi>Jezabel.</hi> So likewiſe the Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> is directed to the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:158553:43"/>Angel, but is the Angel onely ſpoken to in the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>verſe, Feare none of thoſe things that thouſhalt ſuffer, behold the Deviall ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon?</hi> And ſo I might inſtance in the other Churches. But that generall Proclamation ſhall ſerve to evince it, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every Epiſtle; <hi>Let him that hath an eare heare what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches:</hi> Not to the Angel onely, but <hi>to the Churches.</hi> It is <hi>ſent firſt</hi> to the Angel, as a <hi>principall part</hi> of the Church, whoſe Office alſo it is to <hi>receive</hi> from Chriſt, and to <hi>communicate</hi> to the Church. Therefore when Chriſt ſayes, <hi>I have ſomething againſt thee,</hi> he meanes againſt the Church for ſuffering <hi>Jezabel.</hi> So that as wee have found an Eccleſiaſticall power, ſo we have found for the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of its in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eſion,</hi> a particular Church or body; and for the <hi>object of its application,</hi> its own members, as <hi>Jezabel</hi> was. But now for <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> a <hi>particular</hi> Church, and there is no other <hi>miniſtring Church</hi> hath onely the power of <hi>ſubſtraction,</hi> withdrawing from them, or rejecting them; <hi>A man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject;</hi> which is an act, whereby a Church or a Member <hi>reſerves</hi> themſelves, exerciſes not any power over others. In practiſe of which Rule, as a light to the underſtanding of it, Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory furniſhes us with the Inſtances of the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quod apud Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſum, cum Balneas lava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di gratia fulſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet ingreſſus, &amp; vidiſſet ibi Cerin: hum, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilucrit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuò non lotus, &amp; diſceſſerit, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens, Fugianus bincne &amp; Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ncae ipſae corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, in quibus Cerinthus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatur, verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis inimicus. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem etiam ipſe Polycarpus Marcioni ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do cum oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curriſſet, dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſibi Agnoſce nos, Agnoſco (inquit) pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenitum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanae.</hi> Euſeb. lib. 4. cap. 14.</note> Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> profeſſedly avoyding the ſociety of Hereticks; but not exerciſing any power over them, or againſt them.</p>
                  <p>And this <hi>law</hi> of <hi>Church-Diſcipline</hi> is conſonant and harmonicall to <hi>right reaſon,</hi> and to the Rule of <hi>Civill</hi> adminiſtration: Where a man is tryed by his <hi>Peeres:</hi> and 'tis fit he ſhould be ſo in ſpirituall things judged by his <hi>fellow-members.</hi> And there is no reaſon or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, in ſubjecting a Church or member to a <hi>foraine juriſdiction.</hi> Adviſed and <hi>conſulted</hi> with, other Churches may be, ought to be, the nature of the caſe for weight, difficulty, and difference re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it.</p>
                  <p>But to come to the buſineſſe. There be two branches of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns (the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>) claime. The one is power of <hi>judging,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining, impoſing doctrines, and concluſions upon all men and Churches. 2. The other a power of <hi>tranſmitting,</hi> and delivering o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the Magiſtrate, and ſtirring up his power in caſe of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to them.</p>
                  <p>Now for the firſt of theſe, in vaine is it ſaid, <hi>Try all things,</hi> if a Synod may impoſe: For either the tryall relates to a <hi>particular
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:158553:43"/>judgement</hi> to be made, and that judgement to a <hi>practiſe</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, or not; If not, as good not try, if I try onely for <hi>tryall ſake,</hi> and if when I have tryed I am but where I was, to wit, I muſt be <hi>concluded</hi> by others vote and impoſition; If yea, then to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is the impoſition? for if I <hi>approve</hi> it, the impoſition is <hi>needleſſe,</hi> if I <hi>reject,</hi> 'tis <hi>fruitleſſe.</hi> 2. They that have right and power of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, are <hi>Lords of my Faith;</hi> but ſo are not any men, the Apoſtles themſelves aſſumed it not: <hi>For by faith yee ſtand.</hi> Take away a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>judicious faith,</hi> you take away his legs, his <hi>ſtanding</hi> from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. 3. In vaine did the <hi>Bereans</hi> try the Apoſtles doctrine, and unduely were they commended, if that doctrine were impoſed upon them. 4. If yee <hi>Presbytery</hi> have power to impoſe doctrines, then they muſt have power of <hi>Excommunication</hi> over all thoſe on whom they impoſe: For power of <hi>commanding,</hi> without power of <hi>revenging</hi> diſobedience, is a ridiculous ſhadow and image of power. It is like <hi>Jupiters</hi> leg, ſent downe to be the King of Frogges, which they <hi>leapt upon</hi> and ſcorned. But this power of Excommunicating, we have found a <hi>proper</hi> ſeat and ſubject for it already, even a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, and till our Brethren ſhew out of Scripture, a <hi>ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Churches,</hi> I need ſay no more; and if they doe that, then I will ſay with them.</p>
                  <p>For the other branch, <hi>inſtigating</hi> the Magiſtrate, which is not to be underſtood of tranſmitting ſuch things to him as doe <hi>pertinere ad mores,</hi> (wherein he is of himſelfe conſcious of his duty and obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and needs no inſtigation) but of things pertaining properly to <hi>Conſcience.</hi> In which caſes, as Miniſters are not inſtructed with any <hi>externall</hi> force and power to be exerciſed by themſelves againſt men; ſure alſo they ought not <hi>ſevire per alios,</hi> to ſtirre up the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate againſt them. For the Office of the Miniſtery beares no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>temporall</hi> puniſhment. The Magiſtrate is properly <hi>the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God for wrath;</hi> but it is fit for Miniſters to ſay as Chriſt,
<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 9.56.</note> 
                     <hi>I am not come to deſtroy, but to ſave alive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is a reaſon given for the Office of a <hi>Ruling Elder</hi> in the Church, added to the <hi>Teaching Elders,</hi> namely, to avoyd the prejudice and <hi>Odium</hi> that would fall upon the Miniſtry, ſhould they diſcharge that part which is a <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>ſevere</hi> Office; as being to inquire into the converſations of the flock, and each member, and to obſerve their faults, in manners, and otherwayes, and deale roundly with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:158553:44"/>them therein, laying the <hi>axe</hi> of ſevere reproofe to the <hi>roote</hi> of every ſinne. Now if this be a worke of that nature, that God in his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath priviledg'd the Miniſtry from, leſt it might make their <hi>perſons,</hi> and ſo their <hi>doctrine</hi> leſſe acceptable, (the Miniſtry having need to be like <hi>one that has a pleaſant voice, and can play well on an Inſtrument</hi>) and in conſideration hereof, hath for this work found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>diſtinct</hi> Office in his Church; ſhall we thinke thoſe Miniſters provide wiſely for themſelves, and the acceptance of their Miniſtry, that will thruſt themſelves into a <hi>more diſ-affecting</hi> Office, namely, to be <hi>Promoters, Tell-tales, Appparitors,</hi> or <hi>Summoners</hi> to the Civill Magiſtrates Courts? We know how apt men are to receive the truth in <hi>reſpect of perſons:</hi> Miniſters had not need then, to incurre <hi>needleſſe</hi> prejudice. We know how Miniſters <hi>perſonall</hi> faults, make their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to be loathed, ſleighted, and diſ-eſteemed. Ile never heare him, ſays one, he is an <hi>uſurer;</hi> and of another, he is very <hi>worldly,</hi> and covetous; There is indeed an uncomelineſſe more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in the <hi>match</hi> of ſuch vices with ſuch a calling: <hi>High talke becomes not a foole</hi> (ſays <hi>Solomon:</hi>) and is not this as deepe and effectuall an exception againſt a Miniſter, Oh, he is a <hi>cruell</hi> man, he made ſuch a <hi>poore</hi> man <hi>fined,</hi> and he cauſed ſuch a one to be <hi>caſt in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> for a little difference in opinion, when they agreed in the maine, <hi>and his wife and children were ready to ſtarve the while?</hi> (Will not this bring the curſe of the poore ſuffering Families upon them?) And he is a <hi>proud</hi> man, he will breake the backe of any, that will not be <hi>of his mind?</hi> Oh how doth this prejudice the <hi>wholeſome</hi> truths that ſuch men may deliver? And how farre are thoſe Miniſters that give ſuch occaſion, and with whom ſuch conſiderations prevaile nothing, from <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit and temper, who that he might create the greater opportunity to himſelfe among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> would not uſe that power that he had of <hi>living upon them,</hi> and being bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome to them: and <hi>content</hi> himſelfe with a fallacy,
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.14.</note> 
                     <hi>That the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers muſt lay up for their children:</hi> ſo carefull was he even to <hi>over-doe,</hi> in removing prejudices that might be (though <hi>not juſtly</hi>) in carnall minds againſt his doctrine.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, We have
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sed nemo ad Regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſti aruditoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norat, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num non adveniſſe in hunc mundum, ut eſſet Legis &amp; gladii, ſed gratiae tantum &amp; Evangelii Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; praedicaret<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> onmibus peccatorum poenitentiam, &amp; remiſsionem; non afficeret ſuppliciit flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſos.</hi> Martin Bucer. de Regno Chriſti. l. 2. c. 33. upon the place.</note> Chriſts example, that would not have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:158553:44"/>his duty, nor could no more when he was <hi>made under the law,</hi> diſpenſe with it, then we can with ours; for he came <hi>to fulfill all righteouſneſſe.</hi> When they brought to him the Woman taken in the act of adultery; they that apprehended her, were there to witneſſe it: Chriſt doth not now <hi>accuſe</hi> her to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> nor doth he bid them to doe it, but he doth what was fit for a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> a bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of good things to doe: He <hi>exhorts</hi> her to <hi>repent, Goe and ſinne no more.</hi> And did he omit the proceeding againſt her out of incogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance or forgetfulneſſe? No; for he ſays, <hi>Hath no man accuſed thee?</hi> Shee anſwered, no; <hi>Neither doe I,</hi> ſays Chriſt, onely <hi>goe and ſinne no more.</hi> I know Chriſt got an <hi>ill name</hi> by this, <hi>The friend of Publicans and ſinners,</hi> but he cared not for that, he went as far as his office led him, and he advanced his Fathers buſines by that carriage.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, it is a Rule which I have obſerved in <hi>prudent</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, not to encourage their <hi>children</hi> to informe of one anothers faults, (but let the <hi>ſervants</hi> doe it) becauſe it doth not nouriſh love, but <hi>diſ-affects</hi> them towards one another: and it is a good Rule, which we ought to obſerve in this <hi>higher</hi> relation, between <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>people,</hi> which ſhould be carried with all the <hi>freeneſſe</hi> that may be.</p>
                  <p>NOw if there be light in the things that have been brought, and that they conclude for a <hi>greater</hi> liberty then
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Viz.</hi> The Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
                     <hi>ſome Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> want, I hope you will ſave them the labour of <hi>asking</hi> their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty at your hands. Not that we ſhall thinke them <hi>hard</hi> termes to <hi>aske and have,</hi> or that we would not be <hi>beholden</hi> to you. If you will have it of <hi>grace as well</hi> as debt, or <hi>not of debt,</hi> wee are content ſo to receive it. We acknowledge it is of the <hi>Lords free grace</hi> and mercy that wee enjoy <hi>that</hi> liberty that wee doe, that wee have enjoyed it <hi>thus long,</hi> as it were a breathing ſpace: and that our Parliament are not as
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 25.17.</note> 
                     <hi>ſons of Belial, that a man cannot ſpeak unto;</hi> Nay, far enough from that, <hi>great is our boldneſſe towards you,</hi> and <hi>our hearts are inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,</hi> both to you and for you. Wee never goe before the throne of grace, but we carry you in our <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>prayers</hi> along with us, and preſent you together with our ſelves in theſe <hi>works</hi> and <hi>labours</hi> of yours; and are full of hope, that God who hath concurr'd with you thus far, and acted you to ſo many worthy and memorable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of ſervice to him and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, hath not concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:158553:45"/>that <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> againſt both <hi>you</hi> and <hi>us,</hi> as to reſerve your <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Counſels to <hi>ſhut</hi> that doore of Chriſtian liberty that was <hi>firſt opened</hi> to us by your meanes. And let it not be imputed to us as <hi>arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance,</hi> if in the day wherein our ſelves are but <hi>Probationers,</hi> our Principles ſpeake for <hi>others</hi> as well as our ſelves. Common <hi>humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> requires if there be a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a <hi>redundancy</hi> of any thing whereby we may profit others alſo, that we ſhould extend the <hi>overplus</hi> unto them, and that it ſhould not run out to <hi>loſſe:</hi> But <hi>the Royall Law</hi> of love commands us <hi>not to ſeeke our own things, but every one his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers weale,</hi> and to ſerve them <hi>before</hi> our ſelves, accounting it a <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſed thing</hi> to be <hi>inſtruments</hi> of their reſt and peace, then to <hi>injoy</hi> our owne. We ſhall bleſſe God, if he ſhall [ſo far clear] <hi>us and our way</hi> in your thoughts: but our peace and liberty will not fall with that <hi>rich and full</hi> contentment into our boſomes, except all that walke <hi>conſcientiouſly</hi> and <hi>inoffenſively,</hi> may injoy the ſame with us. <hi>Now he who is the Father of lights, from whom comes downe every good and perfect gift, fill you with wiſdome and ability to diſcerne between the intereſts of man, and mans greatneſſe, and the intereſts of God and his glory, that you may adminiſter rightly in this matter, as in all things; that we may have more and more cauſe to bleſſe God for thoſe quiet and peaceable lives we lead under you, in all godlineſſe and boneſty: and that the Lord when be comes may find you</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 12.43.</note> ſo <hi>doing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
